. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYBODY.
WELCOME TO THE JULY 29TH 2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO
AND GAUDIO PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER PRESENT SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAHMATULLAH LONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA.
AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAM OFFICIAL OWNING HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY.
AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING
ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL AND COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN
RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE PLEDGING ALLEGIANCE
TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE
REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD,
INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR ALL.
>> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
AT US OF GOTV TODAY ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE THE
TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE.
MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO ATTEND THIS MEETING HERE IN THE
BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER IN THE SECOND FLOOR ROOM TO 50
OF CITY HALL. OR YOU MAY WATCH THE PROCEEDING
ON SRF GEO TV'S CHANNEL 26 OR VIEW THE LIVE STREAM AT W WW
DOT S.F. GEO VTV.ORG. IF YOU HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT THAT
YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT TO THE BOARD SEND AN EMAIL TO B O S AT
S.F. GOV DOT ORG. OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE
AND JUST ADDRESS YOUR ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. THE NUMBER ONE DOCTOR CARLTON B
GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA 94102
TWO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION REQUEST UNDER THE
AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE
ASSISTANCE. CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT
LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE AND YOU CAN CALL
(415) 554-5184. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. >> APPROVAL OF THE JUNE 24TH
2025 REGULAR BOARD MEETING MINUTES AND THE JUNE 25TH JUNE
25TH 2025 SPECIAL MEETING MINUTES AT THE BUDGET
AND APPROPRIATIONS COMMITTEE MEETING WHICH CONSTITUTED A
QUORUM OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> COLLEAGUES CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES
AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHAN SECONDED BY WALTON.
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND GUARDIAN EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR
CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY
DORSEY I. >> THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT TO AGENDA
ITEMS ONE THROUGH 23 ITEMS ONE THROUGH 23 ARE ON CONSENT.
THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE.
IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED
SEPARATELY. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH 23 SUPERVISOR AND AUDIO
AND GUARDIAN EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MIDDLEMAN EYES
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EITHER R.A. LEBANESE OR WITHOUT
OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED AND THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
UNFINISHED BUSINESS. >> PLEASE CALL ITEM 24.
ITEM 24 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
TO EXPAND THE SCOPE EXCUSE ME OF EMERGENCY PROCUREMENT
PROVISIONS FOR GOODS AND SERVICES AND TO ALLOW CITY
DEPARTMENTS TO MODIFY AGREEMENTS IN WAYS NOT
CONTEMPLATED IN THE ORIGINAL SOLICITATION.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 25 ITEM 25 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
APPROVE HEALTH SERVICES ITEM PLANS AND CONTRIBUTION RATES
FOR CALENDAR YEAR 2026 JUST PURSUANT TO THE CHARTER THIS
MATTER REQUIRES NINE VOTES OF ALL MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO APPROVE FOR PASSAGE TODAY.
>> AND AGAIN WE'LL TAKE THE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 26.
>> ITEM 26 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO SETTLE THE LAWSUIT FILED BY
ARCHDIOCESE OF SAN FRANCISCO PARISH AND SCHOOL JURIDIQUE
PERSONS REAL PROPERTY SUPPORT CORPORATION AGAINST THE CITY
AND COUNTY FOR $248,000. THIS INVOLVES ALLEGED PROPERTY
DAMAGE AND ECONOMIC LOSSES ARISING FROM FLOODING CAUSED BY
A WATER TRANSMISSION PIPELINE BREAK.
SUPERVISOR CHANCE SPOKE LAST TIME TO DISCLOSE THAT SHE DOES
NOT BELIEVE THAT SHE HAS A CONFLICT AND WE CAN THEREFORE
TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
27 AND 28 ITEMS 27 AND 28 ARE TWO ORDINANCES THAT WAIVE THE
COMPETITIVE SOLICITATION REQUIREMENTS UNDER CHAPTERS 14
B AND 21 OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE FOR THE POLICE
DEPARTMENT'S PROCUREMENT OF EQUIPMENT TECHNOLOGY
AND SERVICES. ITEM 27 SUPPORTS THE
DEPARTMENT'S RTI SEE THE REAL TIME INVESTIGATION CENTER
UTILIZING GIFT FUNDS RECEIVED FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
COMMUNITY FOUNDATION. AND ITEM 28 IS FOR THE REGIONAL
VEHICLE INTERDICTION DESK USING GRANT FUNDS FROM THE UNITED
STATES DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE BUREAU OF JUSTICE ASSISTANCE.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT.
COLLEAGUES TODAY ARE BEING ASKED TO APPROVE OVER $9
MILLION OF IN-KIND GIFTS AND WAIVE COMPETITIVE BIDDING
REQUIREMENTS TO EXPAND THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT'S
REAL TIME INVESTIGATION CENTER. >> THESE FOUR ITEMS RANGE FROM
PRIVATE TECH DONATIONS TO SURVEILLANCE SOFTWARE
AND DRONES. >> I WILL BE VOTING NO ON ALL
FOUR ITEMS RELATED TO THE EXPANSION OF THE REAL TIME
INVESTIGATIONS CENTER FOR THE POLICE.
>> WHILE PUBLIC SAFETY IS A PRIORITY THAT I SHARE.
WE NEED TO ALSO CONSIDER THE LONG TERM IMPLICATIONS THAT
COME WITH EXPANDING SURVEILLANCE INFRASTRUCTURE
ESPECIALLY WHEN IT'S FUNDED BY PRIVATE DONATIONS DEVELOPED
WITH MINIMAL REFORMS OF OVERSIGHT AND ADVANCED THROUGH
WAIVERS OF OUR CITY'S COMPETITIVE BIDDING PROCESS.
>> JUST THIS YEAR ALONE WE LEARNED THAT AS OF ILLEGALLY
SHARE DATA FROM AUTOMATIC LICENSE PLATE READERS WITH OUT
OF STATE LAW ENFORCEMENT INCLUDING AGENCIES THE AT THE
FEDERAL LEVEL THIS IS A CLEAR VIOLATION OF OUR CITY'S
SANCTUARY LAWS AND A DIRECT. >> SORRY THIS IS POTENTIALLY A
VIOLATION OF OUR CITY'S SANCTUARY LAWS AS WE HAVE NO
CONTROL OVER THOSE FEDERAL AGENCIES AND WHAT DATA THEY
SHARE WITH ICE. THIS ALSO PRESENTS A DIRECT
THREAT TO CIVIL LIBERTIES OF ALL IMMIGRANT RESIDENTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> I WANT TO REAFFIRM THAT WE
ARE A SANCTUARY CITY AND ANY INVESTMENTS IN SURVEILLANCE
THAT WE CANNOT GUARANTEE HAVE STRONG GUARDRAILS RISKS
UNDERMINING OUR SANCTUARY PROMISE TOOLS LIKE DRONES, DATA
SOFTWARE AND LICENSE PLATE TRACKING MAY BE CRIME FIGHTING
ASSETS. >> BUT WE ALSO HAVE TO EVALUATE
THOSE BENEFITS AGAINST THE RISKS TO OUR COMMUNITIES.
>> THESE MEASURES DEEPEN OUR RELIANCE ON PRIVATELY FUNDED
LAW ENFORCEMENT EQUIPMENT AND IT RAISES CONCERNS ABOUT
ACCOUNTABILITY AND TRANSPARENCY .
FOR THESE REASONS ESPECIALLY FOR THE POTENTIAL HARMS
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES AND CIVIL LIBERTIES, I CANNOT SUPPORT
THIS EXPANSION. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 27 AND 28 ON ITEMS 27
AND 28. SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO IN GAUDIO
I SUPERVISOR FIELDER. FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
I SUPERVISOR WALTON MOULTON NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS FIELDER
AND WALTON VOTING NO THE AUDIENCES ARE FINALLY PASSED
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 29 AND 30 TOGETHER ITEM 29
AND 30 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT APPROVE IN-KIND GIFTS TO
SUPPORT THE POLICE DEPARTMENT'S REAL TIME INVESTIGATION CENTER
ITEM 29 RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE POLICE
DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND AN IN-KIND GIFT OF OFFICE SPACE
FROM REPLY LABS INC VALUED AT 2.1 MILLION THROUGH DECEMBER
31ST 2026 ITEM 30 RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE POLICE
DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND GIFTS OF EQUIPMENT, SERVICES
AND FUNDS TOTALING APPROXIMATELY 7.2 MILLION FOR
THE INSTALLATION OF FIBER INTERNET SERVICE PURCHASE OF 12
DOCKS AND DRONES RELATED SOFTWARE AND SERVICES TO DATA
INTEGRATION SOFTWARE AND EMPLOYEE PARKING FEES WITH
THE START DATE OF APRIL 30TH 2025 AND TO AUTHORIZE THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND FUTURE GIFTS FROM
SAN FRANCISCO POLICE COMMUNITY FOUNDATION FOR SUPPORT OF THE
ARTICLE PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 29 AND 30 SUPERVISORS
IN GAUDIO AND GAUDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SORTER
SORTER EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS FIELDER AND WALTON VOTING NO THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 31 ITEM
31 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
TO PROMOTE EQUITABLE ACCESS TO SHELTER AND BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
SERVICES BY PROHIBITING THE CITY FROM SITING A NEW CITY
FUNDED HOMELESS SHELTER TRANSITIONAL HOUSING FACILITY
OR CERTAIN BEHAVIORAL HEALTH RESIDENTIAL CARE AND TREATMENT
FACILITIES COLLECTIVELY CALLED COVERED FACILITIES IN A
NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE THE NEIGHBORHOOD SHARE OF THE CITY
SHELTER AND TRANSITIONAL HOUSING BEDS EXCEED THE
NEIGHBORHOOD SHARE OF THE CITY'S UNSHELTERED PERSONS
AND TO PROHIBIT THE CITY FROM SITING A NEW CITY FUNDED
HOMELESS SHELTER WITHIN 300FT OF AN EXISTING HOMELESS SHELTER
AND TO AUTHORIZE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO WAIVE THESE
PROHIBITIONS UPON A FINDING THAT APPROVING THE COVERED
FACILITY OR HOMELESS SHELTER AT THE PROPOSED LOCATION IS IN THE
PUBLIC INTEREST AND TO PROVIDE THAT THIS ORDINANCE SUNSETS ON
DECEMBER 31ST, 2031. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AND COLLEAGUES I WANT TO BEGIN ON THIS ORDINANCE BY
RECOGNIZING THE STRONG AND UNITED COMMUNITIES SUPPORT
WE JUST SAW OUTSIDE AT A PRESS CONFERENCE STEPS AWAY.
THAT MOMENT UNDERSCORED WHAT THIS LEGISLATION IS REALLY
ABOUT SHOWING THAT SAN FRANCISCO CAN COME TOGETHER
ACROSS NEIGHBORHOODS, BACKGROUNDS AND SECTORS TO
BUILD A SMARTER, FAIRER AND MORE COMPASSIONATE APPROACH
TO HOMELESSNESS. >> WE HEARD FROM LABOR UNIONS,
BUSINESS LEADERS, POLITICAL LEADERS AND COMMUNITY ADVOCATES
MANY OF WHOM HAVE EXPERIENCED FIRSTHAND HOW OUR CURRENT
SYSTEM STRAINS ALREADY BURDENED NEIGHBORHOODS WHILE LEAVING
OTHERS BEHIND. >> THAT'S WHY WE'RE PROUD TO
BRING THIS ORDINANCE FORWARD WITH THE SUPPORT OF A BROAD
AND DIVERSE COALITION WHO ALL AGREE WE NEED A MORE BALANCED
DATA INFORMED SYSTEM OF CARE THAT MEETS PEOPLE WHERE THEY
ARE AND HELPS COMMUNITIES THRIVE.
>> OUR COMMUNITY AND ORGANIZATIONAL SPONSORS
INCLUDE CODE TENDERLOIN, TENDERLOIN.
COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT TENDERLOIN HOUSING CLINIC, SOMA
WEST NEIGHBORS ASSOCIATION, LOWER HILL NEIGHBORHOOD
ALLIANCE THE SAN FRANCISCO DEMOCRATIC COUNTY CENTRAL
COMMITTEE LOCAL 87 SEIU GENDERS UNION LOCAL FIVE UNITED FOOD
AND COMMERCIAL WORKERS UNION UNITE HERE LOCAL TWO HOTEL
AND RESTAURANT WORKERS UNION THE BAY AREA COUNCIL SAN
FRANCISCO CHAMBER OF COMMERCE FORMER TENDERLOIN SUPERVISORS
JANE KIM AND MATT HANEY. >> THEIR SUPPORT UNDERSCORES A
SHARED BELIEF THAT NEIGHBORHOODS DESERVE A VOICE
IN SHAPING HOW SERVICES ARE DELIVERED.
>> AND THAT PARTNERSHIP NOT SURPRISE IS THE PATH TO
SUCCESSFUL SUSTAINABLE SOLUTION.
THIS ORDINANCE REFLECTS THE YEARS OF ADVOCACY, ADVOCACY
AND A COLLECTIVE EFFORT TO STRENGTHEN THE FABRIC OF OUR
MOST IMPACTED COMMUNITIES. >> THE ONE CITY SHELTER ACT IS
ROOTED IN A SIMPLE BUT LONG OVERDUE PRINCIPLE THAT EVERY
NEIGHBORHOOD SHOULD BE PART OF THE SOLUTION AND EVERY SAN
FRANCISCAN SHOULD HAVE ACCESS TO SHELTER AND CARE NO MATTER
WHERE THEY LIVE. >> FOR TOO LONG WE'VE RELIED ON
REACTIVE AND CRISIS DRIVEN PLANNING.
IT'S LED TO A HARMFUL OVERCONCENTRATION IN JUST A FEW
NEIGHBORHOODS WHILE OTHERS HAVE REMAINED SERVICE DESERTS.
>> THIS ORDINANCE AIMS TO BREAK THAT CYCLE.
>> WHAT WE'RE BRINGING FORWARD TODAY IS THE MOST IMPLEMENTABLE
DATA INFORMED VERSION OF THIS POLICY ONE THAT STRENGTHENS
TRANSPARENCY, ALIGNS SERVICES WITH NEED AND ENSURES EARLY
MEANINGFUL COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT.
>> CURRENTLY 75% OF ALL SHELTER IN TRANSITIONAL HOUSING BEDS
ARE CONCENTRATED IN JUST 30 NEIGHBORHOODS OR SORRY IN JUST
EIGHT NEIGHBORHOODS WHILE MORE THAN 1000 UNSHELTERED RESIDENTS
IN THE REMAINING 30 PLUS NEIGHBORHOODS HAVE NO NEARBY
ACCESS TO CARE. >> THAT KIND OF IMBALANCE SENDS
A MESSAGE WHETHER INTENTIONAL OR NOT THAT ONLY A FEW
NEIGHBORHOODS ARE EXPECTED TO SHOULDER THE CITY'S RESPONSE TO
A CITYWIDE CRISIS. >> IT CREATES A DYNAMIC WHERE
NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE THE TENDERLOIN AND SOMA ARE
CARRYING THE WEIGHT WHILE OTHERS ARE LEFT ON THE
SIDELINES. >> THIS ORDINANCE IS ABOUT
ZOOMING OUT, SHIFTING OUR PERSPECTIVE AND ADDRESSING OUR
HOMELESSNESS RESPONSE THROUGH THE LENS OF ONE CITY WHERE
EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD PLAYS A ROLE AND NO COMMUNITY IS LEFT BEHIND
OR ASKED TO DO IT ALONE. >> THIS IS NOT ABOUT DRAWING
LINES BETWEEN NEIGHBORHOODS. >> IT'S ABOUT DRAWING A CIRCLE
THAT BRINGS EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD IN EQUITY ISN'T A ZERO SUM
GAME. WHEN EACH PART OF THE CITY
CONTRIBUTES, THE ENTIRE CITY BECOMES STRONGER, MORE
RESILIENT AND MORE JUST. >> A BUDGET AND FINANCE
COMMITTEE. WE MADE SEVERAL KEY AMENDMENTS
BASED ON FEEDBACK FROM EXPERTS AND PARTNERS TO STRENGTHEN
AND CLARIFY OUR EQUITY FRAMEWORK.
WE CREATED A FIRST OF ITS KIND FAIR SHARE RULE.
NEW CITY FUNDED SHELTERS CAN'T BE PURSUED IN NEIGHBORHOODS
THAT HAVE ALREADY HAVE A HIGHER SHARE OF BEDS THAN THEIR SHARE
OF UNSHELTERED POPULATION. >> UNLESS A WAIVER IS GRANTED
WE WILL ALSO HAVE A 300 FOOT BUFFER BETWEEN NEW SHELTERS TO
AVOID HYPER CLUSTERING AND PRESERVE NEIGHBORHOOD
BALANCE. >> WE HAVE EXPECTATIONS FOR
PROJECTS ALREADY IN THE PIPELINE OR EXEMPTION
EXEMPTIONS FACILITY IS EXPANDING WITHIN EXISTING
FOOTPRINT OR REPLACING CLOSED CLOSED SERVICES IN THE SAME
NEIGHBORHOOD. WE CALL FOR A BIANNUAL EQUITY
ANALYSIS AND REPORTING TO KEEP DECISIONS GROUNDED IN REAL TIME
DATA AND FOR THE FIRST TIME PROVIDE TRANSPARENCY ABOUT
WHERE THE CITY MIGHT BE CONSIDERING SITING SITES.
>> AND WE WROTE A SUNSET DATE FOR 2031 TO ALLOW US TO TEST,
EVALUATE AND ADJUST THIS LEGISLATION OVER TIME.
>> IT'S IMPORTANT TO RECOGNIZE THAT THIS ORDINANCE IS NOT
ABOUT SHIFTING BURDENS. >> IT'S ABOUT FINALLY BUILDING
A BALANCED SYSTEM THAT SERVES ALL SAN FRANCISCANS AND THE
TENDERLOIN. >> WE HAVE 3500 CHILDREN
AND NOT A SINGLE TOY STORE. >> REVITALIZATION CANNOT HAPPEN
WITHOUT BALANCE. >> WE SEE REAL IMPACTS FROM
THIS COME FROM THIS OVERCONCENTRATION ZONE.
BUT THIS LEGISLATION WILL SEND A MESSAGE THAT WE ARE PUTTING
TRUST BACK INTO THE COMMUNITIES OF COLOR IMMIGRANTS, REFUGEES
THAT HAVE SHOULDER THE BURDEN OF RESPONSIBILITY ON THIS
CHALLENGE. FOR TOO LONG.
AND WHEN WE TALK ABOUT REVITALIZATION OF OUR CITY, WE
HAVE TO CONSIDER THE REVITALIZATION OF THESE
NEIGHBORHOODS BECAUSE YOU CANNOT HAVE A DOWNTOWN
REVITALIZATION WITHOUT A TENDERLOIN REVITALIZATION
EITHER. >> LET'S ALSO BE CLEAR THAT
THIS IS A BUDGET DECISION AND A BUDGET REFLECTS OUR VALUES.
>> WE'RE SAYING THAT CITY FUNDS SHOULD FOLLOW UNMET NEED NOT
POLITICAL CONVENIENCE. >> THIS IS HOW WE REBUILD
PUBLIC TRUST, DELIVER PUBLIC OUTCOMES BETTER OUTCOMES
AND TRULY ACT LIKE ONE CITY. >> IN CLOSING, I WANT TO
ACKNOWLEDGE SO MANY PEOPLE WHO HAVE LED IN ENSURING
AND COLLABORATING ON THIS LEGISLATION.
FIRST I WANT TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE DIRECTOR SAM LOGAN
WHO PUT IN HUNDREDS OF HOURS ONTO THIS LEGISLATION AND THOSE
HUNDREDS OF HOURS HAVE RESULTED IN A COLLABORATIVE APPROACH
BRINGING TOGETHER SO MANY DIFFERENT COMMUNITY
STAKEHOLDERS, DEPARTMENTS OFFICES TO COME UP WITH A FIRST
OF ITS KIND FRAMEWORK THAT WE WILL HOPEFULLY PASS TODAY.
>> MY SINCERE THANKS ALSO TO ANNE PIERSON IN THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR HER CLEAR ,STEADY GUIDANCE AND DEEP
COMMITMENT TO BOTH THE LEGAL AND COMMUNITY IMPACTS OF THIS
LEGISLATION. >> I'M GRATEFUL TO NICK MINARD
AND CHRISTINA MILLER FROM THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE
ANALYST'S OFFICE WHOSE RIGOROUS ANALYSIS PROVIDED A STRONG
FOUNDATION FOR EQUITABLE DECISION MAKING.
>> DEEP THANKS TO OUR PARTNERS AT THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
HEALTH, DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING ESPECIALLY DYLAN SNYDER AND LEE COHEN, STAFF PATEL
AND CLAIRE ALTMAN FOR THEIR GUIDANCE, FEEDBACK
AND COMMITMENT TO MAKING THIS FRAMEWORK WORKABLE ON THE
GROUND. >> I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE
MANY NEIGHBORHOOD LEADERS, SERVICE PROVIDERS AND COMMUNITY
PARTNERS WHO HAVE CARRIED THIS VISION FOR YEARS.
YOUR PERSISTENCE AND HIS INSIGHT AND BELIEF IN A MORE
EQUITABLE CITY HAVE SHAPED EVERY PART OF THIS ORDINANCE.
>> AND FINALLY, I WANT TO THANK YOU TO MY COLLEAGUES
SUPERVISORS WALTON, DORSEY, SAUTER AND MELGAR FOR YOUR
EARLY SUPPORT AND SHARED COMMITMENT TO ENSURING OUR
SYSTEM OF CARE REFLECTS OUR CITYWIDE VALUES.
AND IMPORTANTLY, I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR WALTON WHO LED
US AS A BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO UNANIMOUSLY VOTE IN FAVOR OF
GEOGRAPHIC EQUITY EARLIER THIS YEAR.
THIS LEGISLATION WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN POSSIBLE WITHOUT HIS EARLY
ADVOCACY AND CHAMPIONSHIP. >> SO TODAY, COLLEAGUES, WE
HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO BREAK THAT STATUS QUO TO SAY THAT
GEOGRAPHIC EQUITY COMMUNITY PARTNERSHIP AND DATA DRIVEN
PLANNING ARE NOT JUST IDEALS BUT THE NEW STANDARD FOR HOW WE
CARE FOR OUR MOST VULNERABLE. >> THIS ORDINANCE CHARTS A
CLEAR PATH FORWARD ONE THAT DELIVERS SHELTER AND STABILITY
TO THOSE WHO NEED IT MOST. >> BRINGS BALANCE TO
NEIGHBORHOODS THAT HAVE LONG BEEN ASKED TO CARRY TOO MUCH
AND RESTORES TRUST IN OUR CITY'S ABILITY TO LEAD WITH
BOTH COMPASSION AND FAIRNESS. >> I URGE YOUR SUPPORT NOT JUST
FOR THE LEGISLATION BUT FOR A MORE UNITED AND MORE JUST SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR JAN. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENDHAM
AND COLLEAGUES AS I HAVE STATED IN THE COMMITTEE AT THE BUDGET
AND FINANCE COMMITTEE I AGREE WITH SUPERVISOR BELAL MAHMOOD
THAT NEIGHBORHOODS SUCH AS TENDERLOIN AND SODA MARKET HOW
SHOULDER THE BURDEN OF PROVIDING SHELTER AND SERVICES
TO UNHOUSED INDIVIDUALS IN OUR CITY.
THIS HAS RESULTED IN DECADES OF SATURATION OF BLIGHT IN THESE
NEIGHBORHOODS AND THE DATA CONFIRMS THE SATURATION.
THAT'S WHY I HAVE CONTINUED TO SAY I WOULD SUPPORT A
MORATORIUM ON SHELTERS IN CERTAIN NEIGHBORHOODS.
THIS IS A MOMENT OF HUMAN TERRIBLE CRISIS.
OUR CITY NEEDS TO FOCUS ON DELIVERING EQUITABLE SERVICES
FOR THE PEOPLE WHO ARE IN NEED. HAVE FLEXIBILITY TO MEET THE
PUBLIC HEALTH TRENDS AND DEMANDS.
BE A DRUG INTERVENTION SHELTER ,HOUSING OR OTHER SERVICES.
BASED ON THE DATA THAT WE NOW HAVE.
WE HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO UNDERSTAND THE ACTUAL NEEDS OF
AND HOUSE PEOPLE. THEY ARE NOT MONOLITH.
INSTEAD OF SIMPLE PERCENTAGE BY NEIGHBORHOODS WHICH IS WHAT
WE'RE SEEING RIGHT NOW HAS YET TO REALLY DIG DEEP
AND UNDERSTAND. LET'S PROVIDE SOLUTIONS
ACCORDINGLY. HOWEVER, THE LEGISLATION BEFORE
US TODAY DESPITE ITS MANY AMENDMENTS IS BOTH OVERTLY
PRESCRIPTIVE YET NOT PRECISE ENOUGH IN TARGETED SOLUTIONS
AND ONLY SERVES TO FURTHER DIVIDE OUR NEIGHBORHOODS.
I WOULD RATHER SUPPORT A SHELTER MORATORIUM AIM FOR
SATURATED NEIGHBORHOODS AS WE CONTINUE TO SOLVE HOMELESSNESS
CITYWIDE. FOR THIS REASON I WOULD NOT BE
VOTING IN SUPPORT OF THIS LEGISLATION TODAY.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
I WANT TO FIRST APPLAUD MY COLLEAGUES ROSE OR MAHMUD FOR
ALL OF THE WORK THAT HE POURED INTO THIS.
I BELIEVE THIS IS AMBITIOUS LEGISLATION.
I BELIEVE IT'S IMPORTANT AND MUCH NEEDED LEGISLATION
AND ALSO TO EXTEND THAT GRATITUDE TOWARDS THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE FOR THEIR ROLE IN COLLABORATING AND SHAPING
THIS AND MANY OF MY OTHER COLLEAGUES AS WELL OF COURSE
YOU KNOW I WILL BE SUPPORTING THIS YOU KNOW, AS I THINK ABOUT
THIS LEGISLATION I THINK ABOUT IN MY DISTRICT OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS OF LOWER HILL WHERE I INHERITED A SITUATION
WHERE MORE THAN A HALF DOZEN SITES AND SERVICES HAD BEEN
OPENED IN SHORT ORDER DURING THE PANDEMIC AND THERE HAD BEEN
NO YOU KNOW, NO PAUSE TO THINK ABOUT THAT OR TO COORDINATE
THEIR SUCCESS. AND YOU KNOW, LITERALLY JUST
THIS MORNING WALKING THROUGH THAT NEIGHBORHOOD HAD A COUPLE
THAT CAME UP TO ME AND TALKED TO ME ABOUT THIS LEGISLATION
AND AND SHARED THEIR HOPE AND OPTIMISM, OPTIMISM FOR THIS
LEGISLATION BECAUSE IT WILL REQUIRE US TO BE MORE
THOUGHTFUL ABOUT THIS TO ENSURE THAT WE DO NOT OVER CONCENTRATE
SERVICES IN ONE NEIGHBORHOOD BY MANY MEASURES DISTRICT THREE
HAS A SECOND HIGHEST CONCENTRATION OF SERVICES NOW
LARGELY BECAUSE OF THE LAST FIVE YEARS IN LOWER HILL.
SO I BELIEVE THIS IS AGAIN THOUGHTFUL.
I BELIEVE IT'S NEEDED AND I WILL BE SUPPORTING THIS TODAY.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN I'D LIKE TO
START BY THANKING SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR INTRODUCING
AND WORKING TO SHAPE THIS LEGISLATION AND ALSO TO
SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR HIS LEADERSHIP AS A CO-SPONSOR.
I'M PROUD TO ALSO JOIN AS A CO-SPONSOR AND I ONLY APOLOGIZE
THAT A LATE COMMITMENT EARLIER PREVENTED ME FROM BEING ON THE
CITY HALL STEPS TO FOR FOR THE EVENT.
FOR TOO LONG OUR DISTRICTS HAVE SHOULDERED A DISPROPORTIONATE
SHARE OF HOMELESS SERVICES IN DISTRICT SIX.
I'VE SEEN FIRSTHAND HOW CONCENTRATING VULNERABLE
POPULATIONS IN JUST A FEW NEIGHBORHOODS CAN EXACERBATE
RATHER THAN SOLVE MANY OF THE CHALLENGES THAT WE'RE FACING
OVER SATURATION DOESN'T ONLY STRAINED COMMUNITIES I THINK IT
ALSO ERODES PUBLIC SUPPORT FOR THE VERY SERVICES WE NEED TO
BEST ADDRESS THE CHALLENGES FACING VULNERABLE SAN
FRANCISCANS. I THINK THIS ORDINANCE CREATES
A FRAMEWORK FOR A SMARTER, FAIRER SITE SITING SCHEME AND I
THINK DECISIONS THAT ARE GROUNDED IN DATA TRANSPARENCY
AND EARLY COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT WILL SUCCEED BEST.
THESE ARE PRINCIPLES MY CONSTITUENTS HAVE ASKED FOR
AND THEY'RE EMBEDDED IN THIS LEGISLATION.
I WANT TO THANK ESPECIALLY THE MANY DISTRICT SIX RESIDENTS
AND PARTNERS WHO ARE PART OF THIS INCLUDING SOMA WEST
NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION AND THE SOUTHWEST CBD AMONG
OTHERS WHO HAVE ENGAGED ON THIS ISSUE.
THEIR VOICES HELPS TO SHAPE THIS ORDINANCE AND THAT IS
THANKS IN LARGE PART TO THE WILLINGNESS OF ITS AUTHOR TO
LISTEN TO THOSE VOICES AND I REALLY APPRECIATE IT.
SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
I'M PROUD TO SUPPORT THIS AND I THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP
ON IT. >> SUPERVISOR ONE THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MADAM AND I JUST WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
SUPERVISORS DORSEY SOUDER AND MELGAR FOR THEIR
CO-SPONSORSHIP IN BRINGING THIS LEGISLATION FORWARD.
I ALSO WANT TO SEND A SPECIAL THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR MAHMUD
FOR HIS WILLINGNESS TO WORK WITH OTHERS COOPERATIVELY TO
MOVE TOWARDS A SUCCESSFUL AND EQUITABLE WAY TO COMBAT
HOMELESSNESS AND PROVIDE SERVICES FOR OUR UNHOUSED
IN THIS CITY. I DO WANT PEOPLE TO UNDERSTAND
THAT THIS LEGISLATION IS NOT AN ANTI SHELTER STRATEGY
IN CERTAIN COMMUNITIES BUT MORE OF A PRO SE SHELTER
AND HOMELESS SERVICES STRATEGY ACROSS THE CITY AND IN AREAS
THAT HAVE OPPORTUNITY TO PROVIDE MORE SUPPORT.
A LOT OF WORK HAS GONE INTO GETTING HERE AND ALTHOUGH I
DON'T FEEL THIS LEGISLATION HAS THE COMPLETE NECESSARY TEETH TO
GUARANTEE THAT WE HAVE EQUITABLE ACCESS THROUGHOUT SAN
FRANCISCO, IT MOST CERTAINLY IS THE FIRST LEGISLATION OF ITS
KIND AND RECOGNIZES THAT SHELTER AND SERVICES FOR OUR
UNHOUSED POPULATION SHOULD BE IN CLOSE PROXIMITY
AND AVAILABLE FOR ALL. IF WE ARE EVER GOING TO TRULY
ADDRESS THE ROOT CAUSES AND THE ISSUES SURROUNDING HOMELESSNESS
IT'S THAT WE MUST ALL WORK IN UNISON.
THIS IS SOMETHING THAT AFFECTS THIS ENTIRE CITY AND WE SHOULD
ADDRESS IT AS SUCH AND ENSURE THAT NO ONE COMMUNITY IS
OVERWHELMINGLY CHARGED WITH PROVIDING SHELTER AND SERVICES
FOR OUR UNHOUSED COMMUNITY. WE ALL PLAY A ROLE IN GETTING
PEOPLE OFF OF OUR STREETS AND INTO SHELTER.
SO I WANT TO THANK AGAIN EVERYONE WHO WORKED ON THIS
AND FOR EVERYONE COMING TOGETHER COLLABORATIVELY
AND PROUD TO CO-SPONSOR THIS LEGISLATION.
>> SUPERVISOR JEN THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDO MAN.
COLLEAGUES, I THINK WE ALL WANT MEANINGFUL SOLUTION TO
HOMELESSNESS AND OUR COMMUNITY DESERVE A THOUGHTFUL PLANNING,
TRANSPARENT COMMUNICATION, EFFECTIVE STRATEGY, SUPPORTIVE
SERVICES AND HOUSING THAT TRULY HELPS STABILIZE PEOPLE AND PUT
THEM ON A PATH TO SAFER, HEALTHIER AND SUSTAINABLE
HOUSING OPPORTUNITIES. >> FOR MY OWN DISTRICT, EQUITY
MEANS INVESTING IN WRAPAROUND SERVICES AND PERMANENT
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. >> I WOULD LIKE TO SEE A MORE
INVESTMENT IN DEEPLY AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN DISTRICT 11 AND I
WOULD ALSO WELCOME INTERIM USE AT DOE'S AFFORDABLE HOUSING
SITE THAT ALLOW US TO SERVE UNHOUSED NEIGHBORS
AND HOPEFULLY TRANSITION THEM INTO A PERMANENT HOUSING
SOLUTION IN THE FUTURE. >> THIS ARE THE KIND OF
INVESTMENT DISTRICT 11 NEEDS AND DESERVES AND WE KNOW IT'S
POSSIBLE FOR TWO YEARS PRIOR TO THE GROUNDBREAKING OF KAPUSO AT
THE UPPER YOUNG AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPMENT.
WE HAD A TEMPORARY RV SITE WHERE VIRTUALLY HOUSED IT
NEIGHBORS COULD SAFELY PARK AND LIVE.
>> THIS PROCESS INCLUDED AMPLE COMMUNITY INPUT AND EVENTUALLY
GARNERED SUPPORT FROM THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> FOR TOO LONG MY DISTRICT HAS RECEIVED A TOO FEW RESOURCES TO
MEET THE BASIC NEEDS FOR ALL OUR RESIDENTS INCLUDING THE
MOST PRIMARY CITY SERVICES INTENDED TO PROMOTE PUBLIC
SAFETY, PUBLIC HEALTH, CLEAN STREET AND MORE.
I DON'T BELIEVE THIS PIECE OF LEGISLATION AS IT HAS BEEN
AMENDED GETS US TOWARDS THIS GOALS AND TOWARD THE GOALS OF
GEOGRAPHIC EQUITY PLACING A SHELTER IN EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD
WITHOUT INTENTIONAL COMMUNITY INPUT WON'T ADDRESS ROOT CAUSES
OF HOUSING UNAFFORDABILITY, BEHAVIORAL HEALTH ISSUES
AND MORE. >> FURTHER, I FEAR THAT IT PITS
COURT SERVICES AGAINST NEIGHBORHOOD AGAINST CITY
AGENCIES AS WELL. THUS I WON'T BE SUPPORTIVE OF
THIS LEGISLATION TODAY. WHY?
I STRONGLY BELIEVE THAT IN GEOGRAPHIC EQUITY OF
SERVICES. >> I ALSO BELIEVE OUR FOCUS
SHOULD BE ON PROVIDING PERMANENT SOLUTION THAT ADDRESS
THE ROOT CAUSES OF HOUSING INSECURITY INCLUDING
SIGNIFICANT INVESTMENT INTO PREVENTABLE SOLUTION
AND EXPERTISE DEVELOPING DEEPLY AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
AND I HOPE THAT I CAN WORK WITH MY COLLEAGUES ON THE BOARD
AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE TO MOVE FORWARD WITH THIS KIND OF
INVESTMENT IN THE CITY. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
I WILL START BY SAYING THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR THE
AMOUNT OF WORK THAT WENT INTO THIS ORDINANCE AND TO OUR
COLLEAGUES WHO ARE CO-SPONSORS. I AM THE SUPERVISOR FOR ONE OF
THE WEST SIDE NEIGHBORHOODS THAT HAS SEEN NO SERVICES
SHELTERS, TRANSITIONAL HOUSING OR BEHAVIORAL RESIDENTIAL
SERVICES. REALLY, HOWEVER, WITH THE
EXCEPTION OF LAGUNA HONDA WHERE WE HAVE SEEN SOME OF THE
ACTIVITIES AT BE AT RISK. AND SO I WILL SAY THAT AT
WHEREAS I AGREE THAT COMMUNITY INPUT IS REALLY IMPORTANT.
IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT SOME COMMUNITY
EES DO NOT WANT TO HAVE SERVICES ANYWHERE NEAR THE
COMMUNITY. AND THAT'S A PROBLEM BECAUSE
FOLKS ARE HOMELESS IN EVERY SINGLE DISTRICT IN SAN
FRANCISCO ABOUT THREE YEARS AGO.
ANOTHER COLLEAGUE WHO IS NOW IN THE ASSEMBLY INTRODUCED
LEGISLATION THAT WOULD HAVE DONE SOMETHING SIMILAR.
>> HOWEVER, HE CHOSE TO HAVE A VERY SPECIFIC TOOL
AND NAVIGATION CENTER SITED IN EVERY DISTRICT.
I THINK THIS LEGISLATION IS MUCH MORE FLEXIBLE THAN THAT.
IT ACKNOWLEDGES THAT EVERY POPULATION AND EVERY GEOGRAPHY
HAS SLIGHTLY DIFFERENT NEEDS AND ONE TOOL IS NOT NECESSARILY
THE APPROPRIATE ONE EVERYWHERE .
SO I HAVE SEEN IN MY DISTRICT A GREAT INCREASE OF FOLKS
EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS. A LOT OF IT IS DUE TO THE
ACTIVITIES DOWNTOWN IN THE TENDERLOIN IN SOMA WHERE A
POLICE PRESENCE HAS SHIFTED PEOPLE TO GO TO OTHER PLACES.
AND WHAT HAS HAPPENED IS THAT THOSE PLACES WHERE FOLKS FEEL
LIKE, YOU KNOW, THEY'RE LEFT ALONE HAVE NO SERVICES, THERE'S
NO OPPORTUNITY TO SUPPORT MENTAL HEALTH, TO SUPPORT
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH, TO SUPPORT DRUG ADDICTION, ALL OF THOSE
THINGS THAT WE KNOW ARE NECESSARY TO GET PEOPLE TO
SUCCESS. SO I I'M GLAD WE'RE EVEN HAVING
THIS CONVERSATION BECAUSE PRIOR TO THIS IT WASN'T EVEN AN
ACKNOWLEDGMENT THAT, YOU KNOW, THERE IS A LACK OF EQUITY BOTH
IN COMMUNITIES THAT HAVE TAKEN MORE THAN THEIR FAIR SHARE BUT
AN ACKNOWLEDGMENT THAT SOME COMMUNITIES HAVE NO SUPPORT
AND HAVE A REALLY BIG PROBLEM LIKE MINE.
AND I AM LOOKING FORWARD TO THE DAY WHERE WE HAVE HOT TEAMS.
WE HAVE, YOU KNOW, SHELTER BEDS .
WE HAVE PLACES WHERE PEOPLE CAN GO AND GET BETTER, BE OFF THE
STREETS AND HAVE A PATH TOWARD SUCCESS.
SO I VERY MUCH WELCOME THIS. I'M PROUD TO BE A CO-SPONSOR
AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR OBAMA. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> FOR MYSELF I WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR YOUR WORK ON THIS LEGISLATION.
>> I WAS PROBABLY ONE OF THE HARDER VOTES TO GET AND I
APPRECIATE YOUR WILLINGNESS TO ENGAGE WITH ME.
I OWN MY TIME ON THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
I HAVE BECOME CONCERNED THAT OF COURSE AS I WOULD AGREE WITH
SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND A NUMBER OF YOU THAT THAT WE NEED PLACES
WE NEED PLACES FOR PEOPLE TO COME IN TO OFF THE STREETS
AND THAT WAS THE MOTIVATOR FOR MY PUSH FOR PLACE FOR ALL
AND SHELTER FOR ALL. I'VE ALSO SEEN THE IMPACTS THAT
PLACES BADLY DONE OR OVERLY CONCENTRATED CAN HAVE ON
PARTICULAR NEIGHBORHOODS AND I THINK IT IS NOT UNREASONABLE
FOR NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN FRANCISCO TO SEE WHAT HAS
HAPPENED IN SOME NEIGHBORHOODS AND SAY UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES
HERE. AND SO I THINK THE THE
PROPOSALS THE LEGISLATION HAS I THINK GENERATED CONCERN FROM
FOLKS WHO ARE AFRAID OF THAT. I APPRECIATE YOUR WILLINGNESS
AGAIN TO ENGAGE THE MAYOR'S OFFICE, TO ENGAGE WITH
COLLEAGUES, TO ENGAGE WITH ME AND I THINK THAT THIS IS A
GEOGRAPHIC EQUITY RESOLUTION THAT I THAT I CAN SUPPORT.
I'M HAPPY TO VOTE FOR IT. I THINK THE CONVERSATION
CONTINUES BECAUSE I'M NOT SURE I MEAN WHAT I AM SURE OF IS
THAT WE DON'T WANT TO SEE SHELTERS DOTTING THE LAND
AND CREATING THE IMPACTS IN ALL OF THE NEIGHBORHOODS OF SAN
FRANCISCO IN THE WAY THAT THEY HAVE IMPACTED A FEW.
THAT'S NOT WHAT THIS LEGISLATION DOES.
I SUPPORT THIS LEGISLATION AND I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD FOR FOR THE EXTENSIVE WORK AND OUTREACH
AND WILLINGNESS TO BE FLEXIBLE. I'M A MUCH MORE STUBBORN
PERSON. I APPRECIATE I APPRECIATE YOUR
FLEXIBILITY. WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, COULD
YOU CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 31 AND ITEM 31 SUPERVISOR
AND GUARDIAN AND GUARDIAN EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON HIGH WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO.
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS CHIN AND CHIN VOTING NO.
>> THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER YES THE 230 SPECIAL ORDER IS THE
RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
GOT A LOT OF FOLKS HERE TODAY AND I THINK WE GOT AT LEAST ONE
OF THEM WITH A FLIGHT TO CATCH. AND SO SUPERVISORS SORTER
DISTRICT THREE, WE'RE GOING TO TAKE YOU OUT OF ORDER.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT AND COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE THE
HONOR OF RECOGNIZING THE CONSUL GENERAL OF ITALY, SERGIO
STROZZI. >> SERGIO, WOULD YOU PLEASE
JOIN US? >> SERGIO HAS SERVED IN THIS
ROLE SINCE 2021 AND WE ARE HONORING HIM TODAY JUST THAT
OURS IS A DAYS JUST HOURS BEFORE HIS FLIGHT TO ROME FOR A
NEW POST, SERGIO CAME INTO THIS ROLE AS OUR CITY WAS REELING
FROM THE PANDEMIC AND YET DESPITE THAT HE GOT TO WORK
RIGHT AWAY DOING THE EVERYDAY ROUTINE WORK OF VISAS
AND PASSPORTS BUT ALSO PURSUING AMBITIOUS NEW PROGRAMS TO BRING
OUR COMMUNITIES AND COUNTRIES TOGETHER THROUGH SHARED
INVESTMENTS IN TRADE, TECHNOLOGY AND CULTURE.
IN ONE EXAMPLE HIS LEADERSHIP TO ESTABLISH THE INNOVATE
PROGRAM MEANS THAT HUNDREDS OF ITALIAN ENTREPRENEURS
AND CREATIVES ARE NOW EMBEDDED WITH THE BRIGHTEST MINDS
IN SILICON VALLEY AND WORKING WITH COMPANIES LIKE SALESFORCE,
APPLE AND GOOGLE. >> SERGIO ALSO TOOK EVERY
OPPORTUNITY POSSIBLE TO BE A CHAMPION FOR THE RICH ITALIAN
AMERICAN HERITAGE OF SAN FRANCISCO ESPECIALLY
IN DISTRICT THREE NORTH BEACH. JUST LAST WEEK WE STOOD
ALONGSIDE EACH OTHER IN UNVEILING A NEW PLAQUE FOR
AP GIANNINI AT WASHINGTON SQUARE PARK, WHICH IS PART OF
THE BROADER LITTLE ITALY HONOR WALK.
WE WERE LUCKY TO HAVE CONSUL STROZZI BASED IN SAN FRANCISCO
BUT HIS WORK STRETCHED FURTHER. HE COVERED WESTERN STATES
INCLUDING WASHINGTON, OREGON, UTAH, IDAHO, MONTANA, HAWAII
AND ALASKA. AND IT WAS NOT JUST SERGIO THAT
OUR ITALIAN COMMUNITIES EMBRACED BUT ALSO HIS
DELIGHTFUL FAMILY HIS PARTNER SIMONE AND HIS DAUGHTER
KATERINA. THEY DID ALL OF THIS TOGETHER
AS A TEAM. I KNOW THAT HE HAS MADE A
PROFOUND IMPACT ON EVERYONE HE INTERACTED WITH MAY HAVE BEEN
IN SHARP DRESS HIS FINE BEARD BUT MOST OF ALL I THINK IT WAS
HIS WARMTH THAT TOUCHED PEOPLE IN A SHARED UNDERSTANDING A
SHARED HUMANITY FROM COUNTRY TO COUNTRY AND OPTIMISM THAT OUR
BEST DAYS ARE AHEAD OF US BUT CAN BE REACHED ONLY THROUGH
MUTUAL PARTNERSHIP. SERGIO PLEASE DON'T BE A
STRANGER TO SAN FRANCISCO. YOU WILL ALWAYS HAVE A HOME
AND A PLACE HERE AND NOW IF YOU WISH THE FLOOR IS YOURS TO SAY
A FEW WORDS. BUT FIRST NO, NO, NO YOU CAN
LISTEN TO MORE SUPERVISORS SAY NICE THINGS ABOUT YOU GENERAL
OH CHEN SORRY NOT CHEN SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT CONSUL GENERAL SERGIO IT WAS GREAT MEETING YOU AT
ISLAND DISTRICT 11 TO CELEBRATE CHEN OF THE ITALIAN CLUB.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR FRIENDSHIP.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICES AND I WISH YOU THE BEST JOURNEY
BACK HOME. AND YOU HAVE SAN FRANCISCO AS
YOUR HOME TO WELCOME TO VISIT US ANY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU SO MUCH AND I AM JUST
GOING TO JUMP IN THE QUEUE MYSELF TO SAY I'M VERY UNHAPPY.
I'M NOT EXCITED YOU CANNOT LEAVE.
THIS IS THIS IS NOT ACCEPTABLE. I HAVE ENJOYED GETTING TO KNOW
YOU AND YOUR HUSBAND AND YOUR FAMILY AND I THINK AND MATTEO
AS WELL. >> THE NEWBORN DESERVES A
LITTLE CALL OUT AND YOU'VE YOU'VE JUST BEEN WONDERFUL FOR
SAN FRANCISCO AND IT'S BEEN WONDERFUL TO HAVE YOU HERE
AND I'M GOING TO MISS YOU. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT BOTH IT'S A PROVIDES I FEEL PRIVILEGED,
HUMBLE AND MORE THAN HONORED TO BE HERE WITH YOU TODAY.
IT'S ACTUALLY YOU'RE RIGHT, SUPERVISOR SUTTER, IT'S I'M
GOING TO FLY ON THURSDAY. I CAN'T BELIEVE IT.
I'M TELLING YOU BECAUSE I'VE BEEN ROOTING SO MUCH IN SAN
FRANCISCO. I'M TALKING TO PEOPLE THAT
DON'T KNOW ME BUT I RIDE IN 2022 WITH MY FAMILY IN 2021.
WE'RE VERY FAMILY AND WE BUILD UP A LOT OF THINGS THAT
SUPERVISORS SO THAT YOU SUMMED IT UP SO WELL I'M NOT GOING TO
BOTHER YOU WITH DETAILS BUT YEAH, THE MAIN GOAL WAS TO
BRIDGE MORE SAN FRANCISCO AND ITALY WHICH IS A LITERARY
NIGHTMARE BECAUSE SAN FRANCISCO AND ITALY IS SOMETHING WHICH IS
NATURAL TO BE A BRIDGE BETWEEN THE TWO PLACES.
>> LET ME REMIND THE WORDS OF MARIO DANIEL DURING THE ITALIAN
NATIONAL DAY RECEPTION IT SAYS SAN FRANCISCO SIMPLY WOULD SAN
FRANCISCO WITHOUT THE ITALIAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
OUR IMMIGRANTS CAME HERE LATE 19TH CENTURY POOR FAMILIES,
POOR WORKERS, HARD WORKERS AND THEY BUILT UP THEIR WAY
AND THEIR LIFE WITH THEIR FAMILIES THROUGH THE DECADES.
AND I FEEL HONORED TO HAVE REPRESENTED THIS COMMUNITY BUT
ALSO TO HAVE BROUGHT TO SAN FRANCISCO SOME ITALIAN
INNOVATION AND TECH COMMUNITY WHAT THE INNOVATE THE ITALIAN
INNOVATION HUB IN JACKSON SQUARE IS NOT A SHORT TERM
PROJECT. IT'S A LONG TERM PROJECT TO
BRIDGE COMPANIES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND ITALY, ITALIAN
COMPANIES IN THE FIELD OF INNOVATION AND TECHNOLOGY.
SO WHAT WE'VE DONE HERE IN THE PAST YEARS WAS EXACTLY TO
BRIDGE IN THE LONG TERM THE COMMUNITIES THE ITALIAN BUT
ALSO THE OTHER COMMUNITIES OF SAN FRANCISCO SO VIBRANT ONES,
SO LIVELY ONES AND ITALY THE ITALIANS THAT LIVE IN THE
COUNTRY LET ME REMIND THE SAN FRANCISCO, ITALY THE WALK HAS
BEEN A MILESTONE IN OUR DURING OUR TENURE HONORING THE
GREATEST ITALIAN FIGURES AND THE ITALIAN AMERICAN THAT
CONTRIBUTED TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO THE GREAT CITIES
INNOVATE ON THE TAX SIDE AND ALSO LET ME THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR FOR THE GREAT COLLABORATION WE HAD.
I HAVE TO THANK YOU IN PERSON BECAUSE I WAS NOT HERE THAT
TIME WHEN YOU TOOK THE DECISION ABOUT THE SAN FRANCISCO
APPROVING THE SAN FRANCISCO LITERALLY OUR WALK SO THANK YOU
VERY MUCH FOR APPROVING THAT IT'S BEEN AN HONOR AND I'VE
BEEN WORKING AND COLLABORATING WITH PRESIDENT MANDAN MANNER
WITH YOU SUPERVISOR SOTO WITH SUPERVISOR CHANG.
IT'S BEEN REALLY UNBELIEVABLE JOURNEY FOR ME TO BE HERE WITH
THE MISSION SAN FRANCISCO BUT THE GOOD NEWS IS THAT I'LL BE
BACK TO THE MINISTER OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS BEING A DIPLOMAT
AND NOT A POLITICAL ONE SO I'M GOING CROSS POLITICAL COLORS
LET'S SAY, WHICH MAKES THINGS A LITTLE BIT EASIER FOR ME TO
HANDLE AND I'LL BE HEADING AS WELL TODAY I HAD THE OFFICE FOR
INNOVATION TECHNOLOGY STARTUP SO NOTHING CLOSER TO SAN
FRANCISCO AND TO THE VIBRANT PLACE THAT SAN FRANCISCO IS.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR HAVING ME HERE IN THIS FOR YEARS AND FOR
MAKING MY LIFE SO HAPPY AND MY FAMILY'S LIFE SO HAPPY.
GET OUT AND SUPERVISOR SO I'D BE HANDING OVER TO YOU A LITTLE
MEMORY I WOULD LIKE TO LEAVE TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISOR TO
PRESIDENT MANUEL MAN AND TO YOU PERSONALLY AS SUPERVISOR OF
THESE TWO THREE WHICH IS THE REMODELING OF THE CONSULATE
BECAUSE WE ALSO TOOK CARE OF THE BUILDING WHICH IS HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH AGAIN.
THANK YOU. AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR AND I
HAVE THIS FOR TWO DAYS AND THEN GIVE YES WHAT DID YOU THINK
ABOUT DISTRICT FOR SUPERVISOR ORANGE ENGARDIO GOOD AFTERNOON
COLLEAGUES I WANT TO RECOGNIZE 30 OF THE MOST IMPORTANT PEOPLE
AT CITY HALL OUR CUSTODIANS WE COULD NOT DO OUR WORK WITHOUT
THEM. THE PUBLIC WOULD NOT BE ABLE TO
USE THIS SPACE WITHOUT THEM FROM PASSIONATE PUBLIC COMMENT
IN THE BOARD CHAMBERS TO PASSIONATE WEDDINGS UNDER THE
DOME OUR CUSTODIANS MAKE SURE IT ALL HAPPENS IN A CLEAN
AND WELCOMING SPACE FOR EVERYONE AND THE HARDEST WORK
OF ALL IS KEEPING OUR OFFICES CLEAN EACH PACKED WITH FOUR
STAFFERS, COUNTLESS INTERNS AND A SUPERVISOR WHERE LONG
DAYS MEANS LOTS OF SNACKS AND TAKEOUT CONTAINERS TO CLEAN
UP THE WORK OF A SUPERVISOR AND THEIR STAFF MIGHT MAKE
HEADLINES BUT WE MUST ACKNOWLEDGE THE ROLE OUR
CUSTODIANS PLAY IN MANAGING THE SPACE WHERE THE LEGISLATION
HAPPENS AND WHEN PEOPLE ENTER CITY HALL THEIR FIRST
IMPRESSION IS NOT ABOUT US SUPERVISORS.
IT'S ABOUT HOW BEAUTIFUL AND MAJESTIC THE BUILDING LOOKS
. >> VISITORS APPRECIATE THE
POLISHED FLOORS, THE ORDERLY HALLWAYS AND THE QUIET DIGNITY
OF THIS SPACE. THAT FEELING DOES NOT HAPPEN BY
COINCIDENCE. IT'S THE RESULT OF THE
CONSISTENT DEDICATED WORK OF OUR CUSTODIANS.
THEY ARE AN ESSENTIAL PART OF OUR PUBLIC SERVICE HELPING US
DO OUR JOBS EVERY DAY. THAT'S WHY I WANT TO HIGHLIGHT
RECOGNIZE AND APPRECIATE THESE AMAZING CITY STAFF.
MANY OF THEM ARE PART OF OUR STRONG IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY
IN SAN FRANCISCO A COMMUNITY CONSID RECENTLY UNDER FIRE BY
OUR FEDERAL ADMINISTRATION. NOT ONLY SHOULD WE ACKNOWLEDGE
THEIR HARD WORK AND THE VALUE THEY BRING TO THIS BUILDING BUT
WE SHOULD ALSO CELEBRATE THE RICHNESS THEY BRING TO OUR CITY
AND NATION ON BEHALF OF OUR CITY HALL CUSTODIANS I WOULD
LIKE TO INVITE AUSTIN WANG TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
NOW I KNOW AUSTIN WELL. I SEE YOU OFTEN CLEANS OUR
OFFICE WHEN I'M WORKING LATE. HE'S A VERY WISE AND I ENJOY
TALKING TO HIM AND LISTENING TO HIM AND LEARNING FROM HIM.
AUSTIN CAME TO THE UNITED STATES FROM CHINA 14 YEARS AGO.
HE WORKED FOR THE CITY THE PAST EIGHT YEARS FIRST IN THE PUBLIC
LIBRARY AND THEN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT AND WE ARE LUCKY TO
HAVE AUSTIN AND ALL HIS COLLEAGUES HERE AT CITY HALL.
>> AUSTIN IF YOU ARE HERE THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
COME ON BOSTON YET? NO, HOLD ON AUSTIN YOU HAVE TO
WAIT BECAUSE SUPERVISOR MELGAR HAS SOME THINGS TO SAY.
I THINK WE ALL HAVE SOMETHING TO SAY.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CARDILLO. THANK YOU FOR DOING THIS.
THIS IS A REALLY GREAT COMMENDATION AND THANK YOU TO
THE STAFF THAT DOES THIS AMAZING WORK HERE IN THIS
AMAZING BUILDING. I OF COURSE WANTED TO GIVE A
SPECIAL SHOUT OUT TO AUSTIN. >> I HAVE REALLY ENJOYED
GETTING TO KNOW YOU. I ENJOYED MEETING YOUR PARENTS.
I ENJOYED THE GOSSIP IN THE LATE NIGHT COMMENTS WHENEVER
YOU ARE HERE AND WE'RE HERE AND I SO APPRECIATE THAT YOU
NOTICED EVERYTHING. SO FOR THE REST OF YOU THIS IS
A WAITING BEHAVIOR IS BECAUSE AUSTIN NOTICES EVERYTHING BUT
ALSO YOUR ATTENTION TO DETAIL AND YOUR STRONG SUPPORT FOR
EVERYTHING WE'RE TRYING TO DO. HERE IT GOES.
I JUST I REALLY APPRECIATE YOU. I REALLY APPRECIATE THE STAFF
AND YOU KNOW, SEEING YOU CARRY OUT YOUR WORK EVERY DAY MAKES
IT POSSIBLE FOR EVERYONE TO BE HERE AND ENGAGE IN DEMOCRACY.
>> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR EVERYTHING YOU DO.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD AUSTIN I JUST WANTED TO THANK YOU
AND SAY A COUPLE OF THINGS THAT PEOPLE MAY NOT KNOW BUT BECAUSE
YOU'RE SUCH A FABRIC OF OUR CITY HALL MANY OF MY STAFF HAVE
GOTTEN TO KNOW YOU REALLY WELL WHEN APPARENTLY BEEN PUTTING
THEM TO WORK PRETTY LATE AT NIGHT.
THEY'VE NOTED HOW MUCH YOU TALK ABOUT YOUR CHILDREN AND HOW
MUCH YOU LOVE THEM. YOU'RE APPARENTLY LEARNING
SPANISH AND I DON'T KNOW ANY SPANISH.
I CAN'T EVEN PRACTICE RIGHT NOW WITH YOU BUT UM BUT ALSO JUST
LIKE YOU OFFER SNACKS AND SUPPORT TO OUR TEAM EVERY
DAY THAT THEY'RE WORKING LATE AND I THINK IT JUST SPEAKS TO
THE COMMUNITY WE HAVE HERE AND YOU ARE PART OF THAT
COMMUNITY AND IT MEANS SO MUCH. AND LASTLY MY STAFF WANTED TO
REALLY THANK YOU FOR BRINGING PEACE OF MIND TO THEIR TO OUR
OFFICE AND HELPING THEM FIND THINGS THAT THEY PROBABLY
SHOULD NOT HAVE LOST. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH AUSTIN
SUPERVISOR JAN THANK YOU AND THANK YOU AUSTIN AND AUSTIN
IT'S A GREAT KARAOKE SINGER AND TRULY IS A GREAT FATHER
AND AND WE REALLY APPRECIATE AUSTIN WHO ALWAYS BEEN VERY
CARING BUT REALLY ALSO THANKS TO ALL THE CITY HALL JANITOR
TEAM DOCTOR SALLY SANG AT BOARD 8 OR 10 WE'RE JUST SO
APPRECIATIVE OF YOU. >> YOU WORK HARD.
YOU WEREN'T LATE. YOU WERE EARLY AND CLEAN AFTER
US BUT ALSO THE GENERAL PUBLIC AND YET YOU'RE ALWAYS THERE
AND WE JUST VERY GRATEFUL. >> THANK YOU THAT DESIGN
SUPERVISOR IS THERE CHEN THANK YOU PRESENT MANAGEMENT AUSTIN
THANK YOU. I THINK I'M NOT GOING TO REPEAT
WHAT MY COLLEAGUE HAVE SAID BUT I ALSO ENJOYED IT ALL THE
CHATTING WITH YOU THAT RELATED TO OUR COMMUNITY WHAT IS OUR
NEEDS AND AND YOUR FEEDBACK AND YOUR YOUR ADVICE AS WELL
THIS IS LIKE WHAT PROBLEM YOU SEE I ENJOY ALL THOSE CHATTING
BUT ON TOP OF THAT I REALLY APPRECIATE ALL THE CITY STAFF
WHO ARE KEEPING OUR OUR CITY HALL CLEAN AND I TRULY
APPRECIATE YOUR SERVICES. >> OH WITHOUT DELAY THEY MAY I
CAN THOUGH LADY OTHERWISE I'M GOING TO WHAT'D I DO FOR LIKE
I'M CANCELING THE LAW? WELL, IF I'M GOING THE WHOLE
HOUSE I'M WHO DOES L.A. THEY HELP ME FOR BODILY DAY
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MOUNTAIN MAN AND I
WON'T BELABOR THE POINT ABOUT YOUR AMAZING WORK BUT I DO JUST
WANT TO SAY CONGRATULATE AND THANK YOU AND YOUR ENTIRE
TEAM FOR THE WORK THAT YOU DO EVERY DAY.
AND I WANT TO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR AND GUARDIAN FOR
HONORING AUSTIN AND HIS TEAM THIS AFTERNOON.
I WOULD JUST SAY LIKE I DON'T KNOW BUT YOU HAVE THE UNCANNY
ABILITY TO KNOW WHAT NOT TO THROW AWAY AND I DON'T KNOW HOW
YOU DO THAT BUT I DEFINITELY APPRECIATE YOU AND YOUR TEAM
FOR THAT. >> CONGRATULATIONS AND THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER YES. >> THANKS AGAIN, REZA
AND ENGARDIO FOR FOR RECOGNIZING THE WHOLE STAFF.
THANK YOU, AUSTIN. IT'S BEEN A PLEASURE TO GET TO
KNOW YOU. I KNOW MY STAFF APPRECIATES YOU
. >> IT'S ALWAYS NICE TO SEE A
FRIENDLY FACE AFTER HOURS. >> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH AND I
WILL FINISH JUST BY THANKING AGAIN SUPERVISOR AND GARDENER.
THIS WAS A VERY GOOD IDEA AND AND TO AUSTIN TO ALL THE
STAFF THANK YOU AND AUSTIN IN PARTICULAR YOU ARE BELOVED
EVERYONE IS JUST DELIGHTED TO SEE YOU COMING DOWN THE HALLWAY
OR COMING INTO OUR OFFICES AND I KNOW A LOT OF FOLKS ENJOY
CHATTING WITH YOU ABOUT WHATEVER SO SO THANK YOU
AND CONGRATULATIONS. >> AND NOW FINALLY YOU CAN
SPEAK ALL RIGHT. OH, GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
>> MY NAME IS AUSTIN. IT IS GREAT HONORS FOR ME TO
STAND HERE TODAY AND ACCEPT THIS AWARD.
I AM TRULY GRATEFUL AND DEEPLY MOVED.
THESE RECOGNITIONS IS NOT ONLY A PERSONAL HONOR BUT ALSO AN
AFFIRMATION OF OUR EFFORTS AND DEDICATION.
THIS HONORS A CERTAIN BUT IT IS ALSO A RESPONSIBILITY IN THE
FUTURE I WILL CONTINUE TO WORK HARD IN MY WORK WITH MORE
AND FORESEE US AND I'M FIRMER FAITH AND STRIVE TO CONTRIBUTE
MORE TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF OUR CITY AT THE SAME TIME WE WOULD
ALSO LIKE TO THANK YOU FOR THEIR COOPERATION AND SUPPORT
OF OUR SUPERVISORS AND SUPERVISORS OFFICES.
>> FINALLY, THANK YOU AGAIN FOR YOUR AFFIRMATIONS OF OUR WORK.
WE WILL DEFINITELY CHERISHED TO HONOR AND CONTINUE TO WORK
HARDER. >> I THANK YOU SO MUCH
. HE IS PHENOMENAL MAN DISTRICT
FIVE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS MY HONOR
TO RECOGNIZE DIANE LIM, AN EXTRAORDINARY JOURNALIST,
STORYTELLER AND FIERCE ADVOCATE WHOSE WORK HAS LEFT AN
INDELIBLE MARK ON OUR CITY AND BEYOND.
>> WHEN I COME TO THE STAGE I HOLD ON AFTER NEARLY EIGHT
IMPACTFUL YEARS AS AN ANCHOR AND REPORTER WITH ABC7 HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO, DIANE IS CONCLUDING THIS REMARKABLE
CHAPTER OF HER CAREER. >> HER REPORTING DURING SOME OF
OUR CITY'S MOST CHALLENGING MOMENTS ESPECIALLY HER
COURAGEOUS FRONTLINE COVERAGE OF ANTI-ASIAN HATE DURING THE
COVID 19 PANDEMIC HELPED ASIAN-AMERICANS LIKE MYSELF
FEEL HEARD AND UNDERSTOOD. AND WHAT WAS SUCH A DIFFICULT
MOMENT FOR OUR COMMUNITY? >> HER WORK HAS NOT ONLY
INFORMED BUT INSPIRED US ALL. >> I'D ALSO LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE
THAT YOU ARE THE ONLY PERSON WHO WOULD BE ABLE TO GET MY
FIANCEE TO COME BACK TO THE CHAMBERS AFTER MY INAUGURATION
DESPITE MANY ATTEMPTS. WHEN I ASKED WHY ARE YOU COMING
FOR DIANE? >> BECAUSE SHE SPEAKS FOR US
ALL. AND I THINK I'VE HEARD FROM HER
MANY TIMES HOW THERE'S NO POLITICIAN THAT COULD GET HER
BACK. BUT YOU COULD.
AND I THINK IT'S BECAUSE OF WHAT YOU REPRESENT AND THE
STORIES YOU TELL. YOU'VE TOLD ME HOW YOU REALLY
WANT TO FOCUS ON ELEVATING OUR COMMUNITY AND SHARING OUR
STORIES AND OFTEN HAVING TO FIGHT THE POWERS THAT BE TO
TELL THOSE STORIES. AND I THINK IT RESONATES SO
MUCH WITH SO MANY OF THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS THAT HAVE
COME OUT HERE AS WELL TO SUPPORT AS OTHER LOCAL LEADERS
HAVE ALSO SAID WHILE OTHERS CHOOSE TO SCAPEGOAT OR LOOK
AWAY. DIANE CHOSE TO BE BRAVE BY
SHARING THE TRUTH OF WHAT WAS HAPPENING ESPECIALLY TO OUR
ELDERS NIGHT AFTER NIGHT. SHE HELPED SPARK A MOVEMENT.
DIANE MADE HISTORY AS THE FIRST ASIAN-AMERICAN WOMAN TO ANCHOR
IN MULTIPLE MAJOR MARKETS. BREAKING BARRIERS AND LIFTING
UP UNDERREPRESENTED VOICES WHEREVER SHE WENT.
>> HER FORTHCOMING BOOK AMPLIFY MY FIGHT FOR ASIAN AMERICA IS A
TESTAMENT TO HER ENDURING COMMITMENT TO TRUTH, JUSTICE
AND COMMUNITY. >> SHE HAS RECEIVED NUMEROUS
ACCOLADES FOR HER IMPACT INCLUDING THE CHAMPION OF TRUTH
AWARD FROM S.F. CAUSE RECOGNITION FROM THE CALIFORNIA
STATE ASSEMBLY AND THE SAN FRANCISCO CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE FOR API AND LGBTQ PLUS ADVOCACY AND INCLUSION AND THE
GOLD HOUSE A100 LIST OF THE MOST IMPACTFUL ASIAN-AMERICANS
ALONGSIDE LEADERS LIKE VICE PRESIDENT KAMALA HARRIS.
>> IN 2020 TWO SHE WAS THE ONLY LOCAL JOURNALIST INVITED BY THE
BIDEN ADMINISTRATION TO THE WHITE HOUSE FOR THE FIRST EVER
AAPI HERITAGE MONTH CELEBRATION .
WHETHER MODERATING A FIRESIDE CHAT WITH MARTHA STEWART OR
REPORTING FROM THE OSCARS RED CARPET DIANE BRINGS
AUTHENTICITY, EMPATHY AND INTEGRITY TO EVERY STORY
SHE TELLS HER LEADERSHIP IN COVERING ISSUES OF RACE
AND VIOLENCE HAS RESONATED FAR BEYOND OUR CITY, EARNING HER
RECOGNITION ALONGSIDE NATIONAL FIGURES AND INVITATIONS TO THE
WHITE HOUSE. YET SHE HAS ALWAYS REMAINED
DEEPLY ROOTED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WHERE SHE LIVES WITH
HER HUSBAND AND SPIRITED TODDLER.
>> INDEED, DIANE, THANK YOU FOR YOUR FEARLESS JOURNALISM, YOUR
AUTHENTICITY AND YOUR UNWAVERING DEDICATION TO
AMPLIFYING STORIES THAT NEED TO BE HEARD.
YOUR WORK HAS STRENGTHENED OUR COMMUNITIES UNDERSTAND ADDING
IN OUR CITY'S COMMITMENT TO JUSTICE AND INCLUSION.
THANK YOU. SUPERMAN VI.
OKAY. HE SUPERVISED HER DORSEY.
>> I JUST WANT TO TAKE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO JUST SAY THAT I
WENT TO THE SAME COLLEGE EMERSON COLLEGE AS DIANE LIM
EVERYBODY. WE'RE BOTH EMERSON LYONS
AND IT'S A BIG DEAL FOR FOR THE SCHOOL THAT WE WENT TO.
I STARTED IN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT AS THE
COMMUNICATIONS DIRECTOR JUST A FEW WEEKS BEFORE THE COVID
LOCKDOWN. AND I SAW FIRSTHAND HOW THE
SCAPEGOATING PLAYED OUT AGAINST OUR AAPI COMMUNITY AND HOW THAT
PLAYED OUT IN VIOLENT ATTACKS. AND I AM JUST SO GRATEFUL THAT
IN THAT REALLY DIFFICULT TIME WE HAD A JOURNALIST OF YOUR
CALIBER TO COVER IT. IT MEANT A LOT TO ME AS
SOMEBODY WHO CARES ABOUT PUBLIC SAFETY BUT I KNOW IT MEANT A
LOT TO EVERYBODY IN THE AAPI COMMUNITY AND EVERYBODY WHO IS
LIKE AS I AM A GAY MAN IN A VULNERABLE COMMUNITY THAT'S
ALSO DISPROPORTIONATELY AFFECTED BY HATE CRIME.
SO I JUST WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR HONORING
YOU AND JUST PILE ON WITH KIND WORDS OF MY OWN.
>> CONGRATULATIONS. >> SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AS
SOMEONE WHO WAS A JOURNALIST BEFORE I WAS A SUPERVISOR.
I REALLY RESPECT YOUR JOURNALISM AND HOW IMPACTFUL IT
WAS. IT'S IT'S A NOBLE CAUSE AND YOU
REALLY SHOWED THE BEST IT CAN BE.
SO THANK YOU FOR SERVING THE PROFESSION AND THE COMMUNITY AS
WELL AS YOU AS YOU DID. AND CONGRATS.
WELL, CONGRATULATIONS GUYS AND THANK YOU FOR ALL OF YOUR
YEARS OF SERVICE TO SAN FRANCISCO.
IT HAS BEEN A TREAT FOR ME TO GET TO KNOW YOU A LITTLE BIT
OVER THESE LAST FEW YEARS. >> DIANE LIM, POOL BOY USUALLY
I'M ON THE OTHER SIDE WAITING FOR THIS SEEMINGLY BORING
MEETING TO END SO I CAN CHASE ALL OF YOU DOWN WITH A BIG
MICROPHONE AND GET YOU ALL ON CAMERA.
>> BUT I JUST WANT TO SAY AS I LOOK OUT ON THE CROWD AND I
LOOK OUT AT ALL OF THE SUPERVISORS AND PEOPLE IN SAN
FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT I HAVE TO SAY IT FEELS SO GOOD TO BE A
SAN FRANCISCAN, DOESN'T IT? I DIDN'T EXPECT TO GET SO
EMOTIONAL BUT I HAVE TO SHARE MY DEEPEST GRATITUDE.
FIRST OFF OF COURSE FOR SUPERVISOR BELAL MAHMOOD FOR
SPONSORING THIS. >> AND ALSO FOR EACH AND EVERY
ONE OF YOU FOR BEING ON BOARD BECAUSE AT ONE POINT OR ANOTHER
WE HAVE SPOKEN. I HAVE BEEN HARD ON ALL OF YOU.
BUT YET I THINK WE ALL FIGHT FOR THE GOOD OF THIS FAIR CITY.
>> I CAN'T THANK ENOUGH THE PEOPLE WHO ARE HERE FROM SO
MANY DIFFERENT FACETS OF MY LIFE.
I'M SHAKING BECAUSE I DID NOT EXPECT HALF OF THEM TO BE HERE.
>> BECAUSE THE CHALLENGE SOMETIMES IS BEING A JOURNALIST
ESPECIALLY ONE ON TELEVISION IS YOU SPEAK TO ONE CAMERA, YOU'RE
UNSURE OF WHO'S ON THE OTHER SIDE.
>> YOU DON'T KNOW WHO IS SUPPORTING YOU BUT YOU SURE AS
ALL KNOW THE VITRIOL THAT COMES YOUR WAY.
YOU ALL KNOW AS SUPERVISORS. >> SO TO SEE MY FAMILY AND MY
FRIENDS HERE AND ALSO I HAVE A SPECIAL PLACE OF COURSE IN MY
HEART TO MY TWO YEAR OLD WHO WILL BE TWO ON FRIDAY BECAUSE I
WANT HIM TO SEE WHAT HIS VOICE CAN DO THAT HE IS NOT JUST ONE
PERSON, THAT THERE IS A COMMUNITY RALLYING BEHIND HIM.
>> YOU KNOW, DURING THE PANDEMIC AND THROUGHOUT MY
CAREER I ALWAYS KNEW WHAT REPRESENTATION WAS.
>> AT LEAST I THOUGHT I DID. BY HAVING A SEAT AT THE TABLE.
BUT TRULY WHAT THAT MEANS IS DOING SOMETHING WITH THAT SEAT
FLIPPING THAT SEAT OVER UNTIL PEOPLE LISTEN.
MAYBE THAT'S UNCONVENTIONAL FOR A JOURNALIST.
WELL, THAT'S NOT MY PROBLEM ANYMORE I SUPPOSE.
>> BUT WE'VE ACCOMPLISHED SO MUCH AND WE OFTENTIMES TALK
ABOUT THE HATE, THE VIOLENCE, THE DISCRIMINATION, ALL OF
THAT. BUT WE ALSO MUST TAKE THIS TIME
TO CELEBRATE YOU AS A CHINESE-AMERICAN WOMAN BORN
FROM PARENTS WHO CAME FROM HONG KONG AND TAIWAN.
>> I THINK IT WAS INHERENT IN ME TO ALWAYS BE EXTRA
HUMBLE, EXTRA ASIAN, HUMBLE I USED TO CALL IT WHENEVER THERE
WAS AN AWARD OR AN ACCOLADE OR A COMPLIMENT NO, NO I DON'T
DESERVE IT. >> GIVE THE CREDIT TO SOMEONE
ELSE. BUT I AM STANDING IN FRONT OF
ALL OF YOU PROUD TODAY TO ACCEPT THIS SPECIAL
COMMENDATION BECAUSE I THINK THIS IS FOR ALL OF US.
>> SO I LEAVE YOU NOW WITH THIS REMINDER THAT THE REMARKS THAT
I'M MAKING IF YOU SEE THE SPECIAL COMMENDATION ON SOCIAL
MEDIA OR IF YOU ARE WATCHING ONLINE ON THE INTERNET HELLO
MOTHER AND FATHER OUT THERE IN CONNECTICUT REMEMBER WE MUST
ALWAYS BE BRAVE IN THE FACE OF ADVERSITY WHEN WE ARE BEING
GASLIT WHEN WE ARE BEING MADE TO FEEL TWO INCHES TALL.
>> REMEMBER THAT IF WE HAVE TWO THINGS ON OUR SIDE THE TRUTH
AND OUR COMMUNITY WE WILL ALWAYS ALWAYS PREVAIL.
>> THANK YOU SO SO MUCH. YOU DO YOU WANT TO COME?
YEAH. FIRST ME I, I COME FIRST.
AND WHAT DO YOU THINK? WOW.
WE'RE GOING TO GO OUTSIDE. OH, ALL RIGHT.
DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY.
>> GREAT. THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT MANDELBAUM. >> COLLEAGUES, AS WE CELEBRATE
SAN FRANCISCO'S INAUGURAL SOUTH ASIAN HERITAGE MONTH THIS
MONTH, IT IS MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE ONE OF MY DISTRICT'S
MOST TIRELESS CIVIC AND CULTURAL LEADERS.
CEMETERY. >> NOW SIMA SIMA HAS BEEN A
DISTRICT SIX RESIDENT FOR NEARLY 20 YEARS.
SHE IS AN ACCOMPLISHED CORPORATE RETAIL PROFESSIONAL
WITH MACY'S AND SEPHORA. NORTH AMERICA HEADQUARTERED
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. AND HER EXPERIENCE THERE HAS
WELL INFORMED HER ADVOCACY FOR SAN FRANCISCO'S LOCAL BUSINESS
AND RETAIL VIBRANCY. INSPIRED BY HER INDIAN
IMMIGRANT MOTHER'S URBAN FASHION BOUTIQUE AND IN MEMORY
OF HER FATHER, A HOWARD UNIVERSITY GRADUATE
AND LIFELONG HBCU PROFESSOR SIMA HAS MADE IT HER MISSION TO
BUILD SPACES WHERE DIVERSE VOICES AND COMMUNITIES CAN
THRIVE. SHE HAS AN IMPRESSIVE RECORD OF
CIVIC LEADERSHIP IN DISTRICT SIX.
SHE CO-FOUNDED IDEATE S.F., A VOLUNTEER LED NONPROFIT THAT
STRENGTHENS CIVIC ENGAGEMENT IN OUR HIGHEST DENSITY
NEIGHBORHOODS WITH 88. SHE LED SUCCESSFUL ADVOCACY
CAMPAIGNS THAT INCLUDE THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CROSSING A
CHERISHED PUBLIC SPACE IN THE EAST CUT THAT QUICKLY BECAME
THAT NEIGHBORHOOD'S BACKYARD AND HAS BEEN NATIONALLY
RECOGNIZED. SHE SERVED AS A MEMBER OF THE
OSSEO TRANS BAY CITIZEN'S ADVISORY COMMITTEE WHERE SHE
HAS BEEN A WELL-INFORMED AND FORCEFUL ADVOCATE FOR THE
PROMISE OF 21ST CENTURY URBANISM.
AND SHE ALSO SERVES AS A BOARD MEMBER FOR SOME LOCAL POLITICAL
ADVOCACY ORGANIZATIONS AND I HAVE ALWAYS VALUED HER
THOUGHTFULNESS AS SOMEONE COMMITTED TO BUILDING BRIDGES
RATHER THAN BURNING THEM. IN ADDITION, HER INCREDIBLE
ORGANIZING WORK SHE IS ONE OF THE MOST ACTIVE, INFLUENTIAL
AND BUSY MEMBERS OF THE BAY AREA'S SOUTH ASIAN COMMUNITY.
SIMA SPEARHEADED SAN FRANCISCO'S SOUTH ASIANS, A
GROWING ONLINE RESOURCE THAT HIGHLIGHTS LOCAL SOUTH ASIAN
EVENTS, TALENT VENDORS AND COMMUNITY LEADERS.
SHE HAS ALSO LAUNCHED CULTURAL COLLABORATIONS THAT HAVE BECOME
DISTRICT SIX TRADITIONS FROM DIWALI CELEBRATIONS IN SUMMER
WITH SOMA WEST AND THE RINCON CENTER TO MY HANDS DOWN
FAVORITE THE HOLI, THE LEGENDARY FILM FESTIVAL OF
COLORS WHICH STARTED A COUPLE OF YEARS AGO AT THE CROSSING
IN EAST CUT FROM WHICH THE SAN FRANCISCO CHRONICLE FEATURED A
PHOTO OF ME ABSOLUTELY COVERED IN PINK AND BLUE POWDER THAT I
REALLY CHERISH. NOW CIMATU HAS ALSO ELEVATED
SOUTH ASIAN YOGA TEACHERS, DANCE ARTISTS AND VEDIC
PRACTICES THROUGHOUT THE CITY. HER WORK ISN'T JUST ABOUT
CELEBRATION IT'S ALSO ABOUT BUILDING CONNECTION, INCLUSION
AND VISIBILITY IN THE CITY, SHE LOVES AND PROUDLY CALLS HOME.
>> SIMA SAW GAPS IN THE DISTRICT'S SIX CIVIC SPACE
AND THE SOUTH ASIAN COMMUNITY AND SHE ENTHUSIASTICALLY JUMPED
IN TO FILL THEM. >> SHE IS A DOER, AN INNOVATOR
AND SOMEONE I AM INCREDIBLY LUCKY TO HAVE AS A CONSTITUENT.
I WOULD LIKE TO RECOGNIZE SOME OF THE FOLKS WHO ARE HERE TO
SUPPORT SIMA TODAY. I KNOW THAT ANDREW ROBINSON,
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE EAST COAST COMMUNITY BENEFIT
DISTRICT IS HERE. I BELIEVE BACK THERE ALSO SEE
HIS MOTHER RITA SRI, ALSO A DISTRICT SIX RESIDENT WHO IS
HERSELF STAUNCHLY COMMITTED TO MAKING SURE HER DISTRICT
SUPERVISOR IS AS WELL FED AS POSSIBLE AND WHOM I HOLD
PERSONALLY ACCOUNTABLE FOR MOST OF MY WEIGHT GAIN AS A
SUPERVISOR. >> THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE FOR
SAN FRANCISCO'S FIRST SOUTH ASIAN HERITAGE MONTH.
I CAN'T THINK OF A BETTER DISTRICT SIX REPRESENTATIVE TO
COMMEND FOR YOUR EXTRAORDINARY CIVIC LEADERSHIP AND DEDICATION
TO ADVANCING SOUTH ASIAN CULTURE IN OUR CITY.
THANK YOU. SIMA SRI.
I'D LIKE TO THANK YOU INVITE YOU TO SAY A FEW WORDS OR THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR THOSE VERY KIND WORDS.
WE'VE ALWAYS APPRECIATED THE SUPPORT YOU'VE GIVEN THE SOUTH
ASIAN COMMUNITY AND OUR DISTRICT AND THANK YOU TO THE
ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND OUR AUDIENCE HERE TODAY FOR
CELEBRATING THE INAUGURAL SOUTH ASIAN HERITAGE MONTH IN SAN
FRANCISCO AT THIS MEETING WITH SPECIAL THANKS TO SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD AND COMMISSIONER COULD READ CHAUDHARY FOR SPEARHEADING
THIS INITIATIVE THAT'S HISTORICAL AS THE FIRST SOUTH
ASIAN HERITAGE MONTH ON THE LEGISLATIVE RECORD.
IT IS DEEPLY MEANINGFUL TO SEE OUR CITY HONOR THE RICHNESS OF
THE SOUTH ASIAN DIASPORA. FOR OVER A CENTURY SOUTH ASIANS
HAVE HELPED SHAPE SAN FRANCISCO'S CIVIC AND CULTURAL
FABRIC. FROM FREEDOM FIGHTERS LIKE
BHAGAT SINGH WHOSE WRITINGS INSPIRED STUDENTS OF SOUTH
ASIAN DESCENT HERE IN THE EARLY 1900S DURING THE BRITISH RULE
OF INDIA TO THE EARLY PUNJABI FARMERS WHO SETTLED IN THE BAY
AREA AND ACTIVISTS WHO MADE IT A BASE FOR BOTH LIVELIHOOD
AND JUSTICE. THE LEGACY LIVES ON TODAY
THROUGH THE IMMENSE CONTRIBUTIONS OF SOUTH ASIAN
TALENT IN TECHNOLOGY AND HEALTH CARE AND IN THE GROWING CIVIC
AND POLITICAL LEADERSHIP SHAPING SAN FRANCISCO'S FUTURE
. IT ALSO SHINES AND OUR FOOD
AND CHAI TRADITIONS IN YOGIC AND AYER VEDIC WELLNESS
PRACTICES AND IN THE ARTS DANCE AND MUSIC THAT BRING
COMMUNITIES TOGETHER. THE BOLLYWOOD MEETS BURNING MAN
HOLI COLOR FESTIVAL SUPERVISOR GENEROUSLY CHERISHES IS ALSO
ONE OF MY FONDEST MEMORIES IN MY 20 YEARS IN SAN FRANCISCO
MADE EVEN BRIGHTER BY LEADERS LIKE ASSEMBLY MEMBER MATT HANEY
AND SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY CELEBRATING WITH US IN DISTRICT
SIX. IT'S BEEN A JOY TO COLLABORATE
ON THESE FESTIVALS WITH PARTNERS FROM THE EAST CUT CBD
LIKE ANDREW ROBBINS SAID PARIVAR BAY AREA ASIA FOR
EDUCATION AND MANPREET WHO IS HERE TODAY FROM RUNG DAY
BOLLYWOOD. SHE BRINGS OUT HUNDREDS OF
PEOPLE TO TEACH THEM SOUTH ASIAN DANCE.
COURTESY THE EAST CUTS CBD AND TJP PARTNERSHIP AT
SALESFORCE PARK. EVERY FRIDAY IF YOU HAVEN'T
TRIED IT YOU HAVE TO COME DANCE WITH US.
>> IT'S SUCH A ESSENCE OF SOUTH ASIAN CULTURE.
SO TO REALLY CELEBRATE SOUTH ASIAN HERITAGE MONTH WITH US,
COME DANCE WITH US FRIDAY EVENINGS AT THE PARK AND ALSO
MONTHLY AT THE CROSSING. AND I'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK
BOLLYWOOD DANCE CENTRAL AND OR A T A NEW DELHI RESTAURANT THAT
HAVE PARTNERED WITH US ON THESE POP UPS POST-COVID TO BRING
COLOR BACK INTO SAN FRANCISCO. NEW DELHI RESTAURANT IS THE
OLDEST SOUTH ASIAN LEGACY RESTAURANT IN THE CITY AND WE
WANT TO CONTINUE TO SEE THE SOUTH ASIAN RESTAURANTS
THROUGHOUT EVERY DISTRICT THRIVE FOR GENERATIONS AHEAD.
>> I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING THIS WORK WITH ALL OF YOU
AND SINCE SUPERVISOR MEHMOOD MISSED THE BEGINNING, SPECIAL
THANKS TO YOU AND COULD FOR SPEARHEADING THIS INITIATIVE
AND ALSO JUST TO KIND OF CLOSE .
WE ARE WORKING ON SOME CLOSING CELEBRATIONS FOR EVERYONE TO
DANCE WITH US MID-AUGUST IN THE EAST COURT CBD SO STAY TUNED
FOR THAT. >> FOLLOW SOUTH ASIANS ON
INSTAGRAM TO CURATE MORE SOUTH ASIAN EXPERIENCES FOR YOURSELF
AND THE COMMUNITY AROUND YOU. >> THANK YOU AGAIN
. DISTRICTS SEVEN SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
SO I SEE MY HONOREE HERE MS. M.A. LAO SMITH IF YOU COULD
COME UP ALONG WITH I ALSO I ALSO SEE LIKE THE TOP BRASS OF
SFE, USD AND DCF DON'T GO ANYWHERE.
CHERISE COME ON UP. SO IF YOU COULD ALL COME UP
AND STAND BEHIND ATMEL AS SUPPORT FROM HER COMMUNITY THAT
WOULD BE REALLY GREAT AS WELL. >> SO TODAY I HAVE THE GREAT
PRIVILEGE OF HONORING SOMEONE WHO HAS BEEN SO INSTRUMENTAL
IN SERVING HAVING SUPPORTED THE SUCCESS OF LITERALLY THOUSANDS
OF YOUNG PEOPLE AND FAMILIES IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR 30 YEARS.
AND THAT IS MS. MAINLY LAO SMITH.
>> SO YOU WILL NOTICE SHE'S SITTING BECAUSE SHE HATES THE
LIMELIGHT. WHEN I PROPOSED THAT WE WERE
GOING TO DO THAT SHE WAS LIKE NO MIRNA BUT WE HAVE TO DO IT
MAINLY BECAUSE BEHIND THE SCENES THIS AMAZING WOMAN HAS
BEEN WORKING ON TRANSFORMATIONAL ANTI-RACIST
POLICIES THAT PROMOTE SOCIAL JUSTICE AND EDUCATION
AND PUBLIC HEALTH PRACTICES IN OUR CITY FOR 30 YEARS.
>> MS. LAO SMITH STARTED HER CAREER AT THE SAN FRANCISCO
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH WHERE SHE PLAYED A KEY ROLE
IN LAUNCHING PROGRAMS THAT TACKLED ADOLESCENT TOBACCO
ISSUES. >> AND THE WAY SHE DID IT WAS
FIRMLY ROOTED IN RACIAL JUSTICE ORGANIZING, PEER SUPPORT
AND EDUCATION SOMETHING THAT SHE HAS CARRIED HER WHOLE
CAREER. >> SHE CO-DEVELOPED THE
COMMUNITY ACTION MODEL A FIVE STEP FRAMEWORK THAT EMPOWERS
COMMUNITY TO TACKLE HEALTH INEQUALITIES THROUGH POLICY
AND SYSTEMS CHANGE. MEILI THEN JOINED THE TEAM AT
THE SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT IN 2012 AND HAS
BEEN AN ESSENTIAL STEADY PART OF THE INNER WORKINGS EVER
SINCE. >> SHE HAS SERVED IN VARIOUS
LEADERSHIP ROLES INCLUDING EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF COMMUNITY
SCHOOL. SHE BASICALLY RESCUED THAT
DEPARTMENT. I'M LIKE I'M NOT UNDER
ESTIMATING THAT. >> AND LATER SHE BECAME THE
CHIEF OF STUDENT OF FAMILY SERVICES.
I MET MILLIE IN 2014 MORE THAN ANYONE THAT I'VE EVER MET IN MY
LIFE. SHE EMBODIES THE CONCEPT OF A
WARM DEMANDER. THIS IS SOMEONE WHO
IN RELATIONSHIPS ALL THE ALL THE EDUCATION PEOPLE ARE
NODDING AND FOCUSES ON BUILDING RAPPORT WITH OTHERS AND TRUST
SHOWS PERSONAL REGARD FOR OTHERS EARNS THE RIGHT TO
DEMAND AND ALSO IS VERY COMPETENT, TECHNICALLY
PROFICIENT, ENCOURAGES PRODUCTIVE STRUGGLE.
SHE CERTAINLY DID THAT FOR ME. I THINK MILLIE HAS SAID NO TO
ME MORE THAN ANYONE IN MY LIFE. AND SHE IS THE BEST OF THE BEST
MEILI ALLOWS ME SHOWED INCREDIBLE LEADERSHIP
AND COURAGE DURING THE COVID 19 PANDEMIC.
DEVELOPING DISTRICT WIDE PROTOCOLS AND COORDINATING
ACROSS AGENCIES ALL COMMUNITIES COMMUNITIES THAT SUFFERED THE
MOST. IT WAS MAINLY QUIET WORK,
COMPETENT WORK BEHIND THE SCENES THAT MADE IT HAPPEN.
IN 23 SHE JOINED THE SUPERINTENDENT'S OFFICE WHERE
SHE CONTINUED TO LEAD EQUITY DRIVEN WORK TO SUPPORT STUDENTS
AND FAMILIES. MS..
SMITH'S LEADERSHIP DOES NOT ONLY PERTAIN TO EDUCATION SHE
HAS ALSO SPENT TIME WORKING AND LEADING COMPLEX ADVOCACY
PROJECTS FOR YOUTH, LOW INCOME FAMILIES, COMMUNITIES OF COLOR,
THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY. HER LEADERSHIP WILL HAVE A
LASTING IMPACT ON OUR SCHOOL DISTRICT THE COMMUNITY SHE
SUPPORTS AND THE CITY AS A WHOLE AND COUNTLESS GENERATIONS
OF YOUNG PEOPLE AND FAMILIES. >> A PASSIONATE ADVOCATE FOR
SOCIAL JUSTICE SHE HAS SERVED THE RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO
WITH UNWAVERING PURPOSE, EARNING OUR DEEP RESPECT FOR
HER AND HER WORK. MALE IS ALSO A LOVING, CARING
MOM TO FOUR KIDS FOUR CHILDREN ALL FIVE USC GRADUATES LIKE HER
OH SUPERINTENDENT SUZANNE THE HOUSE TO THANK YOU FOR COMING
BACK SUPERINTENDENT. I AM PROUD TO CALL YOU A
FRIEND, MALIK AND I WISH YOU THE VERY BEST IN YOUR NEXT STEP
IN YOUR LIFE. I'M NOW GOING TO PASS IT ALONG
TO YOUR DISTRICT SUPERVISOR, CHEYENNE TEN WHO WANTS TO SAY A
FEW WORDS BEFORE I HAVE SUPERINTENDENTS WHO COME UP
AND SAY A FEW WORDS AS WELL. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR CAN GRADUATION MEAN LEAVE US WITH
YOUR WORD AT SFD SD AND THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH HAS
ALWAYS BEEN CENTER AROUND COMMUNITY AND EQUITY.
YOU HAVE BEEN AN INCREDIBLE PUBLIC SERVANT ADVOCATE
COMMUNITY ORGANIZERS AND DISTRICT 11 MOM RAISING
YOUR CHILDREN IN THE EXCELSIOR .
I FIRST MET YOU WHEN I WAS A YOUTH AT A YOUTH PROGRAM
IN CHINATOWN. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
MENTORSHIP AND GUIDANCE OVER THE YEARS.
YOUR INCREDIBLE WORK AND INVALUABLE KNOWLEDGE WILL
NO DOUBT BE MISSED BY EVERYONE THERE AND MORE OF YOUR
COLLEAGUES. >> YOU YOU HAVE TOUCHED ME
IN LIFE AND I WISH YOU ALL THE BEST IN THE NEXT JOURNEY WHICH
IS A TIME IN WHICH I ALSO LOOK FORWARD TO SEEING YOU MORE
AROUND IN DISTRICT 11. >> CONGRATULATE AND SUPERVISOR
WALTON. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT
AND MADAM AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR DOING
THIS. MELLIE I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT
WE ALL OVER THE YEARS AND I HAVE A DIFFERENT EXPERIENCE
THAN SUPERVISOR MELGAR IN TERMS OF I DON'T REMEMBER YOU EVER
TELLING ME NO WHEN I WAS ON THE BOARD OF EDUCATION BUT ACTUALLY
COMING UP WITH STRATEGIES AND SOLUTIONS TO SOLVE SOME
REAL PROBLEMS TO ADDRESS A LOT OF THE NEEDS AND ISSUES THAT
OUR OUR YOUNG PEOPLE HAD, OUR STUDENTS HAD AND OUR FAMILY
HAD. >> AND SO I JUST WANT TO THANK
YOU FOR THE CARE AND THE CONSIDERATION AND EVERYTHING
THAT YOU PUT INTO THE WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE IN OUR DISTRICT
OVER THE YEARS. I WANT YOU TO KNOW THAT WE SEE
YOU AND I'M JUST VERY THANKFUL THAT THE DISTRICT HAS HAD THE
OPPORTUNITY TO HAVE SOMEONE LIKE YOU SERVING FOR SO MANY
YEARS. SO THANK YOU
AND CONGRATULATIONS. YOU DESERVE THIS HONOR.
I PRESIDENT I WILL NOW ASK SUPERINTENDENT OF SCHOOLS MARIA
SU TO COME UP AND SAY A FEW WORDS AND ALSO WANT TO
ACKNOWLEDGE THAT WE HAVE TWO SCHOOL BOARD MEMBERS HERE ALITA
FISHER AND PARAG GUPTA AT MIZZOU.
>> THANK YOU. OH, THERE'S A LOT OF SMELLY
SUPPORTERS HERE TONIGHT. TODAY FIRST THANK YOU SO MUCH,
COMMISSIONER SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR FOR HONORING OUR OUR
WONDERFUL MELI AND WHEN I SAY OUR I MEAN SHE IS TRULY A CITY
PERSON BECAUSE SHE STARTED HER CAREER IN THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH. >> I REMEMBER BEING ON THE
HIRING PANEL FOR HER WHEN SHE WAS SHE WAS ACTUALLY APPLYING
FOR A JOB WITHIN THE CITY AND IN THAT ROOM WAS THE
ASSISTANT SUPERINTENDENT OF STUDENT FAMILIES SERVICES
DEPARTMENT KEVIN TRUANT WHO LEANED OVER TO ME AND SAID YOU
BETTER NOT HIRE HER BECAUSE I WANT HER.
>> AND THERE THEN STARTED THE JOURNEY THAT MELISSA HAD MOVING
FROM THE CITY OVER TO THE SCHOOL DISTRICT SHE BROUGHT
WITH HER THE SAME RIGOR RESPONSIBILITY, ACCOUNTABILITY
AND DESIRE FOR GREATNESS FROM THE CITY OVER TO THE SCHOOL
DISTRICT AND SHE HAS DONE THAT FOR MANY, MANY YEARS LEADING
AMAZING TEAMS. >> BUT HONESTLY AT THE END OF
THE DAY IT'S ABOUT MAKING SURE THAT SHE CENTERS HER STUDENTS
AND OUR STUDENTS IN ALL THE DECISIONS THAT SHE MAKES.
>> AND AS YOU CAN SEE HERE BY ALL THE PEOPLE WHO IS THE
HENNEY IN LINE SUPPORTING HER? >> SHE HAS MADE A LASTING
IMPRESSION HERE IN OUR SCHOOL DISTRICT AND I AM POSITIVE
THERE ARE MANY MORE PEOPLE WATCHING AT HOME WATCHING ALL
OVER THE PLACE IN FULL CELEBRATION AND SUPPORT OF
MELLIE. >> I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT
WHEN SHE COMES TO WORK SHE IS BRINGING HER FULL SELF HERE
AND I KNOW THAT HER PARTNER AND HER FRIENDS AND HER
CHILDREN HAVE SHARED HER WITH US AND I AM REALLY HAPPY THAT
NOW SHE GETS TO SPEND MORE TIME WITH HER PARTNER, HER CHILDREN
AND HER FRIENDS AND I FULLY EXPECT TO SEE HER IN DISTRICT
11 BECAUSE THAT'S WHERE I LIVE AS WELL.
AND THEN ALSO ON THE TENNIS COURT BECAUSE SHE IS ALSO MY
HITTING PARTNER ON BEHALF OF THE SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED
SCHOOL DISTRICT, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR HONORING OUR MELILLO
SMITH AND SO MUCH FOR DOING THIS ACCOMMODATION FOR HER.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SUPERINTENDENT YOU HAVE TO SAY A FEW WORDS MALIK
MM. >> WOW.
I DID WRITE SOMETHING BUT IT'S ONLY ONE PAGE SO DON'T WORRY.
I AM SO, SO HUMBLE. TRY NOT TO CRY AND OVERWHELMED
BY THE BEAUTIFUL WORDS SAID I'M SO GRATEFUL TO YOU SUPERVISOR
MALAGA SUPERVISOR CHAN AND SUPERVISOR TO WALTON FOR
YOUR BEAUTIFUL WORDS AND THIS INCREDIBLE GIFT I HAVE BEEN SO
EXTRAORDINARILY BLESSED AND PRIVILEGED TO HAVE SPENT
THE LAST 34 YEARS YOU CUT ME OFF OF YOU.
>> I WANT THAT 34 AS A PUBLIC SERVANT IN SERVICE OF ALL SAN
FRANCISCO RESIDENTS WORKING TOGETHER WITH THEM TO CREATE
AND PUT POLICIES IN PLACE TO IMPROVE THE WELL-BEING OF ALL
ALL OF MY DEAR COLLEAGUES, FRIENDS, FAMILIES WHO ARE HERE
TODAY WHO ARE NOT HERE TODAY AND WHO HAVE PASSED ON.
YOU ALL HAVE MADE ME A BETTER PERSON AND HAVE HONORED ME WITH
YOUR LOVE AND FRIENDSHIP FOR WHICH I AM FOREVER GRATEFUL.
>> TOGETHER WE HAVE DONE GOOD WORK IN SERVICE OF OTHERS AND I
COULD NOT HAVE DONE ANY OF IT WITHOUT YOU.
MANY OF YOU KNOW THAT I DON'T LIKE TO SPEAK IN PUBLIC.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
AND WHEN I MUST I ALWAYS SPEAK OF MY FOUR BEAUTIFUL CHILDREN
AND THE ENDLESS LOVE I HAVE FOR THEM AND THAT LOVE IS EXTENDED
TO THEIR MANY FRIENDS WHO SHARED MEALS AT OUR TABLE
AND SPENT NIGHTS AT OUR HOUSE REEKING HAVOC TOGETHER MAKING
ME LAUGH AND TEACHING ME SO MUCH.
>> DYLAN CAITLIN KYLE AND MILEY ,I KNOW YOU COULDN'T BE HERE
TODAY BUT I WANT TO TELL YOU THAT YOU ARE MY FOUR WIVES MY
FOUR LOUSY YEARS AND MY GREATEST JOY AND MY BEST
TEACHERS. I AM SO INCREDIBLY LUCKY TO BE
YOUR MAMA. YOU FOUR HAVE MADE ME A BETTER
PERSON AND YOU FOUR ARE DEFINITELY WHO I WANT TO BE
WHEN I GROW UP. >> SAN FRANCISCO IS MY HOME.
>> I GREW UP ROAMING ITS STREETS AS DID MY CHILDREN.
TAKING MUNI RIDING MY BIKE AND RUNNING UP AND DOWN ITS
HILLS. IT IS A CITY THAT EDUCATED ME
AND MY FOUR CHILDREN IN ITS PUBLIC SCHOOLS.
>> IT IS A WONDERFULLY DIVERSE CITY AND ITS PUBLIC SCHOOLS ARE
THE RICHNESS OF ITS DIVERSITY. >> ATTENDING PUBLIC SCHOOLS
GAVE ME THE OPPORTUNITY TO MAKE FRIENDS FROM ALL OVER THE CITY
FROM THE BAYVIEW TO THE WESTERN ADDITION TO THE SUNSET TO THE
RICHMOND TO CHINATOWN EVERYWHERE.
AND MANY OF THEM WERE FROM OTHER COUNTRIES AROUND THE
WORLD AS WELL AS OTHER STATES. LATER AS A PEACE CORPS
VOLUNTEER IN NEPAL, I LEARNED MY OWN CULTURE FROM THE
OUTSIDE. >> I EXPERIENCED STRUGGLING TO
BE TO BE UNDERSTOOD AND TO UNDERSTAND WHILE LEARNING A NEW
LANGUAGE. BECAUSE OF THESE EXPERIENCES
BOTH IN MY PERSONAL AND PROFESSIONAL LIFE I HAVE
STRIVED TO PRACTICE CULTURAL HUMILITY TO BE AWARE OF MY OWN
CULTURAL BIASES AND TO LEARN ABOUT AND BE RESPECTFUL OF
OTHER CULTURES. >> NOW MORE THAN EVER WE NEED
TO LEAN INTO THIS PRACTICE OF CULTURAL HUMILITY AND RESIST
THE ATTEMPTS OF THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION TO ERASE SO MANY
OF US. EVERYONE HAS THE RIGHT TO BE
SEEN AND HEARD AND WELCOMED. >> OUR DEMOCRACY DEPENDS ON IT.
I CARRY MY HEART WITH I CARRY YOU ALL IN MY HEART EVERY DAY.
AND AS I START MY NEXT JOURNEY OF RESISTANCE STARTING IN D11,
I WILL CONTINUE TO WORK WITH YOU ALL TO ENSURE THAT WE ALL
HAVE THE RIGHT TO BE SEEN, HEARD AND WELCOMED.
I TRULY BELIEVE THAT A PEOPLE UNITED CAN NEVER BE DIVIDED.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS INCREDIBLE HONOR.
>> THANK YOU. BEAUTIFUL, BEAUTIFUL.
WE'RE GOING TO DO PICTURES
. >> DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR
CHERYL. THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDEL MEN
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM HONORED TO RECOGNIZE CALVIN SWIFT.
PLEASE COME UP TO THE PODIUM. >> FOR OVER 15 YEARS OF SERVICE
MAINTAINING THE CHESTNUT STREET CORRIDOR THROUGH THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC WORKS CORRIDOR PROGRAM.
>> CALVIN WAS BORN AND RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO AND STILL
LIVES HERE TODAY ALONG WITH HIS FATHER, STEPMOTHER AND SISTER.
>> HE IS DEEPLY ROOTED IN HIS IN THIS CITY AND I THINK ALL OF
US IN DISTRICT TO KNOW HOW DEDICATED YOU ARE TO ITS
WELL-BEING. >> NOW CALVIN GOT HIS START
START WITH PUBLIC WORKS IN 2009 THROUGH HUMAN SERVICES AGENCIES
JOB NOW PROGRAM AND TRANSITION TO PUBLIC WORKS AS A PUBLIC
SERVICE AIDE WITH THE CORRIDOR PROGRAM.
>> AND HE HAS NEVER LOOKED BACK.
>> CALVIN'S BEEN WITH THE CITY FOR ALMOST 15 YEARS NOW WITH
ALL OF THEM SPENT ON CHESTNUT STREET.
AND HE IS A CONSISTENT AND FRIENDLY PRESENT TO
MERCHANTS, RESIDENTS AND VISITORS ALIKE.
>> CALVIN SHARED WITH US THAT HE FEELS TRUE HAPPINESS AND A
SENSE OF SATISFACTION BEING PART OF THE CORRIDOR PROGRAM
HELPING KEEP THE STREETS OF SAN FRANCISCO AND ESPECIALLY
CHESTNUT STREET CLEAN, VIBRANT AND BEAUTIFUL.
YOU'VE DESCRIBED THE BUSINESSES AND NEIGHBORS ON CHESTNUT AS
WONDERFUL AND VERY FRIENDLY AND SAYS THAT'S WHY HE'S SO
DEDICATED TO GIVING HIS BEST EVERY SINGLE DAY.
>> AND NOW I KNOW YOU SAY HOW INCREDIBLY PROUD YOU ARE TO
SERVE THIS CITY, BUT I THINK YOU UNDERESTIMATE HOW GRATEFUL
WE ARE FOR YOUR SERVICE. >> I TEXTED A LOT OF PEOPLE
ABOUT YOU. >> AND SO IF I MAY READ A
COUPLE OF THEM. YEAH.
HEART EMOJI. >> HEART EMOJI.
HEART EMOJI FIRE EMOJI. HEART EMOJI.
>> IT'S UNCLEAR WHO LOVES HIM MORE ME OR MY DAUGHTER.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. LOVE YOU.
THANK YOU. AND I DON'T KNOW WHAT I WOULD
DO WITHOUT HIM. HE'S JUST WONDERFUL.
THERE ARE ABOUT TEN OTHERS BUT THEY'RE PRETTY MUCH THE SAME.
SO CALVIN, I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU PERSONALLY FOR BEING KIND
AND GENEROUS TO ME AND ANSWERING MY ANNOYING
QUESTIONS. BUT REALLY FOR BEING SUCH A
WONDERFUL AND DEDICATED PUBLIC SERVANT YOU ARE THE EPITOME OF
WHAT IT MEANS TO BE AN EMPLOYEE OF SAN FRANCISCO AND DPW.
IF EVERY PERSON IN THIS CITY WAS JUST LIKE YOU WE WOULD BE
DOING GREAT AND WE'RE GOING TO BE DOING BETTER BECAUSE OF YOU.
>> SO I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU ON BEHALF OF ME BUT ALSO ON
BEHALF OF THE MARINA COMMUNITY ASSOCIATION, ON BEHALF OF
KAHALA MARINA NEIGHBORS AND MERCHANTS.
AND I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE LONGTIME MARINA RESIDENT
AND PARKS REC AND PARKS COMMISSION PRESIDENT KAT
ANDERSON REPRESENTING THE COMMUNITY AND HER THANKS TO YOU
CALVIN. I JUST CAN'T THANK YOU ENOUGH
FOR YOUR DEDICATION AND YOUR KINDNESS.
>> THE FLOOR IS YOURS. OH, MOST OF ALL I'M GOING TO
THINK OF YOU GUYS BEING HERE TODAY ON MY BEHALF AND I WANT
TO THANK YOU AND EVERYTHING YOU DO.
AND I STARTED HRC BACK IN 2009 AND I WORK MYSELF INTO A JOB
NOW PROGRAM. I USED TO ALWAYS GO OUT LOOKING
FOR JOBS EVERY DAY EVERY DAY AND I LEARNED ONE WITH THE DPW
AND I'VE BEEN HERE EVER SINCE 15 YEARS AND WORKING REAL HARD
. I GET COMPLIMENTS EVERY DAY
EVERY DAY ON THE STREET FROM PEOPLE HANGING OUT THE WINDOWS
PASSING BY CARS HONKING BUSSES HONKING.
SO YOU KNOW AND IT'S A BLESSING.
IT'S A BLESSING TO BE HERE TODAY AND I JUST WANT TO
CONTINUE DOING WHAT I'M DOING AS A GOOD WORKER TO HELP KEEP
THE CITY CLEAN AND I ONLY HAVE LIKE A YEAR LEFT OUT OF MY
THREE YEARS WORKING WITH DPW AND I WOULD LIKE TO CONTINUE
DOING WHAT I'M DOING TO HELP THE PROGRAM OUT AND THE
COMMUNITY AS WELL. >> THANK
DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
>> MAY I HAVE KENNY LAO TO GO TO THE PODIUM?
ON CALI TODAY IT'S MY GREAT HONOR TO RECOGNIZE MR. KENNY
LAO FOR HIS LIFELONG DEDICATION TO TRADITIONAL CHINESE
MEDICINE, CULTURAL PRESERVATION AND COMMUNITY SERVICES.
>> MR. LAO IS A RESPECTED TRAILBLAZER IN HIS FIELD.
A THIRD GENERATION HERBAL MEDICINE PRACTITIONER
AND GRADUATE FROM HALLOWEENTOWN UNIVERSITY OF CHINESE MEDICINE.
HE HAS SPENT DECADES PROVIDING COMPASSIONATE CARE TO SAN
FRANCISCO COMMUNITY. HIS CHINATOWN SHOP HAS SERVED
AS A TRUSTED NEIGHBORHOOD ANCHOR FOR OVER 50 YEARS.
A MILESTONE RECENTLY CELEBRATED BY MANY OF US WHO BENEFIT FROM
HIS WORK BEYOND HIS PRACTICE, MR. LAO HAS HELP ADVANCED
TRADITIONAL CHINESE MEDICINES ON THE INTERNATIONAL STAGE.
HE HAS ORGANIZED IT AND CHAIRED IT MAJOR ACADEMIC CONFERENCES
AND WHOLE LEADERSHIP ROLES IN GLOBAL TCM ASSOCIATIONS.
>> IN 2022 HE FOUND A NASH. HE FOUND THE FIRST NATIONS
TRADITIONAL CHINESE HERBAL MEDICINE EXHIBITION HA RIGHT
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO A REMARKABLE GIFT TO OUR CITY
THAT CELEBRATES CHINESE HERITAGE AND HEALING TRADITIONS
. >> HE'S ALSO A COMMITTED
EDUCATOR AND MENTOR TRAINING FUTURE GENERATIONS AND BUILDING
BRIDGES BETWEEN EAST AND WEST. >> TRADITIONAL KNOWLEDGE
AND MODERN PRACTICES. HIS ADVOCACY LED TO THE
CALIFORNIA STATE ASSEMBLY DECLARING MARCH 18TH, 2024 AS
CALIFORNIA CHINESE MEDICINE DAY RECOGNITION AFTER ENDURING
CONTRIBUTION OF TCM IN PUBLIC HEALTH.
BUT MR. LE'S LEGACY DOES NOT STOP AT MEDICINE.
HE HAS ALSO FOUND CIVIL. >> HE HAS FOUND CIVIC
AND CULTURAL INITIATIVE TO OUTLIVE CHINATOWN POMO SMALL
BUSINESS PRESERVE CHINESE AMERICAN HERITAGE AND FOSTER
CROSS-CULTURAL UNDERSTANDING. >> KENNY LAO THANK YOU FOR YOUR
VISIONARY LEADERSHIP AND YOUR UNWAVERING SERVICE TO CITY OF
SAN FRANCISCO. I'M GOING TO SAY A FEW WORDS
CHINESE AND GIVE ME AN OLD AIG MOLE BAKING POI YEAH SOMETHING
I DON'T KNOW IN HIGH SEAS DE SAN JOSE THINGS GET SO HOT OH
MY GOD I'M DEAD LAO YOU KNOW I SEEN SOMEONE SAY OKAY, YEAH,
YEAH SOME DONKEY
BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS I'M PROUD TO
DECLARE THAT AUGUST 28TH 2025 AS KENNY LAO DAY IN A CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. THANK YOU AND I KNOW MY
COLLEAGUES SUPERVISE THIS ALL TO WOULD ALSO HAVE US FEWER
AND ALSO SUPERVISOR CHAN ALSO HAVE A FEW MORE TO SAY THANK
YOU THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR HONORING KENNY TODAY OR
HONORING MR. LAO TODAY. I THINK IT'S A VERY WELL
DESERVED HONOR. I THINK THAT HE IS REALLY
SOMEONE YOU'RE REALLY SOMEONE THAT BEEN SERVING THE COMMUNITY
IN SO MANY WAY IN SO MANY DIVERSE FASHION BUT I THINK
THAT IT HAS BEEN A VERY LONG TIME FOR THE COMMUNITY THAT
WHEN IT COMES TO OUR TRADITIONAL MEDICINE BE
ACUPUNCTURE OR BE IT HERBAL MEDICINE, IT HAS A STIGMA
ATTACHED TO IT FOR A VERY LONG TIME.
BUT YOU HAVE BEEN WORKING ADVOCATING FOR THE COMMUNITY
TIRELESSLY. YOU'RE MAKING SURE THAT TODAY
THAT I THINK THAT CHINESE HERBAL MEDICINE IS THE WAY IT
IS TODAY IS BECAUSE OF YOUR ADVOCACY WORK THAT PEOPLE
RECOGNIZING THE IMPORTANCE OF IT, THE MEDICINAL ASPECT OF IT
AND RECOGNIZING IT NOW EVEN THE MEDICAID BEING ABLE TO COVER
FOR ACUPUNCTURE TREATMENTS IT'S ALL BECAUSE OF YOUR WORK AND I
THINK YOU'VE BEEN WORKING ON THAT SO FOR SO LONG WITHOUT
MUCH CREDIT. >> SO I APPRECIATE SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR RECOGNIZING YOU TODAY. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
SERVICE. I LOOK FORWARD TO SEE MORE TO
COME AND THANK YOU AND WE ARE GRATEFUL AND CONGRATULATIONS ON
THIS HONEST ADVISOR AND THANK YOU FOR BRINGING THIS BEFORE US
. YOU KNOW I HAVE ENJOYED GETTING
TO LEARN MORE ABOUT HOLISTIC MEDICINE AND TRADITIONAL
MEDICINE THROUGH YOUR WORK AND I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE
THE IMPACT THAT YOU HAVE ON CHINATOWN THROUGH YOUR WORK
AND LEADERSHIP WITH THE HCA AND ENSURING THAT THERE ARE
INITIATIVES IN CHINATOWN THAT WE'RE EXCITED ABOUT.
I SEE YOU NANCY, AND I SEE YOU, DENNIS IN EVERY MEETING THAT WE
HAVE TOGETHER I COME AWAY WITH A VERY LONG TO DO LIST
AND THERE'S A LOT THAT WE'RE EXCITED ABOUT.
SO THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AS A MERCHANT
AND WITHIN THE HEALTH CARE SPACE ON THE BOARD, PRESIDENT
GENTLEMAN HONOR ROLL SYMBOLIZES ESTEEMED GUESTS DEAR FRIENDS IS
MY PROFOUND GRATITUDE THAT I STAND HERE BEFORE YOU TODAY TO
BE HONEST ABOUT THIS INCREDIBLE CITY WE DAY THAT BEARS MY NAME
CAN BE OUT THERE IS IS MORE THAN A PERSONAL MILESTONE IS A
CELEBRATION OF THE VALUE CONDITIONS AND QUALITIES PUT
DURING THE YEAR HAVE SUFFERED MY LIFE AND THE LIVES OF SO
MANY BEFORE ME I EXTEND MY DEEPEST GRATITUDE TO A
SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISORS SUCH AS SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR
RECOGNIZE RECOGNIZED MY JOURNEY WITH THIS BILL AND AND THE
BOARD AND THE POPULATION 45 YEARS AGO WHEN I LIFE IN SAN
FRANCISCO I LOVE THE CITY IMMEDIATELY FROM THE MOMENT I
STEP ON TO THE STORIES STREET I FEEL CALMNESS AND SO POWERFUL
THAT I KNEW I WASN'T JUST ARRIVING SOMEONE SOMETHING
VALUABLE I WAS COMING HOME. DID THE CITY OF DIVERSE CULTURE
AND THE GREAT COMMUNITY WELCOMED ME.
THEY CHOSE ME AND INSPIRED ME. >> I FOLLOWED THE PATH OF MY
FATHER AND GRANDFATHER. IT'S OF HOLLAND TYPICALLY
THEY'LL LEAVE YOU AS AN AND HELPING OUT OF THE
TRANSITION THE CHINESE MEDICINE AS A FAMILY WE HAVE SERVICE THE
COMMUNITY FOR THIS IMPETUS FOR MORE THAN 60 YEARS VISIONARIES
AND OF PIECES VISIONARIES AND OF PUZZLES, PATIENCE
AND PURPOSE FOR THE BUSINESS OUT AS AN ENTERPRISE
CORPORATION WE HAVE REPORTED THAT IN SUPPORTING LONG KNEW
THE WISDOM BUT THE CULTURAL LOCUS OF LEADING THE OLDER
STYLES THAT LITTLE BIT IS IN STORE IN SAN FRANCISCO SINCE
1972 IS NOT ABOUT COMMERCE BUT CULTURE COGNITION AND THE
CONTRIBUTION MY SERVICE HAS EXTENDED BEYOND THE STOREFRONT
FOR 18 YEARS I HAD THE PRIVILEGE TO SERVE AS THE
CHAIRMAN OF OF THE AMERICAN ASSOCIATION.
>> I FIND THAT THE YOUNG UNIVERSITY OF CHINESE MEDICINE
YOU AS A CAMPUS TO EMPOWER FUTURE GENERATIONS WITH A
FORMAL EDUCATION I POLITY ACTIVITIES THE FIRST TIME THIS
IS AN EXHIBITION HALL WHY IN THE HEART OF OF CHARLOTTE
TOWN LOCATED ON THE SECOND FLOOR OF THE CHINATOWN POST
OFFICE SERVING THE COMMUNITY AND THE VISITORS TO LEARN THE
BENEFIT OF CHINESE MEDICINE MY CONTRIBUTION TO THE COMMUNITY
COULD NOT BE POSSIBLE WITHOUT THOSE WHO STOOD BESIDE ME.
I'VE BEEN TO MY COLLEAGUES, MY MENTORS, MY FRIENDS AND SPECIAL
MY FAMILY, MY WIFE SUE AND MY BROTHER EVERYONE AND AND TOO
MANY GOOD FRIENDS. THAT'S A LIE.
SORRY. AND JOSEPH AND TAMMY AND TRINI
AND NANCY AND DENNIS THEY ARE A VERY COULD BEEN WITHOUT THEIR
SUPPORT. WITHOUT THEIR SUPPORT.
I DON'T THINK SO. I COULD I COULD THEN REACH THIS
POINT TODAY THAT CAN ALLOW THEY BE A CELEBRATION NOT ONLY OF
MEN AND WOMEN STORY BUT THE CITY'S BEAUTIFUL STORY OF
IMMIGRANT WITH SILENCE, CULTURAL RICHNESS AND HARMONY.
THANK YOU FOR THE BOTTOM OF MY HEART.
THANK YOU FOR ALL OF THE SUPERVISORS AGAIN THANK YOU FOR
GIVING ME ANOTHER BIRTHDAY FROM THIS YEAR AND I JUST THOUGHT
THAT I REALLY REMEMBER AND CELEBRATE ON THE IF EVERY
YEAR FROM NOW AND FOREVER. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOU
AND I THANK YOU SO JUST ONE TWO
AND THREE CUP PENICK COME ON UP .
I FEEL LIKE I'M ABOUT TO HEAR ABOUT A REAL ESTATE DEAL.
>> COLLEAGUES, TODAY I'M PRESENTING A SPECIAL
COMMENDATION TO ANDREW CO PENICK WHO IS RETIRING THIS
MONTH AFTER MORE THAN THREE DECADES IN PUBLIC SERVICE
INCLUDING THE PAST SEVEN YEARS AS SAN FRANCISCO'S DIRECTOR OF
REAL ESTATE SINCE 2018 AND RICO HAS LED A DIVISION OF 300
EMPLOYEES RESPONSIBLE FOR MANAGING MORE THAN 4,000,000FT2
OF PUBLIC FACILITIES AND HANDLING REAL ESTATE
TRANSACTIONS FOR MORE THAN 50 CITY DEPARTMENTS IN A CITY
WHERE EVERY SQUARE FOOT IS HARD FOUGHT AND HARD WON AND RICO
HAS BROUGHT SECRETS THE STRATEGY, CREATIVITY AND AN
UNFLAPPABLE CALM TO SOME OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST COMPLEX
AND HIGH STAKES NEGOTIATIONS. UNDER HIS LEADERSHIP, THE CITY
FINALIZED MAJOR DEALS THAT WILL HELP SAN FRANCISCO ACHIEVE ITS
PUBLIC SAFETY, HEALTH, HOUSING AND WORKFORCE GOALS.
HE NEGOTIATED A LEASE AT 1455 MARKET STREET TO ESTABLISH A
MODERN SEISMICALLY SAFE CAMPUS THAT NOW HOUSES 11 CITY
DEPARTMENTS AND PROVIDES THOUSANDS OF PUBLIC EMPLOYEES
WITH A SAFER, MORE FUNCTIONAL PLACE TO WORK.
HE ALSO LED THE CITY'S ACQUISITION OF MULTIPLE PARCELS
TO BUILD A UNIFIED SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT
TRAINING FACILITY CONSOLIDATING OUTDATED SITES INTO ONE FUTURE
FOCUSED CAMPUS. NOW IN PLANNING AT 1236 CARROLL
AVENUE IN THE BAYVIEW. ONCE COMPLETED THE FACILITY
WILL SERVE 1700 FIREFIGHTERS AND STRENGTHEN THE CITY'S
EMERGENCY PREPAREDNESS FOR DECADES TO COME.
AND RICO'S CONTRIBUTIONS DON'T ALWAYS MAKE HEADLINES BUT
THEY'RE ESSENTIAL TO THE WORK OF CITY GOVERNMENT.
HE'S HELPED BUILD THE PHYSICAL INFRASTRUCTURE THAT ENABLES OUR
DEPARTMENTS TO SERVE THE PUBLIC MORE EFFECTIVELY, EFFICIENTLY
AND EQUITABLY. BEFORE BECOMING DIRECTOR,
ENRICO SERVED AS DEPUTY DIRECTOR OF THE CITY'S REAL
ESTATE DIVISION, DEPUTY GENERAL COUNSEL OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
REDEVELOPMENT AGENCY AND CHIEF REAL ESTATE COUNSEL FOR THE
CITY OF ALAMEDA WHERE HE PLAYED A KEY ROLE IN TRANSFORMING THE
FORMER FORMER NAVAL AIR STATION INTO WHAT IS NOW ALAMEDA POINT
A SKILLED ATTORNEY AND STRATEGIC THINKER AND RICO
HAS CONSISTENTLY BROUGHT LEGAL RIGOR AND PRAGMATISM TO HIS
PUBLIC SERVICE. A NAVY VETERAN AND AND RICO
BEGAN HIS LEGAL CAREER IN THE JUDGE ADVOCATE GENERAL JUDGE
ADVOCATE GENERAL'S CORPS REPRESENTING THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT AS A PROSECUTOR AND PROVIDING DEFENSE COUNSEL
FOR SAILORS AND MARINES. HE WAS HONORABLY DISCHARGED
WITH WITH THE RANK OF LIEUTENANT COMMANDER.
HE HOLDS A JURIS DOCTOR FROM GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY
LAW SCHOOL AND A BACHELOR'S DEGREE FROM THE GEORGE
WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY IN WASHINGTON DC.
>> THROUGHOUT HIS CAREER ENRICO HAS BEEN KNOWN FOR HIS NO
NONSENSE APPROACH AND METICULOUS ATTENTION TO
DETAIL. HE'S ALSO BEEN A GRACIOUS
AND GENEROUS COLLEAGUE NO MATTER HOW COMPLICATED THE
TASK. HE WORKS BEHIND THE SCENES
NEGOTIATING COMPLEX DEALS, MODERNIZING CITY FACILITIES
AND ENSURING PUBLIC SERVICE. >> PUBLIC SERVANTS HAVE SAFE
FUNCTIONAL SPACES IN WHICH TO DO THEIR JOBS AND THAT'S MADE A
REAL AND LASTING IMPACT FOR SAN FRANCISCO.
I FEEL FORTUNATE TO HAVE BEEN ABLE TO WORK A LITTLE BIT WITH
HIM AND I'M DEEPLY GRATEFUL FOR THE LEADERSHIP, PROFESSIONALISM
AND WISE COUNSEL ALONG THE WAY. WE'RE GOING TO MISS YOU
AND RICO, BUT YOUR RETIREMENT IS WELL-EARNED AND WELL
DESERVED. >> AND WE'LL JUST HAVE TO IT
UP SOMEHOW. SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES WOULD
ALSO LIKE TO SAY SOME NICE THINGS ABOUT YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHANDLER THANK YOU PRESENT A MAN DOMIN DIRECTOR OF
HENIG AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR ALL YOUR WORK.
THERE WERE TIMES I THINK THERE WERE TIMES ME AS BUDGET CHAIR
PUT YOU THROUGH SOME TOUGH SITUATION AND SOME TOUGH
QUESTIONING. YOU JUST KEPT GOING AND VERY
EVEN HERE WITH YOUR PRESENTATION THE ANSWER
QUESTION LIKE IT IS I THINK THERE WERE TIMES EVEN MY OUR
FORMER BOARD PRESIDENT AARON PESKIN GAVE YOU A HARD TIME.
AND YOU KNOW, EVEN THE FORMER VICE CHAIR SUPERVISOR AZAR
SAFAI ALSO GAVE YOU A HARD TIME AND TIME AND TIME AGAIN WE
QUESTION YOU AND WE CHALLENGED YOU.
>> BUT YOU KEPT YOU KEPT IT TOGETHER.
YOU EXPLAIN WHERE YOU WERE COMING FROM BUT YOU ALSO WERE
OPEN MINDED. YOU ACTUALLY UNDERSTOOD THAT
POLICYMAKERS AT TIMES WE WE MAKE COMMENTS AND WE PUSH BACK.
BUT YOU YOU UNDERSTOOD WHAT WE WERE TRYING TO DO AND THAT WE
CAME TOGETHER AND WITH THOSE BACK AND FORTH I WANT TO SAY
CONSISTENTLY YOU REALLY SERVE IN THE BEST INTEREST OF SAN
FRANCISCANS YOUR SERVICE AT LEAST FOR ME BOTH ON A PERSONAL
AND A PROFESSIONAL LEVEL. WELL WORK HARD AND WE'RE JUST
SO GRATEFUL BECAUSE OF YOUR SERVICE.
SAN FRANCISCO AS A CITY GOVERNMENT AND AS A CITY HAS
MADE REALLY SOUND FINANCIAL DECISIONS FOR OUR CITY BOTH
IN OUR ASSET MANAGEMENT BUT ALSO IN OUR DECISION MAKING
BOTH FOR THE PAST GENERATION AND IN BUILDING THAT FOUNDATION
FOR THE GENERATIONS TO COME. AND SO WE'RE REALLY I CONCUR
WITH PRESIDENT AMANDO AND WE WILL MISS YOU.
I MISS NOT JUST YOUR PERSONAL LIKE YOUR PROFESSIONAL SKILLS
AND EXPERIENCE BUT ALSO YOUR PERSONAL CITY YOU KNOW JUST HOW
YOU'RE CONSISTENT ABOUT IT AND WE ALSO GRATEFUL HOW YOU
ALWAYS WORK WITH THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST AND AND
AND WITH US AND MAKING IT WORK .
>> SO THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MAN AND I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU DIRECTOR PINNICK
FOR ALL OF YOUR WORK. >> I THINK I ONE YOU ALWAYS
HAVE THE ANSWER TO A LOT OF PROBLEMS THAT NEED TO BE SOLVED
PARTICULARLY AROUND WHAT TO DO WITH FACILITIES, HOW TO BENEFIT
THE CITY WITH THE FACILITIES THAT ARE AVAILABLE AND YOU KNOW
YOU ALWAYS WORK TOWARDS A YES YOU DON'T COME IN HERE AND AND
SAY THINGS ARE NOT POSSIBLE BUT I REALLY WANT TO APPRECIATE YOU
FOR THE FACT THAT YOU ALSO CONNECT WITH COMMUNITY AND YOU
LED COMMUNITY GROUPS AND MEMBERS OF COMMUNITY HAVE
CONVERSATIONS WITH YOU SO THEY CAN LEARN HOW TO BE SUCCESSFUL
IN SOME OF THE THINGS THAT THEY WANT TO DO WITH CITY BUILDINGS
AS WELL. SO I WANT TO JUST APPRECIATE
YOU FOR THAT AND NOT A LOT OF PEOPLE IN YOUR ROLE WILL ALLOW
THAT OPPORTUNITY AND HAVE THOSE CONVERSATION WITH PEOPLE
IN COMMUNITY. SO I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR ALL
OF YOUR SERVICE OVER THE YEARS LIKE PRESIDENT MANDELA AND I
WILL DEFINITELY MISS YOU AND YOUR WORK AND THANK YOU FOR
ALL OF THE THINGS THAT WE'VE ACCOMPLISHED.
OBVIOUSLY IN MY DISTRICT ONE OF WHICH PRESIDENT MAILMAN SPOKE
ABOUT AND I'LL BE TALKING ABOUT A LITTLE LATER BUT JUST
DEFINITELY APPRECIATE YOU FOR ALL OF YOUR SERVICE.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDELA AND THANK YOU FOR DOING THIS AND RICO, I AM
GOING TO MISS YOU. >> IN ADDITION TO THE THINGS
THAT MY COLLEAGUES HAVE SAID, I WANT TO HIGHLIGHT WHAT A
CREATIVE THINKER YOU ARE AND THAT'S NOT THOSE WORDS ARE
NOT OFTEN ATTACHED TO LIKE REAL ESTATE AND MANAGEMENT, YOU
KNOW. >> BUT YOU EMBODY THAT TO
SUPERVISOR WALTON'S COMMENTS YOU ALWAYS COME TO THE TABLE
WITH A PROBLEM SOLVING APPROACH BUT IT'S MORE THAN JUST LIKE
YOUR KNOWLEDGE, YOUR TECHNICAL SKILLS IT'S ALSO YOUR
CREATIVITY OF CONNECTING THE DOTS ACROSS DIFFERENT AREAS
IN NOT JUST YOUR DEPARTMENT BUT EVERYONE ELSE.
I HAVE REALLY APPRECIATED YOUR SUPPORT ON ANY NUMBER OF ISSUES
DURING MY WORK IN MY DISTRICT BUT ALSO SEEING YOU SOLVE SO
MANY OF OUR ISSUES AS A CITY FOR OUR CITY GOVERNMENT AND I
HAVE JUST SO APPRECIATED YOUR ENORMOUS BRAIN AND YOUR
CREATIVITY AND I HOPE THAT WHOEVER STEPS INTO YOUR ROLE
DOES IT WITH AS MUCH GRACE AND I KNOW THAT YOUR COWORKERS
LOVE YOU SO WE'RE NOT THE ONLY ONES THAT ARE GOING TO MISS YOU
BUT I WISH YOU ALL THE BEST IN THIS NEXT STEP IN YOUR LIFE.
>> THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU'VE DONE FOR US.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR IT IS HURTFUL THAT YOU THINK THAT REAL ESTATE
LAWYERS ARE NOT CREATIVE AND RICO PANIC.
>> PRESIDENT VANDEMAN MADAM CLERK SUPERVISORS ENRICO PENICK
DIRECTOR OF REAL ESTATE. WELL AT LEAST FOR ANOTHER TWO
DAYS I AM A BIT OVERWHELMED MAN AND THANK YOU FOR THIS HONOR.
IT WAS UNEXPECTED. I CONSIDER MYSELF JUST TO BE A
RUN OF THE MILL PUBLIC SERVANT AND I COME TO WORK, I DO MY JOB
AND I DON'T REALLY EXPECT ALL OF THIS BUT IT IS MUCH
APPRECIATE IT. I HAVE TO SAY THAT IT'S BEEN IT
IS WITH EXCITEMENT AND SADNESS THAT I TAKE THIS NEXT STEP
AND RETIRE FROM CITY EMPLOYMENT .
THE DIRECTOR OF REAL ESTATE POSITION HAS BEEN ONE OF THE
HARDEST JOBS I'VE EVER HAD BUT IT'S ALSO BEEN EXTREMELY
REWARDING. THE CITY'S REAL ESTATE NEEDS
IN ITS PORTFOLIO ARE CONSTANTLY CHANGING.
I AM PROUD TO HAVE PLAYED A SMALL PART IN MEETING THE
CITY'S REAL ESTATE NEEDS. I AM THANKFUL FOR THE
EXPERIENCE AND APPRECIATE WORKING WITH EACH AND EVERY ONE
OF YOU. MANY OF MY STAFF ARE WATCHING
ON S.F. GOV TV RIGHT NOW. THEY DIDN'T HAVE THE LUXURY OF
BEING ABLE TO COME TO THE CHAMBERS.
AND I WANTED TO GIVE THEM A SHOUT OUT BECAUSE WITHOUT THE
EXCELLENT STAFF OF THE REAL ESTATE DIVISION AND THAT OF MY
SUCCESS IN THIS ROLE WOULD HAVE BEEN POSSIBLE.
>> I ALSO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE AND THANK MY WIFE CATHERINE WHO
IS IN THE AUDIENCE FOR HER LOVE, SUPPORT AND PATIENCE.
>> THIS ISN'T THE END OF MY JOURNEY.
I'M SURE THERE'S ANOTHER CHALLENGE ANOTHER OPPORTUNITY
ON THE HORIZON AND I'LL BE READY FOR IT WHEN IT COMES.
>> BUT FOR NOW I WANT TO TAKE THIS PAUSE AND ENJOY A
WELL-DESERVED BREAK. >> THANK YOU ALL.
I REALLY APPRECIATE YOU AND I'M GOING TO INVITE YOU TO COME
INTO THE WELL
AND ALL RIGHT, FRIENDS, WE'RE ONLY AN HOUR BEHIND.
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER
ITEMS? >> 56 THROUGH 59 COMPRISE THE 3
P.M. SPECIAL ORDER ITEM 56 IS THE PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS
INTERESTED IN THE DECISION OF PUBLIC WORKS DATED JUNE 25TH
2025 TO APPROVE A TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP FOR A THREE LOT
SUBDIVISION AT 1979 MISSION STREET.
ITEM 57 IS THE MOTION THAT APPROVES THE PUBLIC WORKS
DECISION AND APPROVES THE TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP.
>> ITEM 58 IS THE MOTION TO CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE
PUBLIC WORKS DECISION AND DISAPPROVE THE TENTATIVE
PARCEL MAP BASED UPON THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ADOPTING A
WRITTEN FINDING FINDINGS IN SUPPORT OF THE DISAPPROVAL
ITEM 59 WOULD BE THAT MOTION TO DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF
FINDINGS. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES, WE HAVE BEFORE US AN APPEAL OF A TENTATIVE MAP
APPROVAL BY PUBLIC WORKS FOR THE PROJECT AT 1979 MISSION
STREET AFTER THE HEARING THE BOARD WILL VOTE ON WHETHER TO
APPROVE OR CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE DECISION OF
PUBLIC WORKS UNLESS THERE ARE OBJECTIONS.
>> I PROPOSE THAT WE PROCEED AS FOLLOWS WE WILL GIVE UP TO TEN
MINUTES FOR A PRESENTATION BY THE APPELLANTS AND THEN WE'LL
TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT FROM SPEAKERS TWO MINUTES PER
SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL.
THEN WE'LL HAVE A PRESENTATION OF UP TO TEN MINUTES FROM THE
CITY DEPARTMENTS. >> THEN WE'LL HAVE A
PRESENTATION OF UP TO TEN MINUTES FROM THE PROJECT
SPONSOR. THAT WILL BE FOLLOWED BY PUBLIC
COMMENT OF UP TO TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER IN OPPOSITION TO
THE APPEAL. AND FINALLY WE WILL GIVE THE
APPELLANT THREE MINUTES FOR REBUTTAL.
ANY OBJECTIONS? >> I DON'T SEE ANY OBJECTIONS.
ALL RIGHT. SEEING NO OBJECTIONS, THE
PUBLIC HEARING WILL PROCEED AS INDICATED AND IS NOW OPEN.
AND I WOULD ASK THE APPELLANTS TO COME FORWARD.
HELLO MR. SOLOMON. >> HELLO.
ARE YOU NEEDING ASSISTANCE ON THE ON THE TECH?
>> THERE WE GO. THERE WE GO.
GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR THE SUPERVISORS.
BEFORE WE GET STARTED, I JUST WONDERED IF YOU RECEIVED THE
EMAIL ABOUT STRIKING THE FIRST TWO.
>> YES, WE DID. IF YOU COULD JUST ANNOUNCE THAT
ON THE RECORD AND SPEAK INTO THAT MICROPHONE AS BEST YOU
CAN. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> SO WITH REGARD TO THIS APPEAL, WE'VE DECIDED TO STRIKE
THE FIRST TWO PORTIONS OF THE APPEAL AND WE'RE GOING TO
CONTINUE WITH THE THIRD PORTION WHICH PERTAINS PRIMARILY TO
SAFETY AND SAFETY OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> OKAY. SO HELLO.
MY NAME IS ALI. I LIVE ON CAPP STREET ACROSS
FROM MARSHALL ELEMENTARY. >> I'M A NURSE AT S.F. GENERAL
AND I WORK DAILY WITH NURSES, EMT, SOCIAL WORKERS AND POLICE.
DEEPLY AWARE OF THE AFFORDABILITY CRISIS IN S.F.
I'M ALSO ACUTELY AWARE OF THE HEALTH ISSUES THAT CONCERN
COMMUNITY MEMBERS ACCESSING SAFETY NET HEALTH CARE.
>> I ALSO REPRESENT A GROUP OF NEIGHBORS AND MARSHALL FAMILIES
THE DEFENDERS OF MARSHALL LIVING IN THE IMMEDIATE
VICINITY OF THE PROPOSED 1979 MISSION PROJECT WHO SHARE
CONCERNS ABOUT THE PROPOSED LOT SUBDIVISION AND THE
IMPLICATIONS FOR THE PUBLIC HEALTH AND SAFETY OF THE
NEIGHBORHOOD ESPECIALLY THE KIDS WHO ATTEND MARSHALL
ELEMENTARY. >> WE APPEAL THIS SUBDIVISION
AND MAP AS THE INTENT OF SUBDIVIDING IN 1979 MISSION
ADVANCES THE PLACEMENT OF AN OVERBUILT PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING PCH BUILDING WITH ASSOCIATED SUBSTANCE AND PSYCH
TREATMENT SERVICES WHICH WILL EXACERBATE THE ALREADY
DANGEROUS CONDITIONS FOUND AROUND MARSHALL ELEMENTARY
WHICH SERVES AT RISK STUDENTS INCLUDING IMMIGRANT, HOMELESS,
LOW INCOME AND STUDENTS OF COLOR.
>> STATED SIMPLY IF THIS APPEAL IS DENIED THEN PROJECT SPONSORS
CAN SUBDIVIDE FINANCE AND BUILD PCH AND ASSOCIATED SERVICES
WHICH WILL ENDANGER THE MARSHALL COMMUNITY.
IF THE APPEAL IS UPHELD THAT DANGER WILL BE PREVENTED.
>> AS MARSHALL ELEMENTARY COMMUNITY MEMBERS WE SEEK TO
AMPLIFY THE VOICES OF MARSHALL FAMILIES WHO ARE UNABLE TO
ATTEND THIS HEARING BECAUSE OF THE SUMMER VACATION.
>> WE NEED THE SUPERVISORS TO GO ON RECORD ON WHETHER THEY
SUPPORT A DRUG ALCOHOL AND PSYCH TREATMENT CENTER ON
TOP OF A PRIMARY SCHOOL FULL OF AT RISK STUDENTS.
>> THE DEFENDERS STRONGLY SUPPORT THE CORE PREMISE OF THE
PLAZA 16 COALITION TO EXPAND AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOCUSED ON
WORKING CLASS AND LOW INCOME FAMILIES.
DEFENDERS DEMAND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN MISSION HOUSING
GRANT THE APPEAL UNLESS IT CAN SHOW A SUBSTANTIVE
AND TRANSPARENT MANNER HOW THE PROJECT PROMOTES HEALTH
AND SAFETY IN THE CONTEXT OF OUR NEIGHBORHOOD NOT AS A
STANDALONE DISCRETE CONCEPT BUT IN THE ACTUAL CURRENT CONTEXT
IN OUR APPEAL. >> DEFENDERS OF MARSHALL WILL
SHOW THAT THE CITY AND ASSOCIATED NONPROFITS HAVE
A POOR TRACK RECORD OF FOLLOWING THROUGH ON PROMISES
TO MITIGATE DANGEROUS IMPACTS FROM THEIR PROJECTS WITH FEW
AVENUES FOR REDRESS WHEN CITY FUNDED NONPROFITS FAIL TO MEET
THEIR OBLIGATIONS. THE SIGHTING OF PCH NEXT TO A
SCHOOL WITH VULNERABLE STUDENTS IS DANGEROUS AS A STUDY SHOWS
IT DRAWS AS MUCH VIOLENT CRIME AS LIQUOR STORES THAT PCH IS
DANGEROUS AT THIS SITE AS IT ENTERS EXPRESSION OF SYSTEMIC
AND STRUCTURAL RACISM THAT WOULD BE UNACCEPTABLE AT ANY
OTHER ELEMENTARY SCHOOL IN S.F..
>> THE MARSHALL COMMUNITY HAS BORNE MANY TIMES OVER THE
BURDEN OF DIFFICULT SOCIAL SERVICES THAT ANY OTHER
NEIGHBORHOOD SAVE THE TENDERLOIN ALSO THAT WE IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD HAVE WELCOMED FOR 100% AFFORDABLE BUILDINGS
AND WE SUPPORT MORE MARSHALL PARENTS KNOW RESIDENTS MAKE
GREAT NEIGHBORS. >> ANYONE INCLUDING THE PROJECT
SPONSORS WHO TRY TO WEAPONIZE THE TERM NIMBY IN REFERENCE TO
OUR LEGITIMATE LOCAL CONCERNS OF OUR NEIGHBORHOOD IS
DISINGENUOUS AND IN DENIAL. >> AFFORDABLE HEALTH HOUSING IS
NOT A BINARY OF BEING FOR OR AGAINST CITING PCH HERE IS A
QUESTION OF SAFETY, NUANCE AND PROPORTION WITHIN THE
CURRENT CONTEXT OF THIS NEIGHBORHOOD.
THE SUBDIVISION WILL HAVE SIGNIFICANT CONSEQUENCES FOR
THIS NEIGHBORHOOD. ITS LONG TERM HEALTH,
SUSTAINABILITY AND PROSPERITY AS WELL AS OTHER COMMUNITIES
FACING THE SAME TYPES OF PROJECTS IN THE FUTURE.
>> THE NIMBYS HERE ARE THE PROJECT SPONSORS WHO LIVE
ELSEWHERE FORCING UNDESIRABLE LAND USES IN THE BACKYARD OF
BROWN KIDS SCHOOLS NOT THEIRS. >> WITH RESPECT TO THIS PROJECT
YIMBY NOW MEANS YES IN MARSHALL'S BACKYARD.
>> SO WITH REGARD TO HISTORY OF OUR NEIGHBORHOOD MARSHALL
NEIGHBORHOOD HAS BEEN DESIGNATED AS AT RISK AND IS
OVERBURDENED WITH MANY SOCIAL SERVICE FACILITIES SOME OF
WHICH NEGATIVELY IMPACT THE COMMUNITY AND WHICH NONPROFIT
OPERATORS INCLUDING THE PROJECT SPONSORS DON'T SECURE.
CURRENTLY 45 AGENCIES AND FACILITIES DIRECTED TO
HOMELESS SUPPORT ARE CLUSTERED WITHIN A THREE BLOCK RADIUS OF
THIS SITE. SUPERVISOR WALDEN AND MAHMOOD
HAVE ALREADY SPOKEN TO THIS. JUST TODAY MARSHALL ELEMENTARY
IS DESIGNATED A SENSITIVE COMMUNITY PER VAGUE AND THE
PROPOSED SB 50 2000 TO RESIDENT SUPPORTED A HOMELESS CENTER FOR
160 FIVE CAP WHICH IS MISSION NEIGHBORHOOD RESEARCH CENTER
BECAUSE THE HOMELESS PEOPLE ARE ALREADY THERE AS SOON AS THE
FACILITY OPENED. THE 100 BLOCK OF CAPP WITH THE
SECTION EIGHT MISSION PLAZA PARKING EGRESS HAS BEEN
CONTINUALLY BLOCKED BY ADDICTS AND HOMELESS PEOPLE SLEEPING
IN THE DOORWAYS. >> IN 2015 THE PROJECT RESPECT
FOR ADDICTS WAS SIGHTED AT ST JOHN'S CHURCH AT 15TH
AND JULIAN. THIS HAS BECOME A MAGNET FOR
DRUG USERS IMMEDIATELY DETERIORATING CONDITIONS AT
15TH AND JULIAN INCLUDING A FIRE AT THE CHURCH.
NEARLY 200 DAYS OF OF MISSION LOCAL REPORTING HAS SHOWN THE
AREA WILL NOT STAY CLEAR AND SAFE UNLESS IT IS
CONTINUALLY SWEPT BY POLICE. >> WE HAVE OUR SLIDES IN APRIL
2024 THE CITY WITH THE SUPPORT OF FORMER D9 SUPERVISOR RONEN
SITED MISSION CABINS AT 1979 MISSION NEXT TO MARSHALL.
OVER THE OBJECTIONS OF THE MARSHALL COMMUNITY THE MARSHALL
COMMUNITY OBJECTED BECAUSE WE HAVE SEEN THAT THESE FACILITIES
ARE MAGNETS ONCE MISSION CABINS WENT IN.
THE CONDITIONS AROUND THE ENTRANCE WORSENED ONCE CABINS
ESTABLISHED GUNFIRE BEGINS AND THE BULLETS KEPT FLYING
AND THE BODIES KEPT PILING UP. ONE OF THE VICTIMS I ACTUALLY
TOOK CARE OF AT THE HOSPITAL THAT DAY.
>> TARGET OF GUNFIRE ENTERS MARSHALL AFTER SHOOTING ON CAPP
STREET. MISSION CABINS STILL CAN'T
SECURE EAST SIDE OF MISSION STREET.
>> ONE PROJECT SPONSOR MISSION HOUSING OWNS LA PHENIX
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AT 1950 MISSION.
ALSO A HOME TO A HEADSTART PRE-K PROGRAM.
>> RESIDENTS OF PHENIX AFFORDABLE HOUSING HAVE ASKED
TO MOVE TO ANOTHER BUILDING BECAUSE STREET CONDITIONS ARE
NO PLACE TO RAISE A FAMILY. HOUSING IS FAILING TO SECURE
THE HEAD START FACILITY AND ADDICTS HAVE INFILTRATED
YOUTH SPACES IN A DESPERATE MOVE TO CLEAN UP THEIR ACT
PRIOR TO THIS HEARING. MISSION HOUSING HAS SCRAMBLED
TO CLEAN UP THE WEST SIDE OF MISSION BETWEEN 14TH AND 15TH
STREETS. THIS HAS ONLY DRIVEN ADDICTS
ACROSS THE STREET AND FURTHER INTO THE AREA SURROUNDING
MARSHALL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL. >> MISSION HOUSING DID NOT TAKE
CARE TO ARCHITECT THE SIDEWALK FRONTAGE OF 1950 MISSION TO
MINIMIZE THE OPPORTUNITIES FOR BAD ACTORS.
CAN WE TRUST THEM TO DESIGN THE BART PLAZA FRONTAGE IN THE
SUBDIVISION FOR SAFETY WITHOUT HAND-HOLDING?
THE EVIDENCE INDICATES THAT THESE NONPROFITS WILL NOT
SECURE PCH AND THAT PCH WILL THUS BE DANGEROUS TO MARSHALL
STUDENTS. >> CRIME DANGER A STUDY
INTENDED TO DISPEL NIMBY OBJECTIONS TO SITING PCH
SUGGESTED SUBSTANCE TREATMENT CENTERS LEAD TO VIOLENT CRIME
RATES SIMILAR TO THOSE OBSERVED AT LIQUOR STORES.
CITY WOULD NEVER APPROVE A LIQUOR STORE ADJACENT TO ANY
OTHER ELEMENTARY SCHOOL IN S.F..
THE SFPD AND SUCCESSIVE DAYS APPEAR TO HAVE NEVER ADDED DRUG
FREE SCHOOL ZONE ENHANCEMENTS FOR ARRESTS THAT HAVE BEEN MADE
AROUND A MARSHALL AROUND MARSHALL AND HAS BEEN OF NO USE
IN SECURING THE SCHOOL. CITING THE SUBSTANCE A
SUBSTANCE ABUSE TREATMENT FACILITY NEAR AN OPEN DRUG
BAZAAR CAN BE DEADLY TO THOSE IN RECOVERY IF WE SAW EARLIEST.
EARLIER THIS MONTH WITH THE TRAGIC DEATH OF MELVIN BYLON AT
A GIO FACILITY IN THE TENDERLOIN, MR. BYLON STATED
HE'D RATHER BE IN SAN QUENTIN THAN GO THROUGH REENTRY IN THE
FENTANYL RIDDEN STREETS OF THE TITLE.
>> SADLY, MR. BYLON RELAPSED AND OD'D WHILE IN CUSTODY.
DANGER OF RACISM IS REAL. PCH IS CLUSTERED IN A CENSUS
TRACT WITH HIGHER LATINO POPULATIONS WHICH ONLY
REPRODUCES THE STRUCTURAL RACISM THAT EXISTS.
RACIST TRAUMA DAMAGES YOUTH YOUTH OF COLOR'S BRAINS.
THERE ARE NO RACIAL DIFFERENCES IN BRAIN STRUCTURE BUT THERE
ARE RACIST DIFFERENCES. STRESS FROM BEING VIGILANT
ABOUT EXPERIENCING RACISM CAN LEAD TO ADOLESCENT DEPRESSION.
CHILDHOOD POVERTY EXACERBATES THE IMPACTS OF RACE TRAUMA.
TRAUMATIC EXPERIENCE FROM IMMIGRATION AND ACCULTURATION
STRESSORS EXPERI ENCE OF DISCRIMINATION AND COMMUNITY
VIOLENCE DISPROPORTIONATELY HURT YOUTH OF COLOR.
WITH REGARD TO EQUAL PROTECTION CLUSTERING THESE SERVICES
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD DOES VIOLENCE TO THE 14TH AMENDMENT
EQUAL PROTECTION CLAUSE? THE CONGRESS OF RACIALLY
QUALITY DESCRIBES LULU'S LOCALLY UNDESIRABLE LANDLORDS
LAND USES IN A WRITE UP OF ENVIRONMENTAL INJUSTICE.
THE 14TH AMENDMENT HAS BEEN UNDER ATTACK FROM DONALD TRUMP
RIGHT WING SUPREME COURT. >> WILL SAN FRANCISCO STAND UP
TO THESE ATTACKS ON EQUAL PROTECTION UNDER THE LAW OR AID
THOSE IN SEEKING TO UNDERMINE IT?
>> WE SHARE THE GOAL OF A SUCCESSFUL DEVELOPMENT THAT
WILL EXPAND AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR LOW AND MIDDLE INCOME
FAMILIES NOT PCH. DRUG TREATMENT FACILITY THAT
WILL FURTHER ENDANGER MARSHALL OUR NEIGHBORHOOD IS ONE OF THE
FEW THAT HAVE WELCOMED AFFORDABLE HOUSING BUT THE
STREAMLINING APPROVALS IS JUST FOR THE SAKE OF STREAMLINING
BENEFITS FOR DEVELOPERS AND IN AND IN THIS CASE AT THE EXPENSE
OF OUR COMMUNITY. >> WE DEMAND DENIAL OF THIS
SUBDIVISION. THANK YOU, SIR.
TIMES CONCLUDED. >> THANKS.
>> THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
I DON'T SEE COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS FROM COLLEAGUES SO WE
WILL OPEN UP PUBLIC COMMENT SPECIFICALLY FOR THOSE WHO WANT
TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL AND IN OPPOSING MOTION
TO THE PROJECT. IF FOLKS COULD LINE UP OVER ON
YOUR RIGHT OF THE ROOM OUR I LEFT AND MADAM CLERK WILL YOU
PLEASE CALL THE FIRST SPEAKER WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES. >> WELCOME YOU.
>> MY NAME IS NAOMI FOX AND I'M A SINGLE MOM OF TWO CHILDREN
WHO ATTEND MARSHALL ELEMENTARY .
I'M ALSO A RESIDENT OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
I HAVE RESIDED ACROSS THE STREET FROM MARSHALL AT 15TH
AND CAPPS SINCE MAY 2021. SINCE MY OLDEST STARTED
KINDERGARTEN I HAVE POURED MY HEART INTO THE SCHOOL COMMUNITY
VOLUNTEERING FOR EVENTS AND LEADING THE MARSHALL PTA
AND I'M SO PROUD TO BE A PART OF THIS COMMUNITY.
I'M ALSO VERY INVOLVED WITH MONTHLY NEIGHBORHOOD MEETINGS
WITH THE HRC REPS ABOUT MISSION CABINS.
WE CAN ALL AGREE THAT THE RATE OF DECAY AROUND 16TH IN MISSION
AREA HAS ONLY RAMPED UP IN THE PAST FEW YEARS.
GANGS OF DRUG USERS NOW CROWD OUR STREETS IN ALLEYS AND DRUG
MARKETS AND FILL OUR SIDEWALKS. IT'S BEEN VERY SCARY FOR ME
ESPECIALLY AS A MOM. EVEN ON THE WAY HERE I SAW A
GROUP OF FENTANYL USERS ON THE FRONT STEPS OF MARSHALL.
THIS IS A VERY, VERY COMMON THING I SEE MULTIPLE TIMES
EVERY DAY. SMALL GROUPS OF DRUG USERS
CLUSTERED ON OUR SIDEWALKS. >> LAST MONTH ON THE MORNING OF
THE ANNUAL MARSHALL FIELD DAY THERE WERE GUNSHOTS ON THE
BLOCK AND THE TARGET TOOK REFUGE WITHIN THE MARSHALL
SCHOOLYARD. MY OWN CHILD COULD EASILY HAVE
BEEN CAUGHT IN THE CROSSFIRE. THAT WAS A CLOSE CALL AND I
BELIEVE THAT ONLY MORE VIOLENCE IS COMING UNTIL THE DRUG
MARKETS ARE SHUT. THE POPULATION SERVED BY THIS
PASSAGE WILL FEED THIS DRUG MARKET AND HOUSING THEM IN THAT
CHAOS IS TRULY A DISSERVICE TO THOSE SEEKING RECOVERY.
ON MAY 16TH PRINCIPAL NOAH WHO IS HERE TODAY INVITED MATTER
AND MISSION HOUSING TO COME TO MARSHALL TO TALK ABOUT THIS
PROJECT AND THE CAFETERIA WAS PACKED WITH MARSHALL PARENTS
AND STAFF. ONE AFTER ANOTHER PARENTS STOOD
UP AND BRAVELY VOICED THEIR CONCERNS ABOUT THIS PROJECT
AND I SAW HOW MUCH STRESS THIS HAS BEEN PUTTING US ALL UNDER.
AND I FEEL IT TOO. AND IT'S VERY SAD WHEN CHILDREN
DON'T WANT TO WALK TO SCHOOL BECAUSE OF WHAT THEY MIGHT SEE
ON THE WAY THERE. >> I BELIEVE THE COMMUNICATION
FROM THE DEVELOPERS HAS BEEN VERY POOR.
IT TOOK OVER TWO MONTHS TO REPLY TO OUR EMAIL ABOUT THANK
YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. HELLO THERE BOARD.
MY NAME IS TODD. I WAS A FORMER MARSHALL PARENT
AND MARSHALL PTA LEADER. THE PRESIDENT FOR TWO YEARS
AND I WAS VERY HONORED TO DO THAT.
BUT I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE TO CENTER THE NEEDS OF THE
MARSHALL FAMILIES AND THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO ALL THE
TIME EXPRESS WHAT DIFFICULT CIRCUMSTANCES THEY HAVE TO
ENDURE TO GET TO SCHOOL TO PROTECT THEIR CHILDREN FROM
SEEING THE THINGS THAT THEY SEE ON A DAILY BASIS.
AND YOU KNOW, I'M VERY THANKFUL THAT THE MAYOR HAS RAISED SOME
OF THOSE CONCERNS AND I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT WE DO EVERYTHING
IN OUR POWER TO, YOU KNOW, CENTER THE NEEDS OF THE
FAMILIES WHO DEFINITELY YOU KNOW, THERE'S A LOT OF HOMELESS
FAMILIES AT MARSHALL AND THEY NEED HOUSING AND DEFINITELY YOU
KNOW, I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT PEOPLE UNDERSTAND HOW IMPORTANT
THAT IS AND THAT, YOU KNOW, WE REALIZE THAT, YOU KNOW, THE
CONVENIENT THING TO JUST ACCEPT MONEY FOR PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING FOR YOU KNOW, CERTAIN MEMBERS OF THE COMMUNITY IS NOT
WHAT THE COMMUNITY HAS SAID THAT THEY REALLY NEED
AND THAT'S THAT YOU KNOW, THESE THESE FAMILIES WHO ARE OFTEN
HOUSING INSECURE. AND YOU KNOW I THINK SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FOR HER WORK IN YOU KNOW BRINGING THAT TO PEOPLE'S
ATTENTION BUT I THINK WHEN IT COMES TO THIS PROJECT WE SHOULD
ALSO BE FOCUSED ON THE NEEDS OF THE COMMUNITY RATHER THAN JUST
AN EASY WIN FOR, YOU KNOW, THESE DEVELOPERS.
>> SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
JUST A NOTE TO THE MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC IN THE PUBLIC
GALLERY IF YOU ARE IN SUPPORT YOU CAN JUST QUIETLY RAISE YOUR
HANDS AND WE HAVE A BOARD RULE THAT THERE ARE NO AUDIBLE
SOUNDS TO INTERRUPT THE PROCEEDING.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. HI.
MY NAME IS MARIANNA AND I'M THE COMMUNITY SCHOOLS COORDINATOR
AT MARSHALL ELEMENTARY WHICH SITS JUST STEPS FROM THE
PROPOSED DEVELOPMENT SITE. I'M HERE TODAY NOT AS AN
OPPONENT OF HOUSING BUT TO SPEAK FOR THE CHILDREN OF
MARSHALL ELEMENTARY CHILDREN WHO ARE ALREADY SOME OF THE
MOST VULNERABLE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
OVER 30% OF OUR STUDENTS AT MARSHALL QUALIFY AS UNHOUSED.
THESE ARE CHILDREN WHO COME TO SCHOOL HUNGRY, TIRED,
TRAUMATIZED. AND YET THEY STILL SHOW UP
TRYING TO LEARN WHAT THEY NEED MOST IS STABILITY, SAFETY
AND SUPPORT. BUT WHAT WE'VE SEEN JUST
OUTSIDE OF OUR SCHOOL TELLS A DIFFERENT STORY.
I HAVE PERSONALLY HAD TO CALL SECURITY WHEN TWO PEOPLE WERE
DEFECATING NEAR OUR FRONT DOORS.
>> I'VE WATCHED CHILDREN BE AFRAID TO WALK ON THE SCHOOL
SIDEWALK BECAUSE OF PEOPLE INJECTING IN FRONT OF OUR GATE.
ONE DAY A HOMELESS MAN WAS IN PLAIN SIGHT OF STUDENTS.
THESE ARE NOT ONE OFF INCIDENTS.
THEY ARE PART OF THE DAILY LANDSCAPE OF STUDENTS WHO ARE
FORCED TO WALK THROUGH. I WANT HOUSING BUT I WANT IT
FOR FAMILIES FOR STUDENTS WHO DON'T HAVE A BED TO SLEEP IN.
>> FOR THE PARENTS WHO WANT TO STAY IN THE MISSION BUT CAN'T
AFFORD TO RENT. THIS PROJECT DOESN'T PROMISE
THAT IT PROMISES PERMANENCE, SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FOR ADULTS
WITH SUBSTANCE ABUSE AND OTHER COMPLEX NEEDS BUT GIVES NOTHING
TO THE FAMILIES IN OUR COMMUNITY WHO ARE ALREADY DOING
EVERYTHING THEY CAN TO SURVIVE. >> I'M ASKING YOU TO PAUSE
AND REEXAMINE WHETHER THIS LOCATION NEXT TO A TITLE ONE
ELEMENTARY SCHOOL FILLED WITH TRAUMA IMPACTED CHILDREN IS THE
RIGHT PLACE FOR THIS TYPE OF HOUSING.
WE NEED HOUSING THAT SUPPORTS FAMILIES, NOT ONE THAT RISKS
RETRAUMATIZING OUR STUDENTS. PLEASE DON'T FORGET THE
CHILDREN IN THIS CONVERSATION. THEY MAY NOT BE HERE TODAY BUT
I AM HERE ON THEIR BEHALF. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
OUR NEXT SPEAKER. IF YOU WOULD PLEASE HOLD YOUR
APPLAUSE. WELCOME, SIR.
>> HI BOARD. MY NAME IS GEORGE AND I'VE
LIVED IN THE INTERMISSION FOR 34 YEARS.
23 OF THEM RIGHT AROUND THE CORNER FROM THE MARSHALL
SCHOOL. AND I WON'T REITERATE WHAT ALL
THE OTHER SPEAKERS HAVE SAID OR THE APPELLANTS HAVE SAID
BECAUSE IT SPEAKS FOR ITSELF. THE NEWS ARTICLES SPEAK FOR
ITSELF. I'VE SEEN IT.
I HAVE EXPERIENCED IT THE FIRST TIME THAT I EVER GOT OFFICIAL
INFORMATION THAT THE PLANS WERE CHANGED TO BUILD AFFORDABLE
HOUSING RIGHT FOR FAMILIES. WAS THIS LETTER FROM DPW?
IT WAS DATED JUNE 25TH. I RECEIVED IT IN THE BEGINNING
OF JULY. MY UNDERSTANDING IS THE PROJECT
WAS ALREADY APPROVED BY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT IN MAY.
I WASN'T INFORMED OF THAT. I WASN'T INFORMED OF ANY
COMMUNITY MEETINGS TO DISCUSS PLANS TO CHANGE THE PLANS FOR
THE PARCEL TO DEVELOP THIS HOUSING FOR DRUG USERS
AND HOMELESS PEOPLE. I WAS INFORMED MOST OF MY
NEIGHBORS WERE NOT INFORMED SO I DON'T UNDERSTAND THAT THAT'S
A LACK OF TRANSPARENCY AND IT'S VERY DISRESPECTFUL.
SO WHAT I WOULD LIKE THE BOARD TO DO IS TO GRANT THE APPEAL
AND GIVE US THE STAKEHOLDERS TIME TO FIND OUT WHAT'S REALLY
GOING ON AND HAVE ACTUAL INPUT INTO WHAT THESE CHANGES ARE
BECAUSE IT INVOLVES US TO IT'S NOT JUST ABOUT THE DEVELOPERS
AND THE SPONSORS OF THE PROGRAM WHO DO NOT LIVE WHERE WE LIVE
AND THEIR CHILDREN DO NOT GO TO SCHOOL AT MARSHALL.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT. I'LL JUST MAKE AN ANNOUNCEMENT
AS IF THIS IS THE LAST SPEAKER ON BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT OR
THE PROJECT OR WHO IS AGAINST THE PROJECT.
PLEASE COME ON UP AND GET IN LINE.
>> WELCOME, SIR. HI.
GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS NOAH INGBER.
I'M THE PRINCIPAL OF MARSHALL ELEMENTARY.
SETH USD I WANT TO ECHO WHAT MARIANA MY COWORKER THE
COMMUNITY SCHOOL'S COORDINATOR WAS SAYING ABOUT I WANT TO SAY
I AM VERY MUCH FOR I'M A YES IN MY BACKYARD KIND OF PERSON.
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS CRUCIAL. WHAT I'M MORE CONCERNED ABOUT
IS ABOUT THE HOUSING FOR SUBSTANCE ABUSERS SUBSIDIZED
PEOPLE WITH A HISTORY OF SUBSTANCE ABUSE.
PUTTING THAT NEXT DOOR TO AN ELEMENTARY SCHOOL I THINK IS
VERY PROBLEMATIC AND I'M VERY CONCERNED ABOUT THE REALITY OF
THAT. I'M CONCERNED ABOUT THE HEIGHT
OF THOSE BUILDINGS THAT ARE GOING TO CAST A SHADOW OVER OUR
PLAYGROUND LITERALLY. AND THESE ARE STUDENTS THAT ARE
YOU KNOW, METAPHORICALLY LIVE IN THE SHADOWS AND WE WILL BE
LITERALLY IN THE SHADOW OF THESE TALLER BUILDINGS MUCH
TALLER THAN THE CURRENT BUILDINGS IN THE IN THE
NEIGHBORHOOD. >> BUT IN SHORT, I JUST WANT TO
BE VERY CLEAR THAT I AM FOR PUBLIC HOUSING ESPECIALLY
ESPECIALLY FOR FAMILIES THAT OVER 30% LIKE MARIANA SAID OVER
30% OF OUR FAMILIES AT OUR SCHOOL QUALIFY.
AND I AM CONCERNED ABOUT THOSE SUBSTANCE ABUSE FOLKS.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> EXCUSE ME.
I AM IN SUPPORT OF THIS PEOPLE TALKING ABOUT THE DANGERS THAT
THEY HAVE TO ENDURE EVERY DAY WITH THEIR CHILDREN.
I AM A MOTHER WHO LOST HER CHILD TO HOMICIDE, SHOT 30
TIMES WITH A SEMIAUTOMATIC GUN. SAVING SOMEONE ELSE'S LIFE.
I DON'T WANT NONE OF THESE MOTHERS AND FATHERS THAT ARE
COMING UP HERE AND ASKING FOR JUSTICE AND SAFETY IN THEIR
NEIGHBORHOODS. BECAUSE WHEN WHEN WHEN CHILDREN
ARE KILLED WE'RE COUNTING ON THE SYSTEM TO GIVE THEM HOUSING
SOMEWHERE ELSE BECAUSE OF THE DANGER OF THE RIPPLING EFFECT
OF IT. AND WHO WANTS TO WALK AND TAKE
THEIR KIDS TO SCHOOL IN A DANGEROUS NEIGHBORHOOD?
WHO WANTS TO DO THAT? THESE PEOPLE NEED HELP.
I NEED HELP. >> SO I'M THINKING EVEN NEXT
MONTH IT WILL BE THE ANNIVERSARY OF MY SON'S DEATH.
WHO WAS MURDERED IN SAN FRANCISCO ON SAN FRANCISCO
STREETS. >> SO I ASK FOR ALL THE SUPPORT
THAT THESE PEOPLE ARE ASKING FOR FOR YOU TO SHOW UP AND AND
GIVE US MOTHERS SOME SUPPORT AND SOME FATHERS SOME SUPPORT.
I AGREE WITH YOU. >> THAT ARE THAT ARE HERE
TALKING ABOUT THE SCHOOL THE MARSHALL SCHOOL.
>> I HAD A CHILD THAT WENT OVER TO THAT SCHOOL ALSO AND THE
PAST SHE'S AN ADULT NOW. BUT I UNDERSTAND THAT YOU DON'T
HAVE TO BE TAKING YOUR KIDS TO SCHOOL IN A DANGEROUS
NEIGHBORHOOD. PLEASE HELP THEM.
HELP ME. I'M A MOTHER WHO LOST A CHILD.
SO JUST GETTING UP HERE SUPPORTING THEM AND HEARING
THAT THE FIT NOW AND THE DRUGS IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD IS NOT
GOOD. SO PLEASE THINK ABOUT THEM.
THINK ABOUT ME. I'VE BEEN COMING HERE FOR YEARS
ASKING FOR SUPPORT FOR YEARS. YOU GUYS ARE NEW COMMISSIONERS
. SO NOW I GOT TO GET TO KNOW YOU
AND WHICH IS OKAY. >> I CAN'T LET MY SON'S HIS
DEATH BE NOTHING. SO AND I CONGRATULATE THESE
PEOPLE THAT ARE COMING UP HERE AND ASKING FOR SERVICE.
>> THANK YOU, MS.. BROWN, FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
YES. >> ALL RIGHT.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
WELCOME. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
BART GRIFFIN LEE HERE SPEAKING FROM THE HEART.
I'M ACTUALLY HERE FOR AN INTRODUCTION WHICH I ACTUALLY
MAY NOT BE ABLE TO MAKE PUBLIC COMMENT FOR.
>> I HAVE SOMEWHERE TO BE BUT I DID WANT TO SAY I THINK IF WE
DO APPROVE THIS PLAN AS IS WHICH INCLUDES PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING, THERE'S A VERY GOOD CHANCE IT WILL
CONTRADICT A RESOLUTION THAT WAS ACTUALLY INTRODUCED LAST
WEEK THAT I'M VERY SUPPORTIVE OF WHICH IS ALLOWING FOR
PRIORITY CALLS FOR DRUG USE AROUND PARKS AND SCHOOLS.
>> WELL, THIS HOUSING DEVELOPMENT WOULD BE RIGHT DOWN
THE STREET FROM AN ELEMENTARY SCHOOL AND THERE WOULD BE A
HIGH PROBABILITY OF OF CONTINUED DRUG ACTIVITY ALONG
WITH THOSE LIVING IN PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING IN THAT
DEVELOPMENT. >> GIVEN WE KNOW THE NATURE OF
WHAT'S HAPPENING IN A LOT OF OUR HOUSING TODAY, JUST LOOK AT
THE DATA AND OUR OVERDOSE DEATHS.
>> SO I THINK WE GOT TO RETHINK ABOUT THIS THIS PROPOSAL.
I'M VERY MUCH SUPPORTIVE OF SUPPORT OF AH EXCUSE ME
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND I WOULDN'T LET THE SHADOW TOPIC
GET IN THE WAY OF BUILDING HOUSING.
I THINK WE SAW WHAT HAPPENED ON FIFTH AND MISSION WHICH IS NOW
A DRUG CRISIS CENTER OR A TRIAGE CENTER SO THAT'S MY
$0.02. I WOULD RECONSIDER THE APPROVAL
TO ELIMINATE PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING GIVEN IT'S
DOWN THE STREET FROM A SCHOOL. >> THANKS SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. BEFORE THE NEXT SPEAKER, IF
THERE'S ANYONE IN THE CHAMBER WHO IS HERE TO SPEAK ON BEHALF
OF THE APPELLANT OR IF YOU ARE AGAINST THE PROJECT NOW WOULD
BE YOUR OPPORTUNITY TO PROVIDE THE BOARD YOUR COMMENTS.
>> OTHERWISE THIS WILL BE OUR LAST SPEAKER.
WELCOME. YES.
OKAY. IT'S WHAT GEORGE SAYS OVER
THERE ABOUT NOT HAVING A TIME TO FOR THE NOTIFICATION TO
ARRIVE ON TIME TO ANALYZE EXACTLY WHAT'S WHAT'S GOING ON.
>> THAT'S WHY YOU APPEAL THE REST AND THEN YOU HAVE TIME TO
CONSIDER THAT IN FACT THERE IS NO PROB OKAY.
THESE GUYS DRUG ADDICTS ARE NOT A PROBLEM FOR KIDS SPECIFICALLY
THEY ARE NOT THE PEDOPHILES AND PEDOPHILES ARE NOT IN THE
STREETS. SO YOU WORK TOGETHER SINCE YOU
WORK IN PROGRESS IN PROXIMITY OF EACH OTHER, YOU WORK
TOGETHER. YOU ASK THESE DRUG ADDICTS TO
ADD THE KIDS. IN FACT THEY'RE GOING TO LOVE
IT BECAUSE AT LEAST THAT FOR USEFUL AND IT'S DONE YOU NEED
TO WORK TOGETHER NOT SEPARATE YOU KNOW NO RACISM ALWAYS.
>> HMM. IS THIS CLEAR?
YOU APPEAL MEANWHILE JUST TO HAVE TIME TO SEE THE SITUATION
PRECISELY TO SIMPLIFY YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS,
MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED AND WE
ARE NOW GOING TO HEAR FROM REPRESENTATIVES OF CITY
DEPARTMENTS FOR UP TO TEN MINUTES AND I THINK WE ARE
STARTING WITH A LIST FRENCH FROM PUBLIC WORKS MAYBE.
>> CAN YOU HEAR ME? HI THERE.
MY NAME IS ELIAS FRENCH. I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF ELIAS.
>> CAN YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THAT MICROPHONE?
>> SURE. IT MOVES SO JUST DIRECTED
TOWARDS. GOT IT.
I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS AS
THE CITY AND COUNTY SURVEYOR WHERE THE AGENCY THAT PROCESSES
SUBDIVISION MAP APPLICATIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I'LL GIVE A BRIEF OUTLINE OF THE PROJECTS PROCESS IN THROUGH
OUR OFFICE. WE RECEIVED THE SUBDIVISION
APPLICATION AND TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP ON JANUARY 25TH.
IT WAS DEEMED SUBMITTED WELL CIRCULATED TO CITY AGENCIES
AND APPROVED BY PLANNING. >> ON MAY 28TH 2025.
AT THAT TIME FOLLOWING THAT OUR OF OUR DEPARTMENT AFTER
REVIEWING THE TENTATIVE MAP AND ITS OWN CAPACITY ISSUED
TENTATIVE MAP APPROVAL AT THAT TIME WE NOTIFIED THE NEIGHBORS
AS REQUIRED AND THEREAFTER RECEIVED A NOTICE OF THIS
APPEAL BASED ON OUR REVIEW OF THE SUBDIVISION WHICH PROPOSES
THE SUBDIVISION OF THE EXISTING PARCEL INTO THREE PARCELS.
WE FOUND THAT COMPLIANT WITH THE APPLICABLE RULES AND CODES
. THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOUND
IT SIMILARLY COMPLIANT WITH REGARD TO THE GENERAL PLAN LOT
SIZE AND ETC. THE APPELLANT'S LETTER AND THE CONCERNS HERE
RELATE TO THE TYPE OF HOUSING PROPOSED ON THE SITE THE SIZE
SHAPE OF THE BUILDINGS ETC. AND CONCERNS RELATED TO THOSE.
THESE MATTERS AREN'T DIRECTLY RELATED TO THE SUBDIVISION OF
THE PARCEL ITSELF BUT RATHER TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE
STRUCTURES ON THE SITE WHICH IS NOT WHAT THE SUBDIVISION MAP
INVOLVES. THEREFORE I FIND THE IN OUR
OPINION THE CONCERNS RAISED OUR PLANNING RELATED WITH REGARD TO
THE PROPOSED CONSTRUCTION WHICH ARE APPROVED THROUGH THE
PLANNING PROCESS AND BUILDING PERMITTING PROCESS NOT THE
SUBDIVISION PROCESS. I WILL DEFER THE REST OF MY
TIME TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT WHO I BELIEVE HAS A
PRESENTATION OR CAN EXPLAIN FURTHER UNLESS THERE ARE ANY
QUESTIONS AT THIS TIME NO QUESTIONS.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT MADAM AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS ERIN STAR MANAGER OF LEGISLATIVE AFFAIRS AT THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT. I'LL GIVE A BRIEF OVERVIEW OF
THE PROJECT AND HOW THE SUBDIVISION COMPLIES WITH THE
PLANNING CODE AND THEN ADDRESS THE ISSUES RAISED BY THE
APPELLANTS. THE PROJECT PROPOSES TO
SUBDIVIDE A 57,325 SQUARE FOOT PARCEL INTO THREE NEW LOTS
MEASURING APPROXIMATELY 24,000 718,000 713,800FT2.
>> IT INCLUDES THE DEMOLITION OF AN EXISTING COMMERCIAL
BUILDING AND THE CONSTRUCTION OF A NINE STOREY RESIDENTIAL
BUILDING WITH 136 UNITS OF SUPPORTIVE HOUSING.
>> THIS PROJECT WAS SUBMITTED UNDER AB 2162 WHICH ALLOWS FOR
THE MINISTERIAL APPROVAL OF SUPPORTIVE HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS
. THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
DETERMINED THE PROJECT MET ALL APPLICABLE REQUIREMENTS
AND ISSUED APPROVALS ACCORDINGLY.
THE TENTATIVE MAP WAS SUBSEQUENTLY APPROVED FOR
COMPLIANCE WITH THE PLANNING CODE UNDER PLANNING CODE
SECTION 121. ALL NEW LOTS MUST MEET MINIMUM
STANDARDS FOR AREA WIDTH AND FRONTAGE.
SPECIFICALLY EACH LOT MUST ONE HAVE A MINIMUM OF WIDTH OF 20FT
HAVE AT LEAST 16FT OF FRONTAGE ON A STREET OR ALLEYWAY AND A
MINIMUM AREA OF 1200 SQUARE FEET.
THE PROPOSED SUBDIVISION MEETS ALL OF THESE OBJECTIVE
STANDARDS. I WILL GO AHEAD AND SKIP THE
FIRST TWO CONCERNS THAT THE APPELLANT RAISED IN THEIR
APPLICATION SINCE THEY HAVE WITHDRAWN THEM.
BUT THE LAST ONE THE APPELLANT EXPRESSED CONCERNS ABOUT PUBLIC
SAFETY, HOMELESSNESS AND NEIGHBORHOOD CONDITIONS.
WHILE WE ACKNOWLEDGE THE SERIOUSNESS OF THESE ISSUES,
THEY ARE NOT FACTORS THAT GOVERN THE REVIEW OR APPROVAL
OF A TENTATIVE MAP. SUBDIVISIONS THE SUBDIVISION
DOES NOT CAUSE OR MITIGATE THESE BROADER SOCIAL CONCERNS.
IN SUMMARY THE ISSUES RAISED IN THE APPEAL FOCUS ON THE
BROADER DEVELOPMENT NOT ON WHAT THE TENTATIVE MAP WAS, NOT IF
THE TENTATIVE MAP WAS PROPERLY APPROVED.
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS DETERMINED THAT THE SUBDIVISION
COMPLIES WITH THE PLANNING CODE AND THE GENERAL PLAN.
NO EVIDENCE HAS BEEN PRESENTED TO INDICATE THAT THE CITY ERRED
IN APPROVING THE TENTATIVE MAP .
WE RESPECTFULLY RECOMMEND UPHOLDING THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND DPW DECISION TO APPROVE THE TENTATIVE MAP.
THAT CONCLUDES MY PRESENTATION. I'M AVAILABLE FOR QUESTIONS.
I ALSO HAVE MY COLLEAGUE CARLY GROBE HERE WHO CAN ANSWER
QUESTIONS ABOUT THE APPROVAL OF THE DEVELOPMENT PROJECT.
>> THANK YOU. >> I DO NOT SEE ANY HELP.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER. THANK YOU.
>> I JUST HAVE A COUPLE QUESTIONS.
UM, SO FOR FOR DPW WHAT ARE THE CRITERIA THAT PUBLIC WORKS
CONSIDERS IN APPROVING A PARCEL MAP?
>> ELI FRENCH COUNTY SURVEYOR. THE CRITERIA THAT PUBLIC WORKS
CONSIDERS WHEN APPROVING A PARCEL MAP ARE WE REVIEWED THE
TENTATIVE MAP FOR TECHNICAL CORRECTNESS AND THE THE
PROPOSED PARCEL IS ASIAN FOR CONFORMANCE WITH THE GENERAL
PLAN. AND ALSO INTAKE THE COMMENTS
FROM PLANNING WITH REGARD TO THAT CONFORMANCE.
THOSE ARE THE APPROVAL IS LARGELY TECHNICAL AND DOESN'T
HINGE ON ANALYSIS OF THE TYPES OF CONCERNS THAT WERE RAISED
HERE. >> THANK YOU.
AND THEN PLANNING. >> SO YOU PLANNING APPROVE THIS
PROJECT ON MAY 27TH? >> CORRECT.
YES, I BELIEVE SO. >> CAN YOU SPEAK TO THIS
PROJECT'S COMPLIANCE WITH OUR GENERAL PLAN AND SPECIFICALLY
POLICY? 1526 AND PLANNING CODE
SUBSECTION 1A1 POINT 1B4 AS LAID OUT IN YOUR APPROVAL
LETTER. >> I'M SORRY, COULD YOU REPEAT
THE NUMBERS AGAIN? SO SPECIFICALLY POLICY 1526
AND PLANNING CODE SUBSECTION 1A1 POINT 1B4.
>> SO THE WHAT I WANT BEFORE IS RELATED TO COMMUTER TRAFFIC NOT
IMPEDING MUNI TRANSIT OR OVERBURDEN OUR STREETS OR
NEIGHBORHOOD PARKING. >> CORRECT.
SO WE FOUND THAT THE PROJECT AS DESIGNED WOULD NOT DO THAT.
>> OKAY. DID PLANNING APPROVE A WAIVER
FOR USABLE OPEN SPACE FOR THIS PROJECT?
>> I WILL DEFER TO MY COLLEAGUE ON THAT.
THANK THANK YOU. >> YES.
YES WE DID. >> THANK YOU.
AND LASTLY THE DENSITY OF THE PROJECT IS UNDER PLANNING
PURVIEW. HOW DID PLANNING COMPLY WITH
THE STATE DENSITY BONUS LAW IN APPROVING THIS PROJECT?
>> KALI GROVE PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF.
THE STATE DENSITY BONUS LAW PROVIDES 100% AFFORDABLE
HOUSING PROJECTS UNLIMITED DENSITY AND UP TO THREE STORIES
ABOVE THE ZONE HEIGHT LIMIT AS WELL AS WAIVERS AND INCENTIVES
AND CONCESSIONS FROM CERTAIN PLANNING CODE STANDARDS.
SO THE UNDERLYING DENSITY OF THE SITE IS ALREADY RELATIVELY
HIGH BECAUSE OF THE FORM BASED ZONING FOR THE PROJECT.
SO A CODE COMPLIANT PROJECT HERE COULD BUILD UP TO 105FT
YOU KNOW WITH CERTAIN SETBACKS ASSUMED.
SO ESSENTIALLY THE PROJECT USED PROVISIONS OF THE STATE DENSITY
BONUS THAT ARE ALLOWED BY THE STATE LAW FOR 100% AFFORDABLE
PROJECTS TO ACHIEVE THE DENSITY.
>> THANK YOU. >> AND THEN I WANTED TO BRING
THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPERS UP FOR A QUESTION.
I JUST WANTED TO ASK A QUESTION ABOUT WHAT OUTREACH TO THE
COMMUNITY HAS BEEN LIKE DURING THE DEVELOPMENT PROCESS.
>> THEY ALSO WILL BE DOING A WHOLE PRESENTATION ON IT.
>> YEAH WE CAN SAY THAT THEM. DO YOU WANT ME TO ANSWER?
DO YOU WANT ME TO WAIT FOR THE PRESENTATION?
YOU'RE UP. HI.
SAM WAS THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF MISSION HOUSING DEVELOPMENT
CORPORATION, OUR PARTNER HERE. >> PLEASE GO AHEAD.
GOOD AFTERNOON, LA RAZA. I'M SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF
MARRIOTT MISSION INCOME ANOMIC DEVELOPMENT AGENCY FROM THE
YEARS BEFORE THIS WAS AN RFQ PLAZA DIOCESE'S MISSION HOUSING
MISSION ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AGENCY.
>> WE'RE WORKING WITH COMMUNITY TALKING WITH COMMUNITY.
THE RFQ ITSELF WAS INFORMED BY COMMUNITY AFTER DOZENS OF
MEETINGS AFTER IT WAS AWARDED. FOR THE BETTER PART OF TWO
YEARS WE HAD BOTH SMALL AND LARGE MEETINGS.
>> WE HAD MULTIPLE MEETINGS WHICH WERE PUBLICIZED IN THE
PRESS ABOUT THE DENSITY AND THE HEIGHT.
WE HAD A COMMUNITY VOTE OVER THE COURSE OF THREE SEPARATE
MEETINGS. THE COMMUNITY VOTED FOR AS TALL
AND AS MUCH AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR FAMILIES AND HOMELESS
INDIVIDUALS AS POSSIBLE. BUT I DO BEFORE I SEE IT, I
JUST WANT TO SAY THIS ISN'T GOING TO STOP COMMUNITY
OUTREACH. WE PLAN ON HAVING MEETINGS A
LOT BOTH BEFORE DURING CONSTRUCTION AND THEN AFTER THE
BUILDING IS BUILT THROUGHOUT THE ENTIRE LIFETIME OF THE
BUILDING. IT'S SOMETHING BOTH MISSION
AND MEDICARE A LOT ABOUT. AND WE HAVE OVER 50 YEARS TRACK
RECORD PROVING THANK YOU. I WOULD ALSO ADD THAT WE MET
WITH THE SCHOOL COMMUNITY AS WELL AND WE ARE COMMITTED
AND TAKE VERY SERIOUSLY THEIR CONCERNS.
>> ANY DEVELOPMENT YOUR SCHOOL CAN BRING YOU KNOW, POSITIVE
AND ALSO DIFFICULT SITUATIONS THAT WE ARE COMMITTED COMMITTED
TO ADDRESSING AND WORKING WITH THE COMMUNITY TO MAKE SURE THAT
AREA IS AN ASSET TO THE COMMUNITY.
>> THANK YOU. BACK TO YOU.
PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. AND JUST SO I UNDERSTAND KIND
OF ALL THAT'S GOING INTO THIS. >> I MEAN WHAT'S IN FRONT OF US
TODAY IS OH YOU GUYS CAN SIT DOWN.
UH, WE HAVE A WE HAVE A MAP APPEAL.
YOU'VE TALKED TO US SOME ABOUT THE PLANNING APPROVALS OF THOSE
WERE NONDISCRETIONARY, RIGHT. SO THERE WAS NOT REALLY A PLACE
FOR THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO THINK ABOUT AS A POLICY MATTER
WHETHER THIS IS A GOOD OR BAD IDEA.
SO THE ONLY DISCRETION ON THE CITY SIDE HERE IS ON FUNDING
WHICH PRESUMABLY THERE IS FUNDING FOR THIS PROJECT BUT
THAT'S NOT FROM ANY OF YOU. RIGHT?
I MEAN KIND OF ADAM TALKS ABOUT BUT I'M NOT GOING TO PUT HIM
IN THE IN THE HOT SEAT. >> OKAY.
OKAY. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. >> ALL RIGHT.
I DON'T THINK WE HAVE ANY MORE QUESTIONS FOR FOR OUR
DEPARTMENT. >> SO WITH THAT I'LL CALL UP
THE PROJECT SPONSOR TO SPEAK FOR UP TO TEN MINUTES.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS .
MY NAME IS SAM MOSS AND THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF MISSION
HOUSING DEVELOPMENT CORP MISSION HOUSING HAS BEEN
BUILDING DEVELOPING AND RUNNING AFFORDABLE HOUSING WITH AND FOR
COMMUNITY FOR OVER 50 YEARS. WE'RE PROUD TO STAND WITH
RESIDENTS FAMILIES AND PARTNERS WHO BELIEVE SAN FRANCISCO
SHOULD BE A PLACE WHERE EVERYONE HAS SECURE, AFFORDABLE
AND SUSTAINABLE HOUSING. I WANT TO START BY THANKING
EVERYONE WHO'S HERE TO SUPPORT AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
THANK YOU. YOUR PRESENCE TRULY MATTERS.
THANKS TO THE CITY AGENCIES WHO HAVE SUBMITTED THEIR REPORTS
ABOUT THE APPEAL. THANK YOU FOR THE COUNTLESS
RESIDENTS, FAMILIES AND COMMUNITY PARTNERS WHO'VE
MADE THEIR VOICES HEARD THROUGHOUT THIS PROCESS.
WE'RE HERE TODAY NOT JUST TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF A PARCEL
MAP. WE'RE HERE TO DEFEND THE VERY
IDEA THAT WORKING CLASS AND LOW INCOME FAMILIES WHO ARE THE
BACKBONE OF OUR CITY DESERVE TO LIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THAT THEY DESERVE THE DIGNITY OF A LASTING HOME A HOME THAT
ALLOWS THEM TO HAVE THE RIGHT TO REMAIN IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS
AND THE OPPORTUNITY TO THRIVE IN OUR CITY.
WE'RE HERE TODAY TO DEFEND THE BELIEF THAT HOUSING IS A HUMAN
RIGHT. BUILDING AFFORDABLE HOUSING
IN THE MISSION SHOULD NOT BE CONTROVERSIAL.
IT IS ONE OF THE MANY SOLUTIONS TO A DIRE SITUATION.
IT IS URGENT AND IT IS LONG OVERDUE.
THIS APPEAL ISN'T ABOUT PROTECTING THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT'S ABOUT PROTECTING PRIVILEGE.
IT'S ABOUT USING BUREAUCRACY TO BLOCK EQUITY.
IT SENDS A CLEAR MESSAGE TO LOW INCOME AND HOUSING INSECURE
FOLKS IN SAN FRANCISCO. YOU DON'T BELONG HERE.
>> THAT'S WHAT THIS APPEAL IS REALLY ABOUT AND WE SHOULD CALL
IT WHAT IT IS A WEAPONIZATION OF PROCESS IN THE SERVICE OF
EXCLUSION. THIS ISN'T JUST ABOUT TECHNICAL
OBJECTIONS. IT'S ABOUT A FEW INDIVIDUALS
TRYING TO SILENCE THE VOICE OF HUNDREDS OF COMMUNITY MEMBERS,
UNDERMINE THE CITY'S COMMITMENTS AND BREAK PROMISES
MADE TO THIS COMMUNITY. THE APPELLANT IS ARGUING THAT
SUBDIVIDING ONE LOT INTO THREE SOMEHOW HARMS THE COMMUNITY
THAT IS SIMPLY FALSE. THIS IS A BACKDOOR ATTEMPT TO
DELAY DERAIL AND DISCOURAGE THE CREATION OF DESPERATELY NEEDED
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. AND WE CANNOT LET THAT STAND.
AND YET HERE WE ARE EVEN DEEP AFFORDABILITY WITH WIDE
COMMUNITY SUPPORT STILL FACES OBSTRUCTION.
AND THIS SHOULD CONCERN ALL OF US.
THIS MOMENT RAISES AN IMPORTANT AND BROADER QUESTION ONE THAT
THIS BOARD WILL HAVE TO GRAPPLE WITH.
WHAT SYSTEMS NEED TO CHANGE TO PREVENT THE MISUSE OF
PROCEDURAL STEPS TO BLOCK DESPERATELY NEEDED HOUSING?
>> WHAT ARE YOU THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS DOING TO ENSURE
THAT BASIS APPEALS SUCH AS THIS NO LONGER HAPPEN?
WHAT ARE YOU THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ARE DOING TO ENSURE
THAT WE BUILD AND SUPPORT 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN EVERY
SINGLE NEIGHBORHOOD? BECAUSE IF 100% OF AFFORDABLE
HOUSING SUPPORTED BY COMMUNITY PARTNERS DESIGNED TO SERVE
THOSE MOST IN NEED IN A NEIGHBORHOOD DEEPLY IMPACTED BY
DISPLACEMENT CAN'T MOVE FORWARD WITHOUT BEING ATTACKED
AND DELAYED, THEN WHAT KIND OF CITY ARE WE BECOMING?
EVERY DAY OF DELAY HAS REAL HUMAN COSTS.
THERE ARE THOUSANDS SLEEPING ON OUR STREETS EVERY NIGHT.
CHILDREN ARE SLEEPING IN S.F. USD SHELTERS.
FAMILIES ARE OVERCROWDED CONDITIONS DOUBLING
AND TRIPLING UP IN APARTMENTS THEY CAN BARELY AFFORD.
AND GENERATIONS OF SAN FRANCISCANS HAVE BEEN TOLD THAT
THEY CAN GROW UP IN THE CITY BUT THEY CAN'T GROW OLD HERE.
WHILE WE WASTE TIME HERE, THE CRISIS IS JUST GROWING MORE
URGENT. THIS ISN'T THEORETICAL.
THIS CRISIS IS ABOUT REAL PEOPLE, REAL LIVES.
AND THE MARVEL IS PART OF THAT SOLUTION.
AND IF YOU CARE ABOUT ECONOMIC RECOVERY, FAMILY STABILITY
AND REDUCING HOMELESSNESS, THEN BUILD THIS KIND OF HOUSING.
WE NEED IT NOW. ENOUGH DELAYS, ENOUGH
OBSTRUCTION, ENOUGH HIDING BEHIND TRAFFIC AND PERCEIVED
NEIGHBORHOOD CHARACTER WHILE FAMILIES AND INDIVIDUALS SLEEP
IN OVERCROWDED CONDITIONS AND SORROWS AND ON GYMNASIUM
FLOORS. TRUE EQUITY MEANS TAKING ACTION
WHEN IT MATTERS THE MOST. AND THIS IS ONE OF THOSE
MOMENTS. AND SO TODAY I ASKED THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS TO DO WHAT'S RIGHT.
DENY THIS APPEAL. APPROVE THIS SUBDIVISION.
LET'S BUILD A MARVEL. LET'S BUILD A MORE AFFORDABLE
AND INCLUSIVE SAN FRANCISCO. I WANT TO THANK YOU.
AND NOW PASS IT TO MY COLLEAGUE LAURA GARCIA FROM MICHIGAN
ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AGENCY. OUR PARTNER ON THE PROJECT.
>> THANK YOU, SAM. GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS
AND MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC. MARIA IS A PROUD CO-DEVELOPER
OF LA MARIA THE MARVEL IN THE MISSION.
FIRST I WANT TO REMIND US THAT THIS PROJECT IS THE RESULT OF
OVER A DECADE OF GRASSROOTS ADVOCACY.
TO MEET THE URGENT NEED FOR HOUSING FOR WORKING FAMILIES
IN SAN FRANCISCO, MARIA IS PROUD TO HELP DELIVER OVER 300
UNITS OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING TO THE MISSION A NEIGHBORHOOD THAT
HAS LONG BEEN HOME TO WORKING CLASS FAMILIES.
AND ONE OF THE COMMUNITIES MOST IMPACTED BY DISPLACEMENT THAT
MARIA ALSO PLAYS A CRITICAL ROLE IN HELPING THE CITY MEET
ITS STATE MANDATED HOUSING ELEMENT GOALS INCLUDING THE
REQUIREMENT TO BUILD MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN THE
NEIGHBORHOODS WELL-SERVED BY PUBLIC TRANSIT.
>> ONLY A FEW STEPS FROM BOARD AND KEY MUNI LINES IT OFFERS
FAMILY DIRECT ACCESS TO SCHOOLS, JOBS, HEALTH CARE
AND OPPORTUNITIES. THIS PROJECT PROVIDES HOUSING
STABILITY ADDRESSES HOMELESSNESS AND ENSURES THAT
LONG TIME RESIDENTS AND THOSE WITH GREATEST NEED CAN REMAIN
IN THIS CITY THAT THEY HELP SUSTAIN.
>> THE MERAVIGLIA IS EXACTLY THE KIND OF TRANSIT ACCESSIBLE
COMMUNITY ROOTED AND EQUITY DRIVEN DEVELOPMENT AND THAT SAN
FRANCISCO MUST PRIORITIZE AT A TIME WHEN HOUSING INSECURITY
CONTINUES TO DISPLACE FAMILIES. WE URGE YOUR SUPPORT TO COME TO
MOVE LA MERAVIGLIA FORWARD WITHOUT DELAY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. THANK YOU FOR YOUR YOUR
COMMENTS. I'LL JUST MAKE A NOTE NO
AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF APPROVAL IF YOU ARE IN SUPPORT JUST WAVE
YOUR HANDS IS SUCH THAT THAT IS AN APPROVED BOARDROOM, RIGHT?
>> MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
DO WE HAVE ANY COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS FOR THE PROJECT
SPONSOR? >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU.
>> I JUST WANTED TO HEAR AND I DIDN'T HEAR IT OF THE
PRESENTATION WHY THERE IS A NEED FOR A SUBDIVISION OF THE
LOT. >> WHY IT'S COME BACK UP.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS KEVIN KETCHUM DIRECTOR OF
HOUSING DEVELOPMENT AT MISSION HOUSING.
IN ORDER TO FACILITATE THE TAX CREDIT FINANCE FOR EACH OF
THESE PARCELS THEY HAVE TO BE INDIVIDUALLY PARCELS.
ALSO TO GET A PERMIT FOR EACH OF THE BUILDINGS YOU WOULD HAVE
TO BE ON ONE PARCEL FOR EACH BUILDING.
>> THAT'S A REALLY TECHNICAL ANSWER.
CAN YOU JUST SAY IT AND LAY LAY TERMS?
YEAH, THREE DIFFERENT BUILDINGS IN ORDER TO QUALIFY FOR THE
FINANCING YOU NEED THEM TO BE THREE SEPARATE.
BUT WHAT'S DIFFERENT ABOUT THE BUILDINGS THAT THEY'RE
INDIVIDUALLY FINANCING DIFFERENT?
>> YEAH, THEY'LL BE INDIVIDUALLY OWNED BY SEPARATE
LLC. SO YOU'VE WORKED AT MAYOR'S
OFFICE OF HOUSING FOR YEARS WHO HAVE AS YOU REMEMBER SOME OF
THESE SETUPS. SO WE HAVE TWO.
WE HAVE TO FINANCE THEM INDIVIDUALLY AND THEY HAVE TO
HAVE THEIR PERMITS INDIVIDUALLY .
>> BUT WHY WHAT WHY ARE THEY DIFFERENT?
THAT MIGHT BE A QUESTION FOR THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA AS TO
WHY THEY AFFECT THEIR TAX CREDIT FINANCE THAT WAY.
DOES MO HAVE ANY BACKUP ON THAT?
>> THAT'S ALL I HAVE, MR. MOSS. CAN YOU JUST ANSWER THE
QUESTION? >> WHY ARE THEY DIFFERENT
BUILDINGS? WHY ARE WE NEED THE
SUBDIVISION? >> WELL, THERE ARE THERE ARE
THREE DIFFERENT BUILDINGS AND THREE DIFFERENT PLACES ONE
ON 16TH STREET, ONE ON MISSION STREET AND ONE ON CASS STREET.
>> THEY'LL ALL HAVE THREE DIFFERENT ADDRESSES.
YOU KNOW THEY'RE SERVING DIFFERENT POPULATIONS THAT ONE
WILL BE PERMANENTLY SUPPORTIVE HOUSING AS DISCUSSED AND THE
OTHER TWO WILL BE FOR SENIORS AND FAMILIES MOSTLY FAMILIES.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
NO PROBLEM. WHAT I WAS LOOKING FOR THANK
YOU. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR
MILLER. DON'T GO BACK.
I GOT WELL, MR. MOSS. >> I'LL BE YOU KNOW, I'LL BE
HONEST. I THINK THIS WAS THIS IS SHOULD
BE A PRETTY EASY APPEAL FOR YOU TO WIN.
I THINK ON THE ON THE SIMPLE LEGAL QUESTION I THINK YOU KNOW
THAT PROBABLY THERE'S THERE'S NOT A WHOLE LOT THE BOARD COULD
DO IF THE BOARD WERE CONCERNED ABOUT THIS PROJECT TO STOP IT
BASED ON A MAP A MAP APPEAL. BUT YOU DID GO FURTHER THAN
MAKING THAT ARGUMENT AND YOU DISCUSSED THIS AS SORT OF AS A
BATTLE BETWEEN PEOPLE OF PRIVILEGE WHO ARE OPPOSED TO
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD AND PEOPLE WHO
BELIEVE THAT AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS GOOD AND SHOULD BE IN THE
NEIGHBORHOOD. >> AND I DON'T SEE IT THAT WAY
NECESSARILY. >> I MEAN TO TO I DON'T THINK
THIS IS WHERE SUPERVISOR MELGAR WAS GOING BUT BUT ALL THREE OF
THESE BUILDINGS WILL BE AFFORDABLE.
THEY WILL HAVE DIFFERENT FUNDING SOURCES AND THEY WILL
BE SERVING THE NEEDS OF DIFFERENT POPULATIONS.
>> NOW I DON'T KNOW THE YOU KNOW I KNOW A COUPLE OF THE
APPELLANT'S I DON'T KNOW ALL OF THEM.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT THEIR MOTIVATIONS ARE.
MAYBE THEY HATE AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
I SUSPECT THAT'S NOT THE CASE. >> I THINK THERE'S A CONCERN
IN THE CITY RIGHT NOW AND I THINK WE SAW IT EARLIER IN THE
CONVERSATION ABOUT GEOGRAPHIC OR GEOGRAPHIC EQUITY THE REAL
LIFE LIVED EXPERIENCE OF PEOPLE IN NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE WHERE
HOMELESS SERVICES ARE BEING PLACED IS THAT ALL THAT THE
CITY PROMISES THAT THESE ARE GOING TO MAKE THINGS BETTER,
THAT OFTEN THEY DON'T AND I'VE SEEN THAT SOME IN MY DISTRICT I
THINK WE'VE SEEN IT IN OTHER DISTRICTS AND I AM I ACTUALLY
HAVE GREAT GRATITUDE AND RESPECT FOR MISSION HOUSING
AND NOT JUST DID A SMALL SITE PROJECT AND IN MY DISTRICT
THERE'S 12 PEOPLE WHO ARE ABLE TO LIVE IN THERE, YOU KNOW WHAT
THEIR LONG TERM HOMES BECAUSE BECAUSE OF THE WORK YOU'RE
DOING THERE I HEAR GOOD THINGS ABOUT MISSION HOUSING AND THEIR
OPERATIONS AND YOU KNOW, ALL THE TIME.
BUT I AM A LITTLE I MEAN SINCE WE'RE ON THE POLICY QUESTION OF
THIS WHEN I LOOK AT 16TH AND MISSION WHICH IS ONE OF THE
MAYORS VERY TOP PRIORITIES IN TERMS OF AREAS THAT NEED TO
GET CLEANED UP AND I HEAR THE REAL LIVE CONCERN FROM PEOPLE
WHO SEE WHAT HAPPENS WHEN AND MIGHT NOT BE ALL HOMELESS
FACILITIES BUT CERTAINLY SOME HOMELESS FACILITIES OR DRUG
RELATED FACILITIES DO SEEM TO MAKE THINGS WORSE LIKE WITH
WHAT CONFIDENCE AND WHY SHOULD THESE PEOPLE BELIEVE THAT THIS
WILL BE ONE OF THOSE CASES WHERE THINGS DON'T GET WORSE?
I MEAN ARE WE TALKING ABOUT THE THE ACTUAL APPEAL OR I MEAN I
WOULD HAPPILY YOU KNOW, I, I LOOK I GUESS YOUR STATEMENT WAS
ABOUT THE MOTIVATIONS. PEOPLE ARE WRONG.
I CAN SAY WITH CONFIDENCE THAT THE SUPPORTIVE HOUSING INDUSTRY
IS LEARNING AND GETTING BETTER THE BUDGET FOR OUR BUILDING
WILL BE MUCH MORE WITH MUCH MORE WRAPAROUND SERVICES THAN
EVER BEING BUILT. >> I WOULD ASK WHAT ELSE YOU
WOULD HAVE US DO THAN HOUSE HOMELESS PEOPLE.
I STAND BY MISSION HOUSING I STAND BY MISSION ECONOMIC
DEVELOPMENT AGENCY MORE THAN ANYTHING I STAND BY THE DECADE
AND THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE FROM THE MISSION WHO HAVE CALLED FOR
THESE BUILDINGS AT THESE INCOME LEVELS WE MISSION HOUSING
AND HEAT. >> I DO NOT PLAN ON MAKING
ANYTHING WORSE. WE PLAN ON MAKING AS MUCH
BETTER AS QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE. >> BUT I CAN'T YOU KNOW, I
DON'T HAVE A ONE TO GO TO THE FUTURE TO PROVE IT.
BUT YOU KNOW, WE'RE ALSO OPEN TO ANY SUPPORT THE CITY OF SAN
FRANCISCO, DPW, THE POLICE DEPARTMENT, THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WANT TO PROVIDE FOR THE CURRENT STATE OF THE
STREETS BECAUSE THAT'S NOT PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING IS
NOT. SUPERVISOR ONE THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT I, I WASN'T GOING TO CHIME IN.
I WAS GOING TO STICK TO THE INTENT OF THE HEARING.
>> BUT SINCE WE'RE HAVING A GENERAL CONVERSATION NOW I DO
JUST WANT TO SAY THAT THIS SITE HAS BEEN SOMETHING THAT
COMMUNITY HAS BEEN FIGHTING FOR FOR SO MANY YEARS.
I MEAN PRIOR TO MY ELECTION TO THE BOARD OF EDUCATION, PRIOR
TO MY ELECTION TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THERE WERE
OTHER PROJECTS PROPOSED AT THIS SITE THAT COMMUNITY FOUGHT
AGAINST AND MOST CERTAINLY THEY SHOULD HAVE.
AND THEN COMMUNITY CAME TOGETHER TO GET A SITE WHERE
WE'RE GOING TO SEE ALL AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
>> TO ME THAT IS ONE OF THE MOST WONDERFUL THINGS THAT CAN
HAPPEN IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO IS TO GET A
SITE THAT IS 100% AFFORDABLE, PARTICULARLY WHEN WE KNOW ALL
OF THE PRIOR ISSUES AROUND THE DEVELOPER AND WHAT WAS GOING TO
BE PROPOSED AT THIS SITE. I WENT AND HAD SEVERAL
CONVERSATIONS. OBVIOUSLY IT'S A DIFFERENT
SCHOOL COMMUNITY NOW BUT MOST CERTAINLY SPENT TIME WITH
PARENTS AND FAMILIES AT MARSHALL AT THAT TIME.
BUT THE REALITY OF IT IS WE NEED MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING
IN SAN FRANCISCO. WE NEED MORE PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND THERE ARE SEVERAL WAYS TO MITIGATE ALL CONCERNS THAT HAVE
BEEN BROUGHT UP FROM THE SCHOOL COMMUNITY AS WELL AS ANY
COMMUNITY. BUT I KNOW THAT THERE'S
OVERWHELMING SUPPORT EXCUSE ME FOR THIS PROJECT.
THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
WITH THAT WE WILL GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF OF OF THE
OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT.
IF YOU WOULD LINE UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER
NEAR THE CURTAINS. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST
SPEAKER. >> COME ON UP.
>> WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
>> YES, PROCEED. HI THERE.
MY NAME IS CONOR ALLEN, LONG TIME RESIDENT, FIRST TIME
SPEAKER TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
I'M HERE BECAUSE I WANT TO HIGHLIGHT THE COST OF
BUREAUCRATIC DELAY. >> I'M BORN AND RAISED IN THE
BAY AREA RESIDENT OF THE MISSION 16TH STREET AND BART IS
MY BART STATION. AND WE DESERVE BETTER THAN AN
ABANDONED WAL-MART. THE ALTERNATIVE TO BUILDING
SOMETHING THAT'S GOING TO HOUSE PEOPLE AND SUPPORT PEOPLE IS AN
EMPTY STOREFRONT AND AN EMPTY PARKING LOT THAT BECOMES A
PLACE FOR THESE ISSUES TO GET WORSE.
I DEEPLY CARE FOR THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE THEIR CHILDREN IN THE
CITY. I HOPE TO BE SOMEONE WHO CAN
LIVE IN THE CITY AND RAISE MY KIDS HERE.
>> WE ARE GOING TO BE MORE CAPABLE OF MAKING THE CITY A
SAFE PLACE OF HOUSING PEOPLE WITH A AFFORDABLE HOUSING
DEVELOPMENT AT THIS LOCATION RATHER THAN AN EMPTY WALGREENS
SORRY EMPTY WALGREENS THAT THE POLICE HAVE TO SORT OF SKIRT
AROUND THE EDGES AND CONSTANTLY SWEEP UP AFTER SAN FRANCISCO
NEEDS PEOPLE WHO LOVE IT. MISSION HOUSING IS A GROUP OF
PEOPLE WHO LOVE THIS CITY AND LOVE MEANS A LOT MORE WITH
ACTION AND BUILDING THE SUPPORTIVE HOUSING, BUILDING
THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING THAT INCLUDES SUPPORT FOR FAMILIES
IS THAT ACTION THAT WE NEED AND THE BUREAUCRATIC DELAY IS
GOING TO CONTINUE THE PROCESS THAT WE HAVE SEEN WHICH IS THE
DECAY OF THE STORY. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO, MY NAME IS NICK ROETHLISBERGER.
I LIVE IN THE MISSION AND I CAN'T THINK OF A REASON THAT
YOU I MEAN THIS IS THE PERFECT PLACE.
THERE'S 300 AFFORDABLE UNITS ON TOP OF A BART STATION IN THE
HEART OF THE CITY. YOU KNOW, FOR YEARS PEOPLE HAVE
COMPLAINED WELL, WE DON'T WANT MARKET RATE HOUSING.
THIS IS 100% AFFORDABLE AND NOW THERE'S COMPLAINTS THAT IT WILL
ATTRACT THE WRONG KIND OF PEOPLE.
>> I CAN'T WAIT FOR THIS TO GET BUILT SO THAT MORE PEOPLE CAN
LIVE IN MY NEIGHBORHOOD. THERE'S A LONG LINE OF PEOPLE
AND I'LL STOP. IT'S RIDICULOUS.
IT'S IT'S THE WEAPONIZATION OF PROCESS.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER HI.
>> MY NAME IS RUTH FERGUSON AND I LIVE IN BERNAL HEIGHTS.
>> I AM REALLY PROUD TO BE HERE WITH DINA NEIGHBORS FOR HOUSING
TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF LA MARAVILLA WHICH WILL ADD OVER
350 UNITS OF DESPERATELY NEEDED 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR OUR
COMMUNITY. >> SAN FRANCISCANS HAVE STOOD
LOUD AND PROUD IN OPPOSITION TO TRUMP'S FASCIST ICE RAIDS.
>> WE'VE OPEN OUR HEARTS TO RESIDENTS FACING HOMELESSNESS
AND ADDICTION AND WE CHAMPION OUR SAN FRANCISCO VALUES WITH
COMPASSION AND SENSIBLE SOLUTIONS TO EVEN OUR GREATEST
CHALLENGES. >> SO WHY WOULDN'T WE SUPPORT
THIS CRITICALLY NEEDED AFFORDABLE HOUSING?
WHY WOULDN'T WE STAND TOGETHER TO SUPPORT EVIDENCE BASED
HOUSING FIRST SOLUTIONS FOR OUR NEIGHBORS WHEN WE NEED IT MOST
? THERE'S BEEN A LOT OF TALK
TODAY ABOUT THE IMPACT ON CHILDREN'S AND FAMILIES OF THIS
SITE AS A PERUSE APPROVED. >> BUT WHAT ABOUT THE CHILDREN
AND FAMILIES WHO WILL BENEFIT FROM THIS PROJECT?
>> WHO WILL HAVE A ROOF OVER THEIR HEADS BECAUSE OF THIS
PROJECT? >> I SYMPATHIZE WITH THE
CHALLENGES FACED BY OUR MISSION NEIGHBORS.
I REALLY DO AND I DON'T WANT TO MINIMIZE WHAT THEY'VE
EXPERIENCED. I HEAR YOU WHEN YOU SAY WHEN
YOU SHARE HOW TOUGH IT'S BEEN. >> TO BE CLEAR, I SUPPORT
BUILDING THIS 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING SITE IN THE MISSION.
BUT I KNOW THAT WEALTHIER COMMUNITIES LIKE MY OWN
IN BERNAL HEIGHTS NEED TO STEP UP AND WELCOME MORE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING IN OUR OWN NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> THAT'S WHY MY COLLEAGUES AND I DENY NEIGHBORS FOR
HOUSING HAVE BEEN VOCAL IN ASKING THE CITY TO INCLUDE
BERNAL HEIGHTS IN THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN SO WE CAN SEE MORE
HOUSING LIKE LAMAR VILLA IN OUR OWN BACKYARD.
>> WE MUST ADDRESS THE RACIST HISTORY OF EXCLUSIONARY ZONING
AND SHARE IN THE HOUSING BURDEN FACED BY OUR NEIGHBORS IN THE
MISSION. >> POVERTY AND HOMELESSNESS IS
A POLICY FAILURE AND IT'S A POLICY CHOICE.
I URGE ALL OF YOU TO DENY THIS APPEAL AND INSTEAD BUILD A
FUTURE THAT CREATES OPPORTUNITY FOR ALL SAN FRANCISCANS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS BRANDON POWELL.
I'M A MEMBER OF DISTRICT NINE NEIGHBORS FOR HOUSING.
THE CONCERNS ABOUT STREET CONDITIONS THAT WERE
HIGHLIGHTED IN THE APPEAL PERFECTLY VALID.
IT IS APPALLING. IT'S AN INJUSTICE THAT THIS
CITY ALLOWS NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE THE MISSION AND THE TENDERLOIN
TO BEAR THE BRUNT OF THESE CONDITIONS THAT WOULD NEVER BE
TOLERATED IN OTHER PARTS OF THE CITY.
THAT'S NOT A REASON TO STOP HOUSING.
THIS HOUSING WILL ADDRESS THOSE VERY CONDITIONS.
IT MAY BE INCREMENTAL BUT IT IS STILL PROGRESS.
I ENCOURAGE YOU I IMPLORE YOU I BEG YOU DON'T STOP THIS
PROJECT. >> APPROVE THIS SUBDIVISION
WHICH THE PROFESSIONALS IN CITY GOVERNMENT HAVE INDICATED IS
COMPLETELY WARRANTED AND ALLOW THIS PROJECT TO PROCEED
AND LET'S GET SOME MORE NEIGHBORS.
LET'S TAKE CARE OF SOME PEOPLE WHO NEED HELP.
>> PEOPLE WITH SUBSTANCE ABUSE ISSUES ARE NOT PARIAHS.
THERE ARE NEIGHBORS. >> THERE ARE FAMILY.
THERE ARE FRIENDS. >> SO THAT'S THAT'S NOT A
PROBLEM THAT WE WOULD HOUSE MORE OF THESE PEOPLE.
LET'S PROVIDE SOME HOUSING FOR SENIORS WHO DESPERATELY NEED IT
FOR FAMILIES WHO DESPERATELY NEED THIS HOUSING.
WE'VE GOT TO DO THIS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS PHILLIP RAFFEL. I'M RESIDENT OF DISTRICT EIGHT
VALLEY AND I COME OUT IN SUPPORT OF THIS PROJECT
AND REJECT THE APPEAL. >> MUCH HAS BEEN SAID ABOUT
PERMIT SUPPORT, SUPPORTIVE HOUSING AND THE RISK IT
INVOLVES. >> I JUST BURIED MY FRIEND
EARLIER THIS YEAR WHO OVERDOSED IN THAT IN DOWNTOWN SAN
FRANCISCO. HE WOULD HAVE BENEFITED FROM
PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING TO CLEAR AND IT MIGHT HAVE SAVED
HIS LIFE. IT'S TOO LATE FOR HIM TO THE
FAMILIES WHO ARE WHO ARE MENTIONING THEY FEAR FOR THEIR
CHILDREN. >> I CAN UNDERSTAND I'M NOT NOT
FAR FROM LA MARAVILLA I WAS NEARLY JUMPED TWO YEARS AGO
AND WOULD HAVE BEEN BEATEN UP BY SEVERAL BY SEVERAL MEN HAD
IT NOT BEEN FOR MY 100 POUND ROTTWEILER THAT I WAS WITH THAT
DAY. I UNDERSTAND THE SAY THAT
STREET SAFETY IS A CONCERN AND IT IS A VALID ONE BUT
FURTHERMORE MORE MUCH HAS BEEN TALKED ABOUT IN HOUSING ABOUT
HOW IT'S A GIFT TO DEVELOPERS. THIS IS A NONPROFIT DEVELOPER
BUILDING 300 UNITS OF HOUSING FOR FAM FOUR FAMILIES INCLUDING
CHILDREN WHO ARE WHO ARE WHO GO TO MARSHALL AND WOULD NEED THAT
HOUSING. IT IS FAR BETTER TO BE HOUSED
BUT HAVING TO DEAL WITH STREET SAFETY AND AND THEN TO BE
UNHOUSED AND AT THE MERCY OF THE STREETS.
>> I THINK THIS I THINK IF WE FAIL AT THIS MAGGARD COULD NOT
HAVE CHARACTER TO THE INEFFECTIVENESS OF SAN
FRANCISCO BETTER AND WE WOULD DESERVE IT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO. MY NAME IS KATE VOCAL.
I AM A LONGTIME RESIDENT OF THE MISSION AND A MEMBER OF DINA
NEIGHBORS FOR HOUSING AND I FULLY SUPPORT THIS PROJECT
IN ITS TOTALITY AND I'M GOING TO TELL YOU WHY.
I WAS A PROJECT ARCHITECT FOR SEVERAL OCCUPIED REHABS OF
TENDERLOIN SORROWS BACK IN THE EARLY 2000S.
SO I WAS WORKING DAY IN AND DAY OUT WITH EXACTLY THE KINDS OF
PEOPLE WHO WOULD BE LIVING IN THE PCH IN THIS PROJECT.
AND ONE DAY I WAS DOING A FINAL WALKTHROUGH OF UNIT AS A WOMAN
WAS MOVING IN AND WE ALWAYS PUT LIKE A LITTLE SHELF IN THE
KITCHENETTE. SHE BROUGHT ME OVER THERE TO
SHOW ME HER MOM'S CHINA. >> AND SHE WAS SO PROUD TO BE
ABLE TO AFTER CARRYING IT AROUND IN A BAG FOR I BELIEVE
SIX YEARS TO BE ABLE TO PUT IT ON THIS LITTLE SHELF THIS
LITTLE SHELF IN THIS LITTLE ROOM TRANSFORMED THIS WOMAN'S
LIFE, TRANSFORMED IT. AND HERE WE ARE 20 YEARS LATER
AND WE HAVE BARELY MADE A DENT IN TRYING TO GIVE THAT
TRANSFORM EMOTIVE EXPERIENCE TO THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE IN OUR CITY
. WE DECIDED IN THE MISSION EIGHT
YEARS AGO THAT WE WANTED THIS TO BE 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
AND EVERY SINGLE DELAY COST LIVES.
IT COSTS PEOPLE IN TRAUMA. IT COSTS OUR CITY VITALITY
AND IT'S TIME TO NOT LET THIS PROCESS STOP THE THE PROGRESS.
SO I URGE YOU ALL TO DENY THIS APPEAL AND LET'S GET THIS BUILT
AND LET'S GET THESE HUNDREDS OF FAMILIES AND INDIVIDUALS
IN NEED HOUSED IN THE MISSION. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. >> HI, MY NAME IS CHARLIE
ITALY. I'M A RESIDENT OF MISSION BAY.
I JUST WANTED TO COME AND SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF THIS PROJECT.
NUMBER ONE, IT JUST 300 HOMES IS A LARGE NUMBER I THINK ABOUT
IT'S 300 HOUSEHOLDS OR OVER SORRY OVER 300 OVER 300
HOUSEHOLDS THAT WOULD BE TRANSFORMED BY THIS IS PROBABLY
ENOUGH TO FILL THIS ROOM MULTIPLE TIMES.
AND SO I JUST I'M HERE SUPPORTING THIS TO THINK ABOUT
ALL THE LIVES THAT COULD BE SUPPORTED BY THIS PROJECT.
SECONDLY, WE KNOW WE HAVE TO BUILD A LARGE NUMBER A VERY,
VERY LARGE NUMBER OF AFFORDABLE UNITS BASED ON THE HOUSING
ELEMENT. AND EVERY EVERY SINGLE PROJECT
THAT WE CAN DO REALLY COUNTS A LOT.
>> LASTLY, I THINK THE WAY THAT WE'VE GOTTEN HERE FEELS A
LITTLE BIT WRONG TO ME. >> THIS IS LIKE WE ARE GETTING
HERE. WE'RE HAVING AN ENTIRE HEARING
BASED ON A LEGAL TECHNICALITY AROUND PARCEL SUBDIVISION.
AND YET THE MAJORITY OF THE THINGS WE'RE TALKING ABOUT HAVE
NOTHING TO DO WITH THAT. TO ME THIS SETS A BIT OF A
DANGEROUS PRECEDENT THAT ONLY THOSE WITH THE ACCESS TO FREE
TIME AND LAWYERS CAN FIND THE LOOPHOLES TO BLOCK HOUSING.
>> SO OVERALL I WOULD I WOULD URGE THE BOARD TO TO APPROVE
THIS AND HELP TRANSFORM THE LIVES OF 300 OVER 300
HOUSEHOLDS. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> JUST A REMINDER TO THOSE IN THE VERY BACK OF THE PUBLIC
GALLERY NO AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF EITHER APPROVAL OR LACK OF
SUPPORT. WELCOME.
HI. >> I'M GOING TO BE TRANSLATING.
OKAY. I'LL SET THE TIMER FOR FOUR
MINUTES. YOU CAN SPEAK FOR TWO MINUTES
AND THEN TRANSLATE FOR TWO MINUTES.
>> OKAY
. >> IS SHOWING UP IN SUPPORT OF
THE CONSTRUCTION OF LA MARIA. SHE LIVES ON 18 AND MISSION
AND SHE'S LOOKING FOR SHE WANTS TO MAKE SURE THAT THERE IS AN
ENOUGH AND THAT SHE'S LOOKING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
>> SO THAT'S WHY SHE'S HERE. >> I THANK YOU FOR THE
INTERPRETATION. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> HI LAURA FOOT EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF YIMBY ACTION
AND THIS PROJECT OBVIOUSLY HAS SPECIAL MEANING FOR A LOT OF
US. >> I'VE BEEN DOING ADVOCACY FOR
TEN YEARS AND WAS A SUPPORTER OF THE MARKET RATE HOUSING AT
THE BEGINNING UNTIL MY NOW HUSBAND WAS LIKE SHUT UP LAURA
. >> AND REALLY THE AMOUNT OF
COMMUNITY BUILDING EDUCATE HAITIAN LEARNING THAT HAS COME
OUT OF THE PROCESS OF THIS PROJECT IN PARTICULAR FOR THE
PRO HOUSING MOVEMENT FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING ADVOCATES
THERE IS NO PROJECT THAT IS MORE POPULAR OR MORE WELL
DOCUMENTED AND HAS BROUGHT MORE PEOPLE TOGETHER IN SUPPORT OF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING THAN THIS PROJECT.
I THINK IT IS WITHOUT QUESTION SOMETHING THAT THIS SHOULD MOVE
FORWARD AND THAT THE CITY SHOULD EMBRACE.
IT BRINGS PEOPLE TOGETHER. CHIRAG WAS TELLING ME THAT HE
WAS HAVING MIXED FEELINGS ABOUT A LETTER OF SUPPORT FROM SONIA
STRAUSS SO I THINK THERE'S A LOT OF HUMOR TO BE HAD ABOUT
THIS AS WELL AND I THINK THAT THERE'S A THERE'S AN ASPECT OF
THIS THAT'S WELL THIS IS AN IMPORTANT BECAUSE WE HAVE THE
VOTES BUT ACTUALLY PEOPLE ARE AFRAID OF SUPPORTIVE HOUSING.
>> PEOPLE ARE AFRAID OF HOMELESS PEOPLE IN EVERY
NEIGHBORHOOD. >> PEOPLE ARE AFRAID OF DRUG
USERS. >> THEY'RE GOING TO BE AFRAID
IN EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD AND THAT'S GOING TO CREATE
CONCERNS IN EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD AND IT'S ACTUALLY
UNDERSTANDABLE AND HUMAN AND IT'S SOMETHING THAT THIS
BOARD HAS TO NAVIGATE AND BE RESILIENT TO BECAUSE YOU HAVE
ALREADY DECIDED THAT PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING IS A KEY
STRATEGY FOR ADDRESSING THE HOUSING SHORTAGE.
>> AND SO YOU HAVE TO ADDRESS EVERY TIME THIS COMES UP HOW
ARE YOU ACTUALLY GOING TO GET IT BUILT IN THE WEALTHIEST
NEIGHBORHOODS? I'VE SPOKEN IN SUPPORT OF
HOMELESS HOUSING IN MARIN. OKAY, IT GETS HARDER THAN THIS
BUT IT'S GOING TO GET HARDER FOR YOU IN SAN FRANCISCO AS WE
BUILD ON THE WEST SIDE, AS WE BUILD IN DISTRICTS THAT HAVE
DONE VERY LITTLE TO NO PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING.
THIS IS SUPPOSED TO BE THE EASY ONE AND WE'RE STILL HERE.
>> SO WHAT ARE YOU GUYS GOING TO DO TO ENSURE THANK YOU LAURA
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. OKAY.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS I CAN SPEND YOUR I'M HERE SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO DEMOCRATIC PARTY WHICH PASSED A RESOLUTION
IN MAY OF THIS YEAR CALLING ON SUPPORTING THE MAXIMUM
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AT LA MORAVIA THE MARVEL IN THE
MISSION AND AT THE TIME THE RESOLUTION THAT MY BODY BROUGHT
FORWARD WAS ABOUT A DIFFERENT SET OF COMPLAINTS SOME OF WHICH
WERE BROUGHT UP AN EARLIER PUBLIC COMMENT ABOUT THE
SHADOWING. BUT THE THE NOTION AT THE TIME
WAS THAT IT WAS MORE OR LESS CONCERNS WERE BEING RAISED
IN THE PRESS BUT THAT THIS PROJECT BECAUSE OF STATE LAW
THAT HAS BEEN DEBATED AND SETTLED AND LOCAL LAW THAT
HAS BEEN DEBATED AND SETTLED AND HOUSING ELEMENT PROPOSALS
AND DRAFTS MANY, MANY, MANY MEETINGS HAS BEEN DEBATED
AND SETTLED. THE CITY IS SUPPOSED TO BE
PRIORITIZING BUILDING SUPPORTIVE HOUSING BELOW MARKET
RATE HOUSING FOR PEOPLE WHO CANNOT AFFORD THE MARKET RATES.
WE HAVE TO BUILD A LOT MORE OF ALL HOUSING FOR SURE IN ORDER
TO ADDRESS OUR HOUSING SHORTAGE.
BUT THE SAN FRANCISCO DEMOCRATIC PARTY SUPPORTS
BUILDING THE MAXIMUM AMOUNT OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING AT THIS
PARTICULAR PLACE BECAUSE THE FAMILIES IN THE CITY NEED IT
PEOPLE WHO HAVE NOWHERE TO GO NEED IT.
AND I THINK THAT ONE OF THE PUBLIC COMMENTERS OR NOT THE
PUBLIC COMMENTERS ONE OF THE PROJECT SPONSORS SPOKE EARLIER
WHO SAID IF WE DON'T DO THIS, WHERE DO WE WHERE DO PEOPLE GO?
WHAT IS OUR ACTUAL SOLUTION? PEOPLE WILL DETERIORATE AND DIE
AND BE SUBJECT TO VIOLENCE AND BE SUBJECT TO OTHER THINGS
ON THE STREET. IF WE DO NOT ADDRESS THESE
CONDITIONS AND THE CITY SHOULD DO MORE TO ADDRESS ADDRESSING
THOSE STREET CONDITIONS. BUT WE ALSO NEED TO MAKE SURE
THAT WE ARE BUILDING PLACES FOR PEOPLE TO BE ABLE TO REBUILD
THEIR LIVES AND TO LIVE THE BEST LIFE THAT THEY CAN LIVE.
AND YOU CANNOT DO THAT IF YOU ARE LIVING ON THE STREETS.
SO THE SAN FRANCISCO DEMOCRATIC PARTY URGES YOU TO DENY THIS
SUBDIVISION APPEAL AND TO MAKE SURE THAT THIS PROJECT MOVES
FORWARD. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ROBERT DRUCKMAN. I AM A VOLUNTEER LEAD WITH SAN
FRANCISCO YIMBY I LIVE IN DISTRICT FIVE.
WE STRONGLY SUPPORT THIS PROJECT.
WE BELIEVE THE CITY SHOULD DO MORE TO CLEAR ADMINISTRATIVE
OBSTACLES THAT PREVENT THE CREATION OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
I WILL SAY THAT TWO WEEKS AGO I HAD NO IDEA THAT YOU COULD
APPEAL THE SUBDIVISION MAP FOR ANY KIND OF PROJECT MUCH LESS
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. PEOPLE WILL COME UP WITH ANY
KIND OF REASON TO JUSTIFY THEIR APPEAL IN 2016.
THEN SUPERVISOR SCOTT WIENER SPENT A LOT OF TIME TO PREVENT
A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
NOW MANY, MANY, MANY PROJECTS HAVE SKIPPED A CONDITIONAL USE
APPEALS OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND MORE STATE LAWS HAVE GONE
HAVE HAVE DONE A LOT TO STREAMLINE AFFORDABLE HOUSING
IN SAN FRANCISCO. BUT MORE WORK IS NEEDED.
ONE IMPORTANT LESSON FROM THIS HEARING SHOULD BE THAT APPEALS
OF PROJECTS IS NOT COMMUNITY PLANNING A APPEALS OR VETO
POINTS. IT IS AN INHERENTLY REACTIONARY
PROCESS. THE BEST OUTCOME IS THAT THE
CONTESTED PROJECT PROCEEDS AS PLANNED.
THE FREQUENT ALTERNATIVE IS THAT THE PROJECT DIES AND IT IS
WITH BITTER IRONY THAT I SAY THAT IN APPEAL OF A SUBDIVISION
MAP IS COMMUNITY INPUT BUT THAT DOESN'T MEAN IT'S CONSTRUCTIVE.
CITY LEADERS IN THIS VERY ROOM HAVE MADE IT CLEAR THAT
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS A PRIORITY FOR THE CITY OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND IF IT IS A PRIORITY THEN WE SHOULD DO WHAT
WE HAVE SET OUT TO DO. WE SHOULD NOT SAY WELL WE
SUPPORT AFFORDABLE HOUSING JUST NOT THIS ONE BECAUSE THAT IS
HOW WE HAVE GOTTEN TO THIS CRISIS OVER 50 YEARS OF SAYING
TIME AND TIME AGAIN WELL WE SUPPORT HOUSING JUST NOT THIS
PROJECT. THERE'S A REASON WHY
ADMINISTRATIVE PROCESSES DO NOT RESULT IN MORE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING. >> PLEASE APPROVE THIS PROJECT.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI, I'M MARIO.
I LIVE A BLOCK AWAY FROM THE PROJECT ON SOUTH VAN NESS.
I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT I'M REALLY LOOKING FORWARD TO
HAVING HUNDREDS OF NEW NEIGHBORS.
>> PLEASE DENY THE APPEAL. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS ELI HOLLERAN AND I'M HERE TO SPEAK AGAINST THE
APPEAL OF THE 1979 MISSION PARCEL PARCEL APPROVAL.
THIS APPEAL IS AN UNDEMOCRATIC ATTEMPT TO CIRCUMVENT
CALIFORNIA HOUSING LAWS INTENDED TO ALLEVIATE SEVERE
SHORTAGES OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN THE STATE.
THE 1979 MISSION PROJECT HAS MET ALL STANDARDS SET OUT UNDER
THE LAW FOR APPROVAL AND HAS IN FACT GONE ABOVE AND BEYOND
LEGAL REQUIREMENTS IN SEVERAL CASES BY HOLDING MULTIPLE
COMMUNITY MEETINGS IN THE MISSION TO GET OUR INPUT ABOUT
SHADE AND HEIGHT. THIS APPEAL IS UNRELATED TO THE
ACTUAL PARCEL MAP APPROVAL PROCESS AND ONLY RELATED TO THE
FRUSTRATIONS OF SOME OF MY NEIGHBORS AND HAVING TO
ACTUALLY SEE THE EFFECTS OF ANTI HOUSING ADVOCACY ON THEIR
CITY AND ON THEIR UNHOUSED NEIGHBORS.
I LIVE ONE BLOCK FROM THIS PROJECT AT 15TH AND SOUTH
VENICE AND I TEACH AT HOOVER THAT'S A MIDDLE SCHOOL THAT
RECEIVES STUDENTS FROM MOSCONI, THE OTHER CLOSE BY ELEMENTARY
SCHOOL AND THEY ATTEND IN SUTTON.
>> I WORK WITH STUDENTS FROM THE MISSION WHOSE FAMILIES ARE
UNHOUSED OR UNSTABLE HOUSED EVERY DAY IN SAWYER.
>> TO SAY YOU CARE ABOUT STUDENTS LIKE THIS AND THEN DO
ANYTHING OTHER THAN WHOLE HEARTEDLY SUPPORT A PROJECT
THAT WOULD HOUSE HUNDREDS OF LOW INCOME RESIDENTS THAT WOULD
HOUSE AS OF USC STUDENTS THAT WOULD HOUSE FAMILIES IS A
CONTRADICTION BEYOND RIDICULE. I AM ASHAMED AT THIS CLASS
AND HOSTILE BEHAVIOR FROM SOME OF MY NEIGHBORS AND I URGE YOU
TO RESPECT THE NORMS OF THE PARCEL APPROVAL PROCESS
AND UPHOLD THE VALUES OF A JUST AND WELCOMING CITY.
BY REJECTING THIS APPEAL AND UPHOLDING THE APPROVAL.
>> THANK YOU ELI, FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> WHEN I STARTED THIS
MINIMALIST GENEVA WERE
THANK YOU AND I'LL BE TRANSLATING.
GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS JENNY BARRAGAN.
I WORK WITH COMMUNITY AND LIVE AT 14TH AND MISSION STREET.
I SUPPORT FAMILIES WITH RESOURCES THE MOST VULNERABLE
FAMILIES WITH RESOURCES IN OUR COMMUNITIES THOSE IN SHELTERS
LIVING IN CARS AND SIMPLY ASKING FOR A DIGNIFIED
AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR THEMSELVES AND THEIR FAMILIES.
I SEE WITH GREAT SADNESS THE SUFFERING OF ALL THESE PEOPLE
AND I RESPECTFULLY COME TO YOU AND TRUST THAT YOU WILL MAKE
THE BEST DECISION AND MOVE FORWARD WITH THIS WONDERFUL
PROJECT SO THAT MANY FAMILIES CAN BENEFIT FROM IT AND HAVE
SAFE AND DIGNIFIED HOUSING. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR THE INTERPRETATION.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE WELCOME. >> WHEN I START THIS
THE DAILY ALERT LORI HER LIFE CHANGED FOR HER AND FOR HER
SON. AND THAT'S WHY SHE'S HERE TODAY
TO ASK YOU TO CONTINUE WITH THE PROJECT OF LA BEGAN TO ASK YOU
TO SUPPORT MORE FAMILIES AND TO ENSURE THAT MORE FAMILIES GET
BENEFITS SHADED BY THAT AND THAT THEY HAVE A PLACE TO
LIVE LIKE SHE DOES. >> AND THANK YOU FOR THE
INTERPRETATION. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
ALONG WITH UPTON ON EVERYBODY RESPECT THE SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS BLANCA TREJO. I AM COMMUNITY LEADER FOR THE
MISSION HOUSE IS THEREFORE IS TO BE CRAMMED IN A TWO BEDROOM
APARTMENT. WE WERE NINE PEOPLE LIVED
TOGETHER. MY CHILDREN HAD DIFFERENT
CHRONIC HEALTH CONDITIONS I LIVE IN CRAM WASN'T HELPING
THEIR HEALTH. >> MY DAUGHTER HAS ASTHMA
AND MY SON HAS ONLY ECZEMA IN THIS IF THE HIGH COST OF
HOUSING AND THE LACK OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR FAMILIES
TO LIVE CAMP CHILDREN THEY ROAM THE SPACE TO THEIR DAILY
DEVELOPMENT AND WELL US TO STUDY AND CONCENTRATE ON DOING
THEIR HOMEWORK. I SPENT SEVERAL YEARS APPLYING
THROUGH THE PORTAL FINALLY IN 2000 THROUGH 21 THANKS GOD I
WON THE LOTTERY AT THE BARNES BUILDING OTHER 490 SOUTH
BARNEYS WHICH IS A BLOCK FROM THE FRONT THE MARAVILLA.
>> NOW MY CHILDREN HAVE THEIR OWN SPACE TO STUDY AND DO THEIR
HOMEWORK. THEY DO VERY WELL IN THEIR
STUDIES AND THEY HEALTH HAS IMPROVED A LOT RIGHT NOW THERE
ARE MANY FAMILIES WITH CHILDREN IN SHELTERS.
THERE ARE CHILDREN AND ADULT WITH CHRONIC HEALTH CONDITIONS
AND LIVING IN A SHELTER VERSUS THEIR HEALTH BECAUSE THEY DON'T
HAD ACCESS TO COOKING IN. THEY SAID THAT THERE ARE LOTS
OF FAMILIES WITH CHILDREN LIVING IN CARS.
I HOPE THESE FAMILIES HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO HAVE A DECENT
HOUSING I THINK IS A HUMAN RIGHT THAT EVERY PERSON SHOULD
HAVE. I'M HERE TO CONTINUE ADVOCATING
FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF OR THE MARVEL THOSE AFFORDABLE HOUSING
FOR FAMILIES BECAUSE HAVING A STABLE HASN'T CHANGED YOUR LIFE
AND IMPROVED YOUR HEALTH AND GIVES YOU YOUR SECURITY.
HAVING THIS IN HOUSE IN WHATEVER YOUR FAMILY IS A
FOUNDATION FOR MOVING FORWARD AND OUR CHILDREN'S TO.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
THANK YOU. NEXT SPEAKER
I'M GOING TO DO MY BEST TO SUMMARIZE BECAUSE EVERYTHING
SHE SAID IS AMAZING AND SO POWERFUL.
BUT HER NAME IS GLADYS. SHE'S A BENEFICIARY OF THE
DOLLAR HOUSING LOTTERY AND SHE'S HAD IT FOR THE LAST
TWO MONTHS. >> SHE'S LIVED HERE FOR THREE
YEARS. BEFORE THAT SHE LIVED WITH 18
PEOPLE AND AS PART OF THAT HOUSING BECAUSE OF THE
SITUATION SHE WAS SEXUALLY ASSAULTED.
>> SHE'S A SURVIVOR OF SEXUAL ASSAULT AND AFTER SHE RECEIVED
THE HOUSING HER LIFE COMPLETELY CHANGED.
SHE WAS ABLE TO FINISH HIGH SCHOOL.
SHE LEARNED ENGLISH. SHE NOW IS ABLE TO LIVE HAPPILY
WITH HER GIRLFRIEND AND SHE'S ABLE TO LIVE A DIGNIFIED LIFE
AND SHE BELIEVES THAT EVERYBODY DESERVES HOUSING AND A CHANCE
TO BE ABLE TO THRIVE BECAUSE HOUSING ALLOWS FOR PEOPLE TO TO
NOT ONLY SURVIVE IN THE CITY BUT ALSO TO THRIVE AND LIVE
THEIR BEST LIVES. >> THANK YOU GUYS.
THANK YOU FOR THE INTERPRETATION.
>> ALL RIGHT. ARE THERE PLEASE COME ON UP
JUST BEFORE YOU SPEAK, SIR, I'LL JUST ASK IF THERE ARE ANY
OTHER ROOMS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD
AGAINST THE APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT PLEASE
COME FORWARD. ALL RIGHT.
>> WELCOME. GOOD AFTERNOON.
SUPERVISOR. SUPERVISOR THIS IS NIGHT ROMERO
ANIMATION MISSION RESIDENT WORKING FROM THERE FOR A LONG
TIME IN HOUSING AND BEING WITH MANY COMMUNITY ORGANIZERS
AND LEADERS FIGHTING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN THE
MISSION DISTRICT WE ARE PROUD TO BRING A LOT OF DEVELOPMENT
MORE THAN SEVEN HOUSING MORE THAN 800 FAMILIES AND THE
SITUATION IN 16 AND 24 AND CLUSTER 20.
I LIVE IN 20 STATE HISTORY. >> IT HAS BEEN FOR ALL THESE
YEARS AND WE WANT TO ADDRESS THOSE ISSUES.
>> WE HAD TO BRING TOGETHER THE ORGANIZE AND DEMAND FROM THE
CITY MORE SERVICES FOR PEOPLE THAT ARE IN DIFFICULT
SITUATION. >> THIS IS THE FIRST THING I
WAS DOING COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT FOR MOST OF THE PROJECTS IN THE
MISSION. THIS IS THE FIRST TIME THAT I
HEAR FROM COMMUNITY MEMBERS HERE TREATING HUMAN BEINGS LIKE
NOTHING AND I THINK THAT WE DESERVE BETTER.
WE DESERVE BETTER BECAUSE I, I, I WAS IN A COMMUNITY MEETING
WHEN A WOMAN A LATINA MOTHER WAS TALKING WITH THE MARSHALL
PARENTS TELLING THAT THANK YOU GOT ANOTHER JEW RELATIVES A SON
HAS A PROBLEM WITH ADDICTION WE HAD TO TREAT PEOPLE WITH
RESPECT AND BRING THEIR RESOURCES FOR THAT ONE OF THE
BUILDINGS IS FOR THAT PEOPLE WHO HAS BEEN USED ON ISSUES
THAT WE CAN SUPPORT THEM. THIS IS THE FIRST TIME THAT I
SEE THIS TREATMENT TO PEOPLE AND THIS IS UNACCEPTABLE FOR
SAN FRANCISCO. PLEASE DO THE RIGHT THING.
AND FROM PLACES 16 WHEN WE WERE FIGHTING FOR AGAINST THE
MONSTER WE MENTIONED THAT ONE BUILDING IT HAS TO BE FOR LOW
VERY LOW INCOME PEOPLE LIVING IN THE ASSURANCE NOW IS ALLOWED
TO LIVE WITHIN LIVING IN THEIRS ARE NOT NOW THEY ARE IN THE
STREET. >> WE HAD TO ALLOW PEOPLE TO
HAVE A BETTER CONDITION LIFE AND THEIR FAMILIES.
THERE WERE KEYS HERE. SOME PEOPLE HAD TO LEAVE BUT
THEY WERE REAL KEYS HERE ASKING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. HELLO, IT'S ME AGAIN.
MY NAME'S KRISTEN ACOSTA. >> I'M THE COMMUNITY PROGRAMS
MANAGER AT THE WOMEN'S BUILDING .
I'M ALSO A HOUSING ADVOCATE AND A RESIDENT OF THE MISSION
DISTRICT AND I'M HERE IN DEFENSE OF THIS 100 100%
AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT WHICH LIVES OFF THE BACK OF A
DECADE OF COMMUNITY ORGANIZING. MANY OF US KNOW THAT OUR
COMMUNITIES FOUGHT REALLY HARD FOR LA MARAVILLA BECAUSE WE
REALLY KNOW HOW URGENT AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS AS WELL
AS SUPPORTIVE SERVICES. >> OUR COMMUNITY MAKES UP A
REALLY WIDE RANGE OF INDIVIDUALS AND ALL OF THOSE
INDIVIDUALS WHETHER THEY'RE JUST INDIVIDUALS OR FAMILIES
THEY DESERVE THE RIGHT TO LIVE WITH DIGNITY AND SUPPORT AND WE
NEED TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT NO HUMAN BEING IS DISPOSABLE AS
OPPOSED TO A LOT OF THE THINGS WE ARE HEARING TODAY AND WITH
THAT MANY OF THEM WOULD BENEFIT FROM THIS PROJECT AND MANY OF
THESE PEOPLE HAVE FAMILIES WHO ARE WORKING TOWARDS A REALITY
THAT ENABLES THEIR HOUSEHOLDS NOT ONLY TO SURVIVE BUT ALSO TO
THRIVE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. WE SHOULD ALL BE COMING
TOGETHER AS A COMMUNITY TO PRIORITIZE HOUSING AND NOT
VILLAINIZE THOSE WHO NEED SUPPORT.
SO WE MUST GO FORWARD WITH MAKING THE MAHDAVI A REALITY
AND WE APPRECIATE YOUR SUPPORT .
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS,
MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
>> PUBLIC COMMENTS IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL IS
CLOSED AND NOW WE WILL HEAR FROM THE APPELLANT FOR A THREE
MINUTE REBUTTAL OF UP TO THREE MINUTES WE WERE TOLD FIVE
MINUTES REBUTTAL, FIVE MINUTES REBUTTAL, THREE MINUTES BUT
WE'RE EMAILED FIVE MINUTES I'M SURE IT WAS THREE MINUTES.
MR. SOLOMON MR. PRESIDENT, SUPERVISORS I'M MARK SOLOMON, A
36 YEAR RESIDENT OF MARSHALL NEIGHBOR.
I HELPED WRITE THE APPEAL. NONE OF US ARE ATTORNEYS.
WE DON'T HAVE A BUDGET OR A STAFF.
DANGER IS A LEGAL BASIS FOR GRANTING AN APPEAL ON A
SUBDIVISION MAP PROJECT SPONSORS HAVE INTRODUCED NO
EVIDENCE OF THE PROJECT AS PLANNED.
PURSUANT TO THIS MAP, BONDING WILL NOT ENDANGER MARSHALL SO
MANY WHITE MEMBERS FROM NOWHERE NEAR MARSHALL THAT HAVE NO SUCH
FACILITIES NEAR THEM SPOKE IN THE FIRST PERSON ABOUT OUR
NEIGHBORS PROJECTING THEIR PREJUDICES.
OUR NEW NEIGHBORS LIVE AT LA PHENIX CASA AVANZA AND 17TH
AND FOLSOM. OUR NEIGHBORHOOD NEEDS MORE
HIGHER FUNCTIONING NEIGHBORS LIKE THAT.
WHY DOES MR. MOSS INSIST ON IMPLYING CASTING AND BE
PREJUDICED ONTO RESIDENTS ABOUT EVERYTHING EVERY TIME HE OPENS
HIS MOUTH? MISSION HOUSING IS NOT
MITIGATED ANY IMPACTS AT LOVE ENIX MISS CLARK SAID THEY HAD
THE VOTES. HOW DOES SHE KNOW THAT WAS X
PARTY VIOLATED HERE I'VE WORKED TO BETTER THE MARSHALL
COMMUNITY WITH FORMER SUPERVISOR JANE KIM TO RECITE
PARKING EGRESS FROM 1550 15TH STREET TO DIVERT CARS AWAY FROM
MARSHALL AND WITH S.F. MTA ON THE HOME ZONE THAT CALM TRAFFIC
AROUND SCHOOLS SUPERVISOR WALTON'S CONCERNS I WAS ONE OF
THE FEW RESIDENTS IN THE NONPROFIT DOMINATED 16 THREE
PLAZA COALITION THAT WORKED ON THIS STUFF TEN YEARS AGO.
RIGHT? WE ADVOCATED FOR COMMUNITY
BASED PLANNING TO BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR FAMILIES
AND TO CARE TO CALL THREATS TO CALL FOR SOLAR ACCESS AT
MARSHALL. THAT'S ALL BEEN THROWN OUT THE
WINDOW WITH THE SUBDIVISION THAT IS WRONG.
I SUPPORT A SALES FORCE TOWER OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR
HOMELESS FAMILIES ON THAT PARCEL UNQUESTIONINGLY THAT'S
WHAT WE NEED PROJECT SPONSORS HAVE NOT REACHED OUT TO ANY
MARSHALL AREA RESIDENTS THEY CALL THEIR NONPROFIT CLERK TO
RIG PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT. THEY'VE KEPT THEIR CARDS CLOSE
TO THE VEST BECAUSE THEY KNOW THAT PERCEPTION IN PHASE ONE
WITH A GENDER OPPOSITION. THE FIRST WE LEARN WAS AT THE
MISSION CABINS COMMUNITY MEETING MEMBER MEETINGS SINCE
MISSION CABINS WENT IN WHERE MISSION CABINS TOLD US WHAT
WE'RE GOING TO GET. WE DIDN'T APPEAL BECAUSE IT WAS
THE ONLY WAY FOR THE COMMUNITY TO BE HEARD.
OUR CLAIMS THAT THE SUBDIVISION DOES INCREASE DANGEROUS.
THE RISK IN MARSHALL HAS NOT BEEN ADDRESSED BY SPONSORS
AND STANDS. WE LIVE THIS EVERY DAY MARSHALL
FAMILY SUPPORT DENSE AFFORDABLE HOUSING ON THE PARCEL
AND POSTED ON TOP OF THEIR KIDS SCHOOLS.
YOUTH HAVE A RIGHT TO BE SAFE AROUND AND WALKING TO THEIR
SCHOOLS AND YOUTH OF COLOR HAVE A RIGHT FOR THEIR CITY NOT TO
DO A RACISM TO THEM THIS SENDS A MESSAGE TO KIDS OF COLOR THAT
YOU ARE EXPENDABLE SECOND CLASS CITIZENS OF THE MARSHALL
COMMUNITY IS ANTI NIMBY. WE'VE TAKEN IN OUR BACKYARD BUT
MOST OF YOU WON'T EVER HAVE IN YOURS.
WE'VE SEEN THE WORK WE'RE DEMANDING OF THE CITY NOT BLOW
IT AGAIN AND FURTHER ENDANGER OUR NEIGHBORS.
KIDS PROJECT SPONSORS ARE THE NIMBYS HERE WE ARE THE END
BECAUSE WE WANT PERMANENT AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR FAMILIES
AS DENSE AS YOU CAN GET. WE CAN'T TRUST A SHAKY
NONPROFIT BUDGETS TO FOLLOW THROUGH WITH SECURITY
OBLIGATIONS. WHAT IF THEY LOSE FUNDING?
WE'RE SCREWED. >> DEFENDERS CALL ON SUPES TO
SUSTAIN THE APPEAL AND FORCE SPONSORS ON A COUNCIL A
NONPROFIT ARTS CLASSIC IS TO WORK WITH THE COMMUNITY TO
BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR HOMELESS FAMILIES THAT POSES NO
SUCH DANGERS. YOU'VE HEARD FROM THE
ELEMENTARY SCHOOL PRINCIPAL. OKAY.
FIRST DO NO MORE HARM THAN THE CITY HAS ALREADY DONE TO OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD. WE NEED TO BUILD UP.
WE DON'T NEED ANY MORE BURDEN. WE'VE TAKEN MORE THAN ANY OF
YOUR NEIGHBORHOODS HAVE EVER TAKEN AND WE WANT TO SEE
PERMANENT AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR HOMELESS FAMILIES AS HIGH
AS YOU CAN GO. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
AND MR. SOLOMON, WE'VE PRINTED OUT OUR COMMUNICATION AND WE'LL
PROVIDE IT TO YOU IN JUST A MOMENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. WITH THAT, THE PUBLIC HEARING
HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED AND AS PREVIOUSLY DISCUSSED,
WE'RE NOW GOING TO CONSIDER WHETHER TO APPROVE OR
CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE DECISION OF PUBLIC WORKS
AND THE TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP. AND I SEE THREE COLLEAGUES
IN THE QUEUE. SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN. >> SO THIS IS A RARE AND MAYBE
EVEN UNIQUE LAND USE APPEAL IN THAT I AM STRONGLY
SYMPATHETIC TO CONCERNS VOICED BY THE APPELLANTS BECAUSE THEIR
CONCERNS ARE VERY SIMILAR TO CONCERNS I HEAR REGULARLY FROM
THE RESIDENTS OF MY DISTRICT WHOSE HOMES AND BUSINESSES ARE
ADJACENT TO PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FACILITIES.
>> I WILL SAY IN THIS LITTLE ARCANE PROCEEDING, YOU KNOW
WE'RE HAVING A POLICY CONVERSATION NOW THAT MAYBE WE
WEREN'T PLANNING ON HAVING AS PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN SAID.
>> BUT I AM A LITTLE TROUBLED BY SOME OF THE CONFLATION
BETWEEN THE POLICY CONVERSATION AROUND AFFORDABLE HOUSING WHICH
I THINK EVERYONE SUPPORTS AND PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING WHICH I THINK HAS REAL PROBLEMS THAT WE AS
POLICYMAKERS REALLY NEED TO DIG IN ON AND HELP TO SOLVE.
AND THAT I WOULD ARGUE THAT WE IGNORE AT OUR PERIL VIRTUALLY
ALL PCH FACILITIES IN THIS CITY EMBRACE DRUG TOLERANT POLICIES
THAT ARE MANDATED BY CALIFORNIA'S IMPLEMENTATION OF
HOUSING FIRST. THIS OFTEN COMES UP IN PUBLIC
SETTINGS WITH THE RESIDENTS THAT I WORK WITH WHEN WE HAVE
PCH FACILITIES IN SOUTH OF MARKET, THE THINGS THAT END UP
ON SOCIAL MEDIA ARE PROVISIONS FROM THE HOUSING FIRST POLICY
SAYING THAT TENANT SCREENING AND SELECTION PRACTICES PROMOTE
ACCEPTING OUR CLEAN UP APPLICANTS REGARDLESS OF THEIR
SOBRIETY OR USE OF SUBSTANCES THAT THE USE OF DRUGS IN AND OF
ITSELF WITHOUT OTHER LEASE PROVISIONS IS NOT A REASON FOR
EVICTION. THAT RECOGNIZES DRUG USE AS AN
ADDICTION AS PART OF TENANTS LIVES WHERE TENANTS ARE ENGAGED
IN NONJUDGMENTAL COMMUNICATION REGARDING THEIR ALCOHOL
AND DRUG USE. SO THIS IS THE FEATURE AND THIS
IS AND THIS IS THE THING THAT RESIDENTS ARE OBJECTING TO
AND WHEN WE TELL THEM THAT THERE'S NOT GOING TO BE DRUG
RELATED BAD BEHAVIOR, THEY KNOW THAT WE'RE NOT ACCURATE ABOUT
THAT. I DON'T OPPOSE HOUSING FIRST.
I DO WISH CALIFORNIA BACK IN 2016 HAD EMBRACED AN
APPROACH TO HOUSING FIRST THAT THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION'S HUD
HAD RECOMMENDED WHICH THAT THERE SHOULD BE RECOVERY
INCLUSIVE. I APPLAUD THE WORK BEING DONE
BY MY PREDECESSOR MATT HANEY, WHO WAS IN THE LEGISLATURE
RIGHT NOW TRYING TO LEGALIZE FUNDING FOR DRUG FREE
AND RECOVERY ORIENTED HOUSING OPTIONS WITHIN OUR HOUSING
FIRST FRAMEWORK. BUT I DO THINK WE HAVE TO
ACKNOWLEDGE THE FACT THAT PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING
SITES IN OUR CITY ARE ROUTINELY AMONG THE MOST RESPONDED TO
RESIDENTIAL ADDRESSES FOR 911 CALLS FOR SERVICE AND THAT'S
ESPECIALLY TRUE FOR POLICE CALLS FOR SERVICE.
AND THAT CAN BE SOMEWHAT EXASPERATING BECAUSE WHAT I
HEAR FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING AND WHAT I HEAR FROM OUR NONPROFIT PARTNERS IS THAT
NO ONE HAS IT IN THEIR BUDGET TO PROVIDE SECURITY FOR SITES.
AND AS A MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WHO HAS SOME
RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ENTIRE CITYWIDE BUDGET BUDGET THAT'S
EXASPERATING TO HEAR BECAUSE THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO IS PROVIDING SECURITY.
WE'RE PROVIDING THE MOST INEFFICIENT AND EXPENSIVE
SECURITY BECAUSE THE POLICE DEPARTMENT IS SHOWING UP AT
THESE FACILITIES ONCE OR TWICE A DAY WHEN WE COULD BE HAVING
MAYBE RETHINKING ABOUT HOW WE'RE FUNDING THESE SO THAT
WE'RE AVOIDING THOSE PROBLEMS. OUR FAILURE TO DO SO IS WHY
WE'RE LOSING THE CONFIDENCE OF SAN FRANCISCANS.
>> ONE THING I THINK WE CAN ALL AGREE ON IS THAT AS A CITY WE
SEEM TO BE ASKING PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING TO SOLVE
PROBLEMS THAT PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING WAS NEVER
INTENDED TO SOLVE. I HAD A HEARING LAST YEAR ON
SECURITY ISSUES AROUND PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING
INCLUDING ONE THAT WAS IN MISSION BAY IRONICALLY NEXT
TO THE PUBLIC SAFETY BUILDING A BLOCK THAT ONE WOULD EXPECT TO
BE THE SAFEST IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THERE THAT WAS ONE OF THE
TOP CALLS FOR POLICE SERVICE AND THE CALLS ABOUT DRUG USE
AND VIOLENCE AND NUISANCE BEHAVIOR WERE JUST OFF THE HOOK
AND THERE WAS IN THAT HEARING A LOT OF TALK FROM NEIGHBORS
AND ALSO RESIDENTS OF THE FACILITY TALKING ABOUT THE FACT
THAT THERE WAS A WOMAN WHO SPENT ALL NIGHT SCREAMING
AND NOBODY COULD GET ANY SLEEP. >> AND AFTER THAT HEARING I WAS
HAUNTED THAT YES, WE HAVE RESIDENTS ACROSS THE STREET WHO
ARE OBJECTING TO THE NOISE FROM THE WOMAN SCREAMING AND YES,
THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO ARE IN THAT PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING FACILITY WHO ARE UPSET BECAUSE THERE'S A WOMAN
SCREAMING. BUT I'M ALSO HAUNTED BY THE
FACT THAT I HAVE HAD A CONSTITUENT WHO SPENT THE NIGHT
SCREAMING AND WHAT ARE WE DOING FOR HER AND WHAT WE OWE THE
KIND OF LEVEL OF CARE THAT WE OWE HER AND WHAT WE GAVE HER
INSTEAD WAS A LEASE AND A KEY. WE I THINK WE FINALLY GOT THAT
PERSON THE LEVEL OF CARE THAT SHE NEEDED.
BUT THAT IS SOMETHING ELSE THAT I THINK WE AS POLICYMAKERS NEED
TO HAVE SERIOUS CONVERSATIONS ABOUT.
>> TWO WEEKENDS AGO I HAD I HAD TO CALL 911 MYSELF FOR A
NEIGHBOR OF MINE WHOSE MY DOG IS FRIENDS WITH HER DOG SHE
DOESN'T HAVE A PHONE. SHE LIVES IN A PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FACILITY. SHE'S BEING THREATENED BY
SOMEBODY THERE AS SOMEBODY WHO'S VERY OUT ABOUT BEING
IN RECOVERY FROM ADDICTION MYSELF I HEAR FROM A LOT OF
PEOPLE IN THE RECOVERY COMMUNITY WHO LIVE IN PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING WHO ARE BEGGING AND PLEADING WITH ME TO
DO EVERYTHING I CAN TO FIGHT FOR DRUG FREE AND RECOVERY
HOUSING OPTIONS. I HAD ONE CONSTITUENT WHO EVEN
SAID IF IT WEREN'T FOR THE FACT THAT HE HAD THE RESPONSIBILITY
TO TAKE CARE OF A DOG HE WOULD RATHER BE ON THE STREET.
>> IT WAS A MAD HOUSE WHERE HE WAS LIVING.
SO I DO THINK THAT YOU KNOW, I ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THIS
PARTICULAR PROJECT HAS ITS OWN HISTORY BUT I WOULD FEEL MUCH
BETTER TO HEAR FROM NONPROFIT PARTNERS AND ANY CITY
POLICYMAKER IS THAT WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO TO LISTEN TO
OUR SIDES, TO HEAR ALL PERSPECTIVES AND TO ACKNOWLEDGE
PROBLEMS WHERE THEY EXIST. AND I'M TROUBLED WHEN I HEAR
PEOPLE SORT OF SHAMED AS PRIVILEGE NIMBYS WHEN I DON'T
THINK THAT'S TRUE. >> ALL THAT BEING SAID, YOU
KNOW THE BOARD'S LEGAL DUTY HERE IS TO ADDRESS WHAT IS AT
ISSUE IN THIS APPEAL. THIS IS A TENTATIVE MAP UNDER
THE PLANNING CODE A SUBDIVISION OF A PARCEL, A PARCEL I AGREE
WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S CONCLUSION THAT THE APPELLANT'S
CONCERNS RELATE TO MATTERS THAT ARE OUTSIDE OF THE TENTATIVE
MAP THAT'S UNDER APPEAL. I'LL BE SUPPORTING THE PROJECT
OPPOSING THE APPEAL BASED ON THIS PROCEEDING BUT AS
POLICYMAKERS BECAUSE THE POLICY CONVERSATION CAME UP, I THINK
IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT THAT WE ALL RECOGNIZE THAT WE HAVE A
LOT OF WORK TO DO IN THIS CITY TO GET PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING. RIGHT.
AND I HOPE THAT WE WILL CONSIDER THINGS THAT WE CAN DO
TO EXPAND DRUG FREE AND RECOVERY INCLUSIVE OF
OPTIONS IN OUR PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING PORTFOLIO.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
>> I ALSO WILL BE SUPPORTING THE PROJECT IN VOTING AGAINST
THE APPEAL. IT IS, YOU KNOW, FAIRLY
STRAIGHTFORWARD IN TERMS OF THE TECHNICAL ASPECTS OF IT AND WE
HEARD FROM THE DEVELOPER THAT IT IS NEEDED FOR THE PROJECT TO
PROCEED WITH FINANCING BUT I WANTED TO ADDRESS A COUPLE OF
THE ISSUES THAT HAVE BEEN BROUGHT UP MORE PHILOSOPHICALLY
IN THIS CONVERSATION LIKE MY COLLEAGUE FROM DISTRICT SIX.
>> SO ONE OF MY VERY FIRST JOBS IN SAN FRANCISCO WAS WORKING
FOR AN ORGANIZATION CALLED THE IRISH CENTER THAT PROVIDED
PERINATAL ALL SUPPORT TO WOMEN WHO USE DRUGS OUTRIGHT.
THERE ARE BETWEEN 14TH AND 17TH AND YOU KNOW, ROUGHLY THAN
VALENCIA AND CAPP STREET AND AT THE TIME WE WERE STILL YOU
KNOW, IN THE DAYS OF AIDS TRANSMISSION IN MY JOB WAS TO
HAND OUT CONDOMS AND BLEACH TO THE LADIES WHO WORKED IN THE
SORROWS ON MISSION STREET AND THIS WAS A POPULATION THAT
WAS THEN ON THE STREETS 30 YEARS AGO AND IT'S STILL THERE
NOW. >> SO I DON'T THINK IT IS
CORRECT TO SAY THAT THE MISSION CABINS OR LE PHENIX OR ANY OF
THESE NEW ACTIVITIES HAVE, YOU KNOW, BROUGHT THIS POPULATION
BECAUSE I CAN TELL YOU THIS POPULATION WAS ALWAYS THERE
AND NO, IT HAS NOT INCREASED. THE DRUG OF CHOICE IS
DIFFERENT. BACK THEN IT WAS HEROIN A
DECADE BEFORE THAT IT WAS CRACK.
TODAY IT'S FENTANYL. BUT I YOU KNOW TO TO YOUR POINT
AT SUPERVISOR DORSEY, I DO THINK WE HAVE A RESPONSIBILITY
TO LOOK AT HOW WE'RE SPENDING OUR DOLLARS TO SEE WHETHER WHAT
WE ARE SPENDING ON WORKS AND IF IT DOESN'T WORK TO ADJUST THE
MODEL BUT I CAN TELL YOU THAT 30 YEARS AGO WHEN MOST OF THESE
FOLKS WERE LIVING IN SRO THAT ARE PRIVATELY OWNED WITH NO
SERVICES THAT DIDN'T WORK EITHER.
SO YOU KNOW, I, I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, WE HAVE SPENT A LOT
OF TIME TALKING ABOUT GETTING PEOPLE OFF THE STREETS, GETTING
SUPPORTS AROUND THEM. >> I DO BELIEVE THAT PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING IS PART OF THAT ANSWER.
I DON'T THINK IT'S THE WHOLE ANSWER.
I DON'T THINK IT'S A MODEL THAT WORKS PERFECTLY.
I THINK THAT THERE'S AN EVOLUTION THAT NEEDS TO HAPPEN
IN LIFE THAT WE CAN DO. BUT ONE THING I'M SURE OF IS
THAT IT'S UNACCEPTABLE TO HAVE PEOPLE LIVING ON THE STREETS
DECAYING TO THEIR DEATH USING AND NOT PROVIDING THEM
SERVICES. SO THIS PROJECT WILL BUILD A
HOUSING FOR FOLKS WHO HAVE STRUGGLED WITH DRUG ADDICTION
AND ALSO FOR SENIORS AND ALSO FOR FAMILIES WHICH WE
DESPERATELY NEED. SO I ALSO WAS ON THE PLANNING
COMMISSION AND WHEN WE HELD THE HEARING ON THE PROJECT THAT DID
NOT GO FORWARD THAT WAS PROPOSED BY MAXIMUS WE HELD A
HUGE HEARING AT MISSION HIGH SCHOOL WHEN WHERE HUNDREDS OF
COMMUNITY MEMBERS YOU KNOW, LATINO COMMUNITY, CHINESE
COMMUNITY FOR THE YIMBY'S EVERYONE CAME OUT AND TALKED
ABOUT HOW WHAT WE NEEDED IN THE MISSION WAS DEEPLY AFFORDABLE
HOUSING. SO THERE WERE PROTESTS THAT THE
CASE 16 COALITION THIS WAS YOU KNOW ALMOST A DECADE OF WORK OF
COMMUNITY ORGANIZING TO MAKE SURE THAT WE HAD AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AT THIS CORNER AND I AM PROUD TO SUPPORT IT NOT TO
MINIMIZE THIS AT THE ISSUES MARSHALL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL HAS
BEEN IN THIS SPOT NOT IN THE SAME BUILDING IN THIS SPOT FOR
100 YEARS IN THE CONDITIONS ON THE STREET ARE UNACCEPTABLE.
I DON'T THINK IT'S DUE TO AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
I DON'T EVEN THINK IT'S DUE TO PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING.
I THINK IT IS A FAILURE OF OUR CITY GOVERNMENT TO PROVIDE
SECURITY SERVICES FOR THIS COMMUNITY AND TO PROVIDE
HOUSING AND SERVICES THAT ARE TARGETED AND ADEQUATE.
BUT I THINK THAT HOUSING IS ACTUALLY PART OF THE SOLUTION
AND I'M PROUD TO DENY THE APPEAL.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT MET AND I
JUST WANT TO SAY AS WE LOOK AT THE APPEAL ITSELF, I BELIEVE
THAT PLANNING AND DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS HAVE GIVEN THE
APPROPRIATE RESPONSE IN TERMS OF WHAT IS ALLOWABLE BY CODE
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. BUT WHAT I WAS GOING TO SAY
BEFORE I INTERRUPTED MYSELF WAS THE ISSUES THAT HAVE BEEN
RAISED HERE BY COMMUNITY ONE ARE NOT TO BE INVALIDATED
IN OUR IMPORTANT BUT I ALSO THINK THAT THERE ARE WAYS TO
MITIGATE THOSE CONCERNS AND THIS WOULD ACTUALLY NOT BE
THE FIRST TIME WHERE WE HAVE SEEN A SITUATION WHERE WE'VE
HAD PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING AND OTHER TYPES OF
HOUSING QUITE FRANKLY THAT FOLKS DON'T NECESSARILY GET
EXCITED ABOUT AND CLOSE PROXIMITY TO SCHOOLS, TO
BUSINESSES AND TO OTHER RESIDENTS OR AREAS.
BUT THIS PROJECT IS VERY IMPORTANT AND IF I GO BACK
AND LOOK AT PROJECTS LIKE WHEN WE HAD CONVERSATIONS ABOUT
BRINGING A STAY OVER SITE TO ONE TO VISIT THE HORACE MANN
AND THE WORK THAT WE HAD TO DO WITH THE SCHOOL COMMUNITY WHEN
I WAS ON THE BOARD OF EDUCATION THEN AND SUPERVISOR RONEN WAS
IN OFFICE OR EVEN THE PROXIMITY OF THE SAFE PARKING SITE TO
BRETT HART AND MY COMMUNITY WHERE WE HAD TO WORK ON HOW WE
WOULD MITIGATE CONCERNS OF COMMUNITY SORT OF CONCERNS ARE
VERY REAL BUT THE WORK THAT HAS GONE INTO GETTING TO THIS POINT
AT THIS SITE IS ALSO VERY REAL AND IS SOMETHING THAT I ALSO
CANNOT OVERLOOK AS WE HAVE A POLICY CONVERSATION AND I WOULD
LOVE FOR ALL HOUSING TO BE 100% SUBSTANCE ABUSE FREE BUT THE
REALITY OF IT IS WE CANNOT KEEP PEOPLE LIVING ON THE STREETS
BECAUSE OF ADDICTION OR BECAUSE OF SOME OF THE THINGS THAT
MIGHT AFFECT THEM NEGATIVELY. WE HAVE TO PROVIDE THE HOUSING
I THINK THERE IS A BIGGER CONVERSATION TO YOUR POINT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY BUT MOST CERTAINLY WE HAVE TO GET
EXCITED ABOUT A PROJECT THAT IS GOING TO PROVIDE HOUSING FOR
SENIORS THAT IS GOING TO PROVIDE HOUSING FOR FOR
FAMILIES THAT IS GOING TO PROVIDE PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING AND GET FOLKS OFF THE STREET ALL THE SERVICES THAT
NEED TO ACCOMPANY THAT. THAT'S IMPORTANT AND WE HAVE TO
FIGHT TO MAKE SURE THAT THAT HAPPENS.
MITIGATING THE CONCERNS THAT WERE EXPRESSED TODAY BY A
SCHOOL COMMUNITY. ABSOLUTELY.
WE HAVE TO COME UP WITH STRATEGIES TO MITIGATE THAT.
BUT THIS IS AN IMPORTANT PROJECT FOR THE CITY.
IT'S AN IMPORTANT PROJECT FOR THAT COMMUNITY AND I DO NOT
LIVE IN A MISSION BUT I MOST CERTAINLY HAVE WORKED CLOSELY
WITH A LOT OF LEADERS IN THAT COMMUNITY AROUND THIS
PARTICULAR PROJECT FOR A VERY LONG TIME AND THIS IS SOMETHING
THAT IS WELCOME AND IN COMMUNITY THE PEOPLE EXPRESSED
CONCERNS MOST CERTAINLY THEY'RE VALID AND I THINK THAT A LOT OF
THAT CAN BE MITIGATED AND OBVIOUSLY THERE ARE GOING
TO BE MORE CONVERSATIONS ABOUT HOW TO COME TOGETHER, WHAT TO
DO TO ADDRESS CONCERNS. BUT FROM A POLICY STANDPOINT
THIS IS IMPORTANT HOUSING THAT THIS COMMUNITY HAS FOUGHT FOR
FOR OVER A DECADE QUITE FRANKLY.
BUT EVEN POLICY ASIDE AND MY PERSONAL FEELINGS ASIDE, IF WE
TAKE THE HEAR ON THIS HEARING ON ITS MERITS, WE HAVE TO STAND
BY IT PLANNING AND DPW. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS, PRESIDENT ADELMAN THANK YOU,
COLLEAGUES. I HAVE A LOT TO SAY SO EVERYONE
BUCKLE UP. >> FIRST OFF, IT'S KIND OF A
FULL CIRCLE MOMENT. I MYSELF WAS IN THE AUDIENCE AT
MISSION HIGH SO MANY YEARS AGO IN SUPPORT OF THIS PROJECT
AND THEN COMMISSIONER MELGAR, PRESIDENT OF THE COMMISSION WAS
PRESIDING OVER THE TOWN HALL AND SO THIS IS INDEED A LONG,
LONG JOURNEY THAT THAT BEGINS SO BEYOND THIS ROOM AND SO
BEYOND THE PEOPLE IN THIS ROOM JUST FIRST OFF, THIS APPEAL IS
NOT IN FACT AN APPEAL OF THE PROJECT ITSELF.
IT'S A CHALLENGE TO A MINISTERIAL SUBDIVISION OF THE
PARCEL MAP WHICH IS A PROCEDURAL STEP HANDLED BY THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS AND IS REQUIRED FOR THE PROJECT
TO PROCEED. >> THIS IS NOT THE EXACT PROPER
VENUE FOR OPPOSING THE PROJECT ITSELF.
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT REVIEW THIS APPLICATION IN COMPLIANCE
WITH STATE HOUSING LAWS THAT REQUIRE CITIES TO APPROVE
QUALIFYING AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECTS MINISTERIAL
MINISTERIAL. IN SHORT, THE CITY FOLLOWED
STATE LAW. >> LAMARR VILLA IS A 100%
AFFORDABLE AND PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING DEVELOPMENT
WITH DEEP ROOTS IN COMMUNITY ORGANIZING AND PUBLIC NEED THAT
MEETS BOTH THE LETTER AND THE SPIRIT OF STATE LAW AND THE
APPEALS CLAIMS ABOUT THE PROJECT ALL FALL UNDER THE
PURVIEW OF PLANNING APPROVAL OF THE PROJECT NOT PUBLIC WORKS
SUBDIVISION OF THE PARCEL MAP AND PLANNING CLEARLY DID THEIR
DUE DILIGENCE AND COMPLIED WITH THE LAW IN APPROVING THIS
PROJECT BUT HOLDING THE LAND USE MATTERS FOR ASIDE I WANT TO
TAKE SOME TIME TO ADDRESS THE CONCERNS RAISED ABOUT PUBLIC
SAFETY FULL STOP. >> IT'S NOT ACCEPTABLE FOR
CHILDREN OR MARSHALL STUDENTS TO FEEL UNSAFE WALKING TO
SCHOOL OR TO SEE PUBLIC DRUG USE OR BE SUBJECT TO VIOLENCE
FROM DAY ONE MY OFFICE HAS BEEN ACTIVELY WORKING WITH CITY
DEPARTMENTS TO IMPROVE SAFETY AND CONDITIONS AT 16 STREET
AND THE SURROUNDING AREA. >> IT'S BEEN A TOP PRIORITY FOR
ME NOT AN AFTERTHOUGHT. MY STAFF AND I, WE ALL LIVE
IN THE MISSION. WE WALK THROUGH 16TH STREET
EVERY DAY. >> WE MONITOR CONDITIONS AT THE
BART PLAZA AND NEARBY BLOCKS. >> WE ARE CONSTANTLY ON THE
PHONE WITH RESIDENTS SMALL BUSINESS AND COMMUNITY ORGS.
>> ONE OF MY FIRST ACTS IN OFFICE WAS TAKING THE
MAYOR ON A WALK DOWN 16TH STREET VOTING TO SUPPORT THE
MAYOR'S FENTANYL EMERGENCY ORDINANCE AND ASK HIM TO
UNFREEZE THE VENDING INSPECTORS THAT WERE CAUGHT IN IS HIRING
FREEZE AND WE GOT THEM UNFROZEN.
THEY'RE OUT THERE TODAY. I TOLD THE MAYOR I WOULDN'T BE
SUPPORTING A RENEWAL OF THE FENTANYL EMERGENCY ORDINANCE IF
IT DOESN'T BENEFIT THE MISSION AND IF CONDITIONS DETERIORATE
REGARDING DISPLACEMENT WHICH IS WHAT I HEAR ABOUT ALMOST EVERY
DAY I HEAR YOU. >> I'VE BEEN CONSISTENTLY
BEATING THIS DRUM ABOUT THE CITY'S FAILED STRATEGY OF
DISPLACING PEOPLE FROM NEIGHBORHOODS TO NEIGHBORHOOD
AND BLOCK TO BLOCK. IT WAS THEN AS A PD COMMANDER
LOU MONTHS AGO OUT OF COMMITTEE HEARING OPENLY ADMITTING THAT
DISPLACEMENT IS PART OF SFP STRATEGY FOR MANAGING PUBLIC
DRUG USE SUPERVISOR DORSEY IF YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT
INEFFICIENT SECURITY I SUBMITTED A LETTER OF INQUIRY
TO S.F. PD TWO WEEKS AGO AND RECENTLY FOUND OUT FROM THE
ANSWERS THAT S.F. PD AND THE SHERIFF'S HAS SPENT UPWARDS OF
$350,000 OF OVERTIME RESPONDING TO ANTI ICE AND ANTI TRUMP
PROTESTS. >> IT WAS THIS BOARD WITH
MYSELF AND SUPERVISOR WALTON DISSENT THAT APPROVED $9
MILLION IN OVERTIME WITHOUT ANY INSIGHT AT ALL INTO HOW
OFFICERS ARE SPENDING THEIR OVERTIME HOURS.
>> THAT'S WHY I CONTINUED TO HOLD AS A PD ACCOUNTABLE FOR
CALLING OUT SICK THE SAME DAY THAT SOME OFFICERS ARE
MOONLIGHTING AS PRIVATE SECURITY AND THE TEN BE RUN A
COP PROGRAM AS OPINION SHERIFFS GOT MORE THAN $50 MILLION
IN THIS BUDGET FOR OVERTIME AND WAGE INCREASE.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY YOU SAID THE ORGANIZATIONS AND OPERATORS OF
PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING DON'T HAVE ENOUGH FUNDING FOR
SECURITY. >> WE DON'T EVEN GIVE THEM
ENOUGH FUNDING TO PROVIDE LIVING WAGES FOR CASEWORKERS.
MAYBE THEY WOULD HAVE FUNDING IF THE CITY GAVE JUST A SMIDGE
OF THE HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS THAT GOES TO POLICE
OVERTIME AND INVESTS IT IN AMBASSADORS AND ENGAGEMENT
SPECIALISTS THAT ARE GOING TO BE OUTSIDE THESE PLACES.
>> ASIDE FROM THAT, I'VE BEEN IN A FERVENT SEARCH IN MY FIRST
SIX MONTHS IN OFFICE FOR LONG TERM SOLUTIONS THAT WORK.
I CONVENED A HEARING CO-SPONSORED BY MEMBERS OF THIS
BOARD VISOR MAHMUD'S VISOR, DORSEY'S VISOR, WALTON'S
RESOLUTION ON THE FOUR PILLARS STRATEGY IN LIGHT OF INCREASED
PUBLIC DRUG USE AND RISING RISING OVERDOSES IN THE MISSION
. AND IN THIS HEARING I ASKED
THIS AS A PD AGAIN WHAT IS THEIR PLAN TO MITIGATE
DISPLACEMENT AND THEY COULDN'T PROVIDE AN ANSWER AND WHERE WE
LEARNED THAT ZURICH, SWITZERLAND IN THE FACE OF A
SIMILAR CRISIS DEPLOYING THE STRATEGIES OF HARM REDUCTION
PREVENTION TREATMENT AND ENFORCEMENT TO DRAMATICALLY
TRANSFORM THEIR CITY INTO ONE OF THE SAFEST CITIES IN THE
WORLD. >> A SMART BALANCE STRATEGY IS
RIGHT THERE. >> BUT SO FAR WHAT I'VE SEEN
FROM OUR BUDGET DECISIONS IS THAT THE CITY CONTINUES TO BET
THAT ENFORCEMENT ALONE AND THE ACCEPTED NATURAL DISPLACEMENT
OF PEOPLE FROM NEIGHBORHOOD TO NEIGHBORHOOD IS WHAT'S GOING TO
GET US OUT OF THIS MESS. IN MAY I HOSTED A TOWN HALL
ALONGSIDE AS A PD BART THE NEW DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT NEIGHBORHOOD TEAM SPECIFICALLY TO GIVE THE
COMMUNITY THE OPPORTUNITY TO SHARE CONCERNS ABOUT 16TH
STREET AND THE SURROUNDING AREAS WHEN THAT SHOOTING
HAPPENED OUTSIDE OF MARSHALL, MY OFFICE CONNECTED MARSHALL
DIRECTLY WITH THE ASIAN MISSION STATION POLICE CAPTAIN TO
ENSURE FAMILIES AND STUDENTS FELT SAFE COMING BACK TO SCHOOL
. >> I'VE BEEN WORKING ON
ADVANCING SUSTAINABLE LONG TERM SOLUTIONS INCLUDING MEANINGFUL
VENDING REFORMS TO PROMOTE SAFETY AND A MORE STRATEGIC
PUBLIC HEALTH RESPONSE TO THE DRUG CRISIS THAT PRODUCES REAL
OUTCOMES AND DATA NOT HEADLINES AS IN THIS BUDGET I ADVOCATED
FOR $2 MILLION TO BE ALLOCATED TO NON-POLICE COMMUNITY
ENGAGEMENT SPECIALISTS TO SUPPLEMENT SECURITY ALL ALONG
MISSION STREET FROM 24 TO SIXTH STREET 16TH AND WHILE WE DIDN'T
GET ALL OF THAT 2 MILLION WE DIDN'T PRESERVE THE
COMMUNICATION SPECIALISTS TO BE ABLE TO TRANSFER THEM TO WHERE
THEY WERE AROUND 20 SECOND TO THE 16TH STREET AREA WHERE THEY
ARE NOW ENSURING THAT CHILDREN AND THEIR FAMILIES CAN GET TO
AND FROM PHENIX YOUTH ART EXCHANGE AND THE 16TH STREET
CORRIDOR AND AGAIN I DON'T THINK THAT'S ENOUGH.
MY STAFF AND I WE ALL HAVE LONG AND SHORT TERM GOALS FOR
COMMUNITY SAFETY. OUR DRUG OVERDOSE CRISIS
HOMELESSNESS AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND I TRULY BELIEVE
THEY ARE ALL MUTUALLY REINFORCING.
>> I ENVISION A 16TH STREET CORRIDOR WHERE CHILDREN CAN
WALK SAFELY WITH THEIR FAMILIES TO MARSHALL TO YOUTH ART
EXCHANGE TO BART AND TO HOME. >> I BELIEVE IN A 16TH STREET
THAT CELEBRATES THE BEAUTY OF OUR AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURE
DISTRICT AND OUR LATINO IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY WHERE WE
HAVE TRANSIT ORIENTED AFFORDABLE HOUSING WHERE BART
AND MUNI RIDERS FEEL SAFE AND DARE I SAY PLEASE TO TAKE
PUBLIC TRANSIT AND WHERE SMALL BUSINESSES THRIVE.
>> I WOULD SAY THE MAJORITY OF THE MISSION AND THE PUBLIC
SERVANTS THE POLICE OFFICERS, PUBLIC HEALTH WORKERS, VENDING
INSPECTORS, STREET OUTREACH WORKERS WHO WORK DAY IN AND DAY
OUT ALL AROUND 16TH STREET SHARE THAT VISION TOO.
I HAVE LONG BEEN A CHAMPION FOR LOW INCOME STUDENTS, FOR
HOMELESS FAMILIES, FOR WORKING CLASS FAMILIES AND I WILL
CONTINUE TO BE I MYSELF WAS RAISED BY A SINGLE MOM IN A LOW
INCOME NEIGHBORHOOD. I LIVED IN A MULTIFAMILY
HOUSING COMPLEX SURROUNDED BY GANG VIOLENCE.
>> MY NEIGHBOR OWNED A LIQUOR STORE ACROSS THE STREET AND WAS
MURDERED. >> I KNOW WHAT IT'S LIKE TO
GROW UP IN A DANGEROUS NEIGHBORHOOD AND I'M
SYMPATHETIC TO THE CONCERNS ABOUT SAFETY FOR KIDS
AND FAMILIES. BUT THIS IS NOT A LAND USE
ISSUE. IT'S AN INVESTMENT ISSUE.
>> 16TH STREET THE SURROUNDING AREA IS HOME TO PEOPLE OF ALL
WALKS OF LIFE, ALL INCOMES. IT'S VIBRANT, IT'S MULTIRACIAL.
IT'S A GEM. >> AND I ALSO WANT TO USE THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO IMPLORE EVERYONE WHO WANTS TO SEE THIS PROJECT
COME TO FRUITION TO CONTINUE TO JOIN ME AND THE FAMILIES OF THE
MARSHALL STUDENTS AND THE CHILDREN LIVING THEIR LIVES
IN THIS AREA TO CONTINUE ADVOCATING FOR REAL
INVESTMENTS. THIS AREA DESERVES THIS BUDGET
SEASON BUDGET CUTS EVISCERATED SAFETY PROGRAMS, SAFETY NET
PROGRAMS IN DISTRICT NINE AND IF THIS CITY IS ALL ABOUT
ABUNDANCE RIGHT NOW, ABUNDANCE FOR WHOM?
>> ABUNDANCE FOR DOWNTOWN. ABUNDANCE FOR AIR COMPANIES,
FOR MARKET RATE DEVELOPERS, ABUNDANCE FOR POLICE OVERTIME
BUT NOT ABUNDANCE FOR 16TH STREET NOT ABUNDANCE GUIDED
AND GROUNDED IN BLACK AND BROWN LEADERSHIP AT 16TH STREET WE
NEED MORE COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT SPECIALISTS TO SUPPLEMENT
SECURITY MORE RESPITE CENTERS FOR PEOPLE TO EXIST, MORE GREEN
SPACE FOR KIDS, MORE FOOT PATROLS FROM AN ACCOUNTABLE
AND COMMUNITY INTEGRATED S.F. PD, MORE FUNDING FOR COMMUNITY
LED ACTIVATIONS, MORE GRANTS FOR AMERICAN INDIAN AND LATINO
ARTISTS AND PERMANENT VENDORS. >> OUR ATTENTION CAN'T JUST BE
ON DOWNTOWN AT THE EXPENSE OF NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE THE MISSION.
SO LET'S NOT MAKE THIS A ONE AND DONE DEAL.
LET'S MAKE THIS A COLLECTIVE CALL TO ACTION.
>> WE NEED ALL HANDS ON DECK NOT JUST FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING
,NOT JUST FOR SOLUTIONS TO HOMELESSNESS BUT FOR INVESTMENT
AND ACTIVITY. >> ADDING 16TH STREET AND THE
SURROUNDING AREA. I DO WANT TO HIGHLIGHT A LETTER
SENT BY UNITED TO SAVE THE MISSION THE SAN FRANCISCO
LATINO TASK FORCE S.F. LATINO PARITY AND EQUITY COALITION
THAT IS SUPPORT OF THIS PROJECT ON MANY GROUNDS INCLUDING
SUPPORTING TRANSIT ORIENTED DEVELOPMENT FOR POOR
AND WORKING CLASS PEOPLE OF COLOR.
>> THE ADDICTION CRISIS AMONG AMERICAN INDIANS AND RESEARCH
THAT HOUSING IS A KEY FACTOR IN HEALING THE TRAUMA
AND HEALTH RELATED CONDITIONS INCLUDING SUBSTANCE USE
DISORDER, THE MISSION THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL
DISTRICT UNDER MY TENURE WILL CONTINUE TO BE AN HONOR.
THE ORIGINAL PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT THAT FOUGHT THE MONSTER IN THE
MISSION AND AGITATED FOR AND WON LA MORAVIA UNDER MY
TENURE THE MISSION WILL CONTINUE TO BE A WELCOMING
PLACE FOR ALL PEOPLE OF ALL WALKS OF LIFE AND ALL MEANS
AND UNDER MY TENURE I WILL CONTINUE TO FIGHT FOR THE
SAFETY OF ALL CHILDREN NO MATTER THEIR RACE, CLASS OR
HOUSING SITUATION. AND WITH THAT COLLEAGUES I'M
MOVING TO APPROVE ITEM 57 AND TABLE ITEMS 58 AND 59.
>> SECOND, THERE HAS BEEN A MOTION FROM SUPERVISOR FIELDER
SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR MELGAR TO APPROVE TENDED MAP DECISION
BY APPROVING ITEM 57 TABLING 58 AND 59.
I DON'T SEE ANYBODY ELSE IN THE QUEUE.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO APPROVE
ITEM 57 AND TABLE 58 AND 59 SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SAUTER EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION ITEM 57 IS APPROVED ITEMS 59 AND 58 AND 59 ARE
TABLED MADAM CLERK THAT CONCLUDES OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDER AND NOW WE'LL GO BACK A FEW HOURS AND I BELIEVE WE WERE
WE HAD JUST FINISHED ITEM 31 AND SO MADAM CLERK COULD YOU
PLEASE CALL ITEMS 32 THROUGH 36 TOGETHER ITEM 32 THROUGH 36 OUR
FIVE RESOLUTIONS THAT PERTAIN TO AMENDMENTS TO AGREEMENTS OR
GRANTS FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF DISABILITY AND AGING SERVICES
AND THE FOLLOWING ENTITIES FOR ITEM 32.
THIS IS AN AMENDMENT TO THE AGREEMENT WITH THE SAN
FRANCISCO HEALTH PLAN FOR CAL AME COMMUNITY SUPPORT SERVICES
FOR FOUR YEAR TERM THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 WITH ANTICIPATED
REVENUE OF APPROXIMATELY 6 MILLION TO THE CITY.
ITEM 33 THIS APPROVES A THIRD AMENDMENT TO THE AGREEMENT WITH
THE SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH PLAN FOR ENHANCED CARE MANAGEMENT
FEE FOR SERVICES HAVING ANTICIPATED REVENUE OF 3.9
MILLION TO THE CITY THIS TERM IS THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028.
ITEM 34 THIS ITEM APPROVES THE FIRST AMENDMENT TO AN AGREEMENT
WITH THE INSTITUTE ON AGING FOR THE PROVISION OF THE COMMUNITY
LIVING FUND PROGRAM TO INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATELY
14.2 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL OF 25.6 MILLION WITH THE TERM
EXTENSION BY TWO YEARS THROUGH NOW JUNE 30TH 2027.
TO CLARIFY THE SCOPE OF THE SERVICES AND TO ADD APPENDICES
CONSISTENT WITH THE ONGOING RECEIPT OF FEDERAL FUNDING,
ITEM 35 APPROVES A GRANT AGREEMENT WITH SELF-HELP FOR
THE ELDERLY FOR THE PROVISION OF CONGREGANT NUTRITION
SERVICES FOR OLDER ADULTS PROGRAM.
THIS HAS A FOUR YEAR TERM THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029 AND A
TOTAL AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 11.1 MILLION AND FOR ITEM 36 IT
APPROVES A GRANT AGREEMENT WITH SELF-HELP FOR THE ELDERLY FOR
THE PROVISION OF HOME DELIVERED NUTRITION NUTRITION SERVICES
FOR OLDER ADULTS PROGRAM WITH A FOUR YEAR TERM THROUGH JUNE
30TH 2029 AND A TOTAL AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 13.9 MILLION.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THESE ITEMS ON ITEMS 32 THROUGH
36 SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO EYES SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN I BATTLEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES
SUPERVISOR SANDRA SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 37 TO 39 TOGETHER ITEMS
37 THROUGH 39 ARE THREE RESOLUTION THAT PERTAIN TO REAL
PROPERTY LEASES FOR THE PORT. >> ITEM 37 APPROVES A PORT
COMMISSION LEASE NUMBER L DASH 17 25 THREE WITH TECH OF
CALIFORNIA INC FOR APPROXIMATELY 22,000FT2 OF
SHARED SPACE AND APPROXIMATELY 11,000FT2 OF PAVED LAND AT PIER
80 4A3 YEAR TERM WITH THREE ONE YEAR OPTIONS TO EXTEND FOR A
NOT TO EXCEED AMOUNT OF 2.7 MILLION APPROXIMATELY ITEM 38
THIS RETROACTIVELY APPROVES PORT COMMISSION LEASE NUMBER L
DASH 1725 SIX WITH AUTODESK INC LOCATED AT PIER NINE SUITE 116
AND BAYS ONE THROUGH THREE FOR A 36 MONTH LEASE WITH 112 MONTH
OPTION TO EXTEND THE TERM THROUGH JANUARY 31ST 2028 FOR
APPROXIMATELY 33,000FT2 OF SHED SPACE 1600FT2 OF SHARED SPACE
FOR STORAGE APPROXIMATELY 6600 LICENSED SQUARE FEET OF ROOF
SPACE AND 6594FT OF ON THE MARGINAL WHARF LOCATED BETWEEN
PIER NINE AND PIER 15 FOR USE AS OFFICE SPACE RESEARCH
AND DEVELOPMENT WORKSHOP SPACE AND PUBLIC ACCESS FOR A MONTHLY
RENT OF 147,004 ITEM 39 THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO TO EXECUTE A
MUTUAL TERMINATION AGREEMENT WITH GOMEZ RESTAURANT INC FOR
PREMISES ALONG L SCHOEMAN WAY OVER BAY WATER AND I THINK WE
CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 40 ITEM
40 THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO TO
ACCEPT AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE 12 A $12.4 MILLION
GRANT AWARD FROM THE CALIFORNIA STATE TRANSPORTATION AGENCY
PORT FREIGHT INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM TO FUND THE PIER 80
SUBSIDENCE PROJECT FOR THE PERIOD OF AUGUST 1ST 2025
THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 AND WE CAN DO THIS ONE SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
41. >> ITEM 41 THIS RESOLUTION
RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC
AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $179,000
GRANT INCREASE FOR A NEW TOTAL OF 679,000 FROM JOBS FOR THE
FUTURE. >> A RECIPIENT OF THE GRANT
AWARD FROM THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF LABOR EMPLOYMENT
AND TRAINING ADMINISTRATION FOR THE RAPID INFORMATION
TECHNOLOGY EMPLOYMENT INITIATIVE GRANT DURING THE
GRANT TERM JUNE 25TH, 2021 THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH 2025
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 40 TWO ITEM 40 TWO
THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT APPROVES AN INCREASE IN THE NOT
TO EXCEED AMOUNT FOR THE GENERAL AND ADMINISTRATIVE COST
FOR CLEAN POWER SFA PARTICIPATION IN THE CALIFORNIA
COMMUNITY POWER AUTHORITY BY APPROXIMATELY 3.5 MILLION FOR A
NEW AMOUNT OF 8.2 MILLION WITH NO CHANGE TO THE DURATION
THROUGH NOW DECEMBER 31ST 2014 EIGHT.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 43 AND 44
TOGETHER ITEMS 43 AND 44 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT
RETROACTIVELY APPROVE TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND GRANTS FOR THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH FOR ITEM 43 THIS IS A $106,000
GRANT FROM THE NATIONAL INSTITUTES OF HEALTH THROUGH
FRED HUTCHINSON CANCER CENTER FOR A PROGRAM ENTITLED
STATISTICAL METHODS FOR ADVANCING HIV PREVENTION FOR
THE TERM MARCH 1ST, 2023 THROUGH FEBRUARY 28TH 2026
AND FOR ITEM 44 THIS IS A $108,000 GRANT FROM THE
NATIONAL INSTITUTES OF HEALTH THROUGH THE FAMILY HEALTH
INTERNATIONAL PANEL FOR PARTICIPATION IN A PROGRAM
ENTITLED HIV PREVENTION TRIALS NETWORK THROUGH NOVEMBER 30TH,
2025 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 45 ITEM 45 RESOLUTION TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE
MAYOR AND THE DIRECTOR OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO EXECUTE A GRANT AGREEMENT WITH
180 JONES ASSOCIATES LP FOR 6 MILLION FOR A 25 YEAR TERM TO
PROVIDE OPERATING SUBSIDIES FOR A 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING
PROJECT HOUSING FOR LOW INCOME AND FORMERLY HOMELESS
HOUSEHOLDS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 46.
ITEM 46 THIS MOTION APPROVES THE AMENDMENTS TO THE
PROFESSIONAL SERVICES CONTRACT AGREEMENT WITH WEST COAST
CONSULTING GROUP FOR SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT SERVICES TO
IMPLEMENT A STATE OF THE ART LEGISLATIVE MANAGEMENT SYSTEM
TO THE EXTENT THAT FUNDS HAVE BEEN APPROPRIATED FOR THAT
PURPOSE. 2 MILLION FOR IT.
2 MILLION APPROXIMATELY 1.2 TO 3.2 FOR AN INITIAL TERM OF FIVE
YEARS ENDING AUGUST 31ST 2028 WITH TWO OPTIONS TO EXTEND THE
TERM 4 OR 5 ADDITIONAL YEARS EACH SAME HOUSE SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 447 THROUGH 51 TOGETHER ITEMS
47 THROUGH 51 ARE FIVE RESOLUTIONS THAT ACCEPT VARIOUS
REPORTS FOR THE SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT OVERSIGHT BOARD FOR
CALENDAR YEAR 2024. ITEM 47 ACCEPTS THE FIRST
QUARTER REPORT. ITEM 48 ACCEPTS THE SECOND
QUARTER REPORT. ITEM 49 ACCEPTS THE THIRD
QUARTER REPORT. ITEM 50 ACCEPTS THE FOURTH
QUARTER REPORT AND ITEM 51 ACCEPTS THE ANNUAL REPORT.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
52. >> ITEM 52 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO APPROVE THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT'S USE OF
EQUIPMENT POLICY 2024 ANNUAL REPORT CONSISTENT WITH THE
CRITERIA SET FORTH IN STATE LAW.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 53 ITEM 53 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF HEALTH TO SIGN A CALIFORNIA
DEPARTMENT OF STATE HOSPITALS AND CALIFORNIA MENTAL HEALTH
SERVICES AUTHORITY MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDING TO FACILITATE
ACCESS TO MENTAL HEALTH TREATMENT AND FACILITATE THE
TRANSFER OF FUNDS TO COVER SAN FRANCISCO'S OBLIGATION TO PAY
FOR MENTAL HEALTH TREATMENT AT THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF
STATE HOSPITALS FOR A ONE YEAR TERM AND NINE MONTHS THROUGH
JUNE 30TH 2025 FOR 10 MILLION. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITH
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 54.
ITEM 54 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE
PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO TO ACCEPT AN EXPENDED $200,000 PARKING
MANAGEMENT CAPITAL GRANT FROM THE METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION
COMMISSION A TRANSPORTATION PLANNING, FINANCING
AND COORDINATING AGENCY FOR THE NINE COUNTY SAN FRANCISCO BAY
AREA TO FUND THE ACQUISITION AND INSTALLATION OF MULTI SPACE
PAY STATIONS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 55.
ITEM 55 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO DESIGNATE DESIGNATE AUTHORIZED
OFFICERS THE TREASURER, COMPTROLLER AND CITY ATTORNEY
OR THEIR SUCCESSORS IN OFFICE TO ACCEPT AND WITHDRAW TOBACCO
SETTLEMENT FUNDS ON BEHALF OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO PURSUANT TO THE MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDING
DATED AUGUST 5TH, 1998 AMONG THE ATTORNEY GENERAL OF THE
STATE OF CALIFORNIA AND CITIES AND COUNTIES IN THE STATE
INCLUDING SAN FRANCISCO. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM 60. ITEM 60 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE
BUDGET AND FINANCE COMMITTEE AT A SPECIAL MEETING ON WELL THIS
MORNING TUESDAY, JULY 29TH AND WAS FORWARDED AS AMENDED
WITH THE SAME TITLE. ITEM 60 IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO CREATE A TIME LIMITED AMNESTY
PROGRAM FOR PROPERTIES LISTED ON THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTIONS INTERNAL QUALITY CONTROL AUDIT AND SUBJECT TO A
NOTICE OF VIOLATION TO A AFFIRM TO SEEK WE DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL OR
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
AND THANK YOU TO THE BUDGET COMMITTEE MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM 60 ONE YES AND I'LL FIRST STATE THAT ITEMS 61
THROUGH 65 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE AT THEIR REGULAR MEETING MONDAY, JULY 28TH.
ITEM 61 WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED BEARING A NEW TITLE
WHICH NOW READS ITEM 61 ORDINANCE AMENDING THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO AUTHORIZE TENANTS RIGHTS
ORGANIZATIONS TO ENFORCE THE PROHIBITION AGAINST LANDLORDS
USE OF ALGORITHMIC DEVICES TO SET RENTS OR MANAGE OCCUPANCY
LEVELS FOR RESIDENTIAL DWELLING UNITS LOCATED IN SAN FRANCISCO
. AND WE CAN TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 62 ITEM 62 WAS RECOMMENDED
AS AMENDED WITH THE SAME TITLE. IT'S AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
PLANNING CODE TO REQUIRE APPLICANTS TO DISCLOSE THE
PRESENCE OF ANY UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNIT AND REQUIRE THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO INVESTIGATE ANY UNAUTHORIZED
DWELLING UNIT UPON SUBMITTAL OF A DEVELOPMENT APPLICATION.
REQUIRE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO DOCUMENT WHEN A PROPERTY IS
SUBJECT TO A REGULATORY AGREEMENT SUBJECTING ANY UNITS
ON THE PROPERTY TO THE SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENTIAL RENT
STABILIZATION AND ARBITRATION ORDINANCE AND TO REQUIRE THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO INSPECT PROPERTIES PRIOR TO
RECOMMENDING APPROVAL OF ANY LOSS OF A RESIDENTIAL UNIT OR
UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNIT TO AMEND THE BUILDING CODE TO
EXPAND THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING INSPECTIONS EXPANDED
COMPLIANCE CONTROL PROGRAM TO ADDRESS FRAUD, BRIBERY
AND FAILURE TO ACCURATELY REPRESENT THE PRESENCE
AND NUMBER OF UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNITS AT PROPERTIES
SUBJECT TO A PERMIT APPLICATION TO AFFIRM THE SECOND
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDELA
AND COLLEAGUES I JUST WANTED TO TALK A LITTLE BIT ABOUT THIS
LEGISLATION WHICH PASSED OUT OF THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE UNANIMOUSLY. IT WAS INSPIRED BY MY
EXPERIENCE BOTH AS A BUILDING INSPECTION COMMISSIONER
AND PLANNING COMMISSIONER THAT WE SAW OFTEN WHERE OWNERS
APPLYING FOR PERMITS FOR RENOVATIONS IN THEIR HOMES LIE
ABOUT HAVING UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNITS THAT WERE
OCCUPIED BY TENANTS. >> AND THIS WAS AN ATTEMPT TO
CIRCUMVENT OUR RENT CONTROL LAWS BECAUSE YOU TO USE
UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNITS ARE RENT CONTROLLED.
AND WE CALLED THESE RENOVICTIONS.
AND AS YOU KNOW WITH THAT REZONING THAT IS COMING WITH SB
330 AT DEVELOPERS MAY WANT TO ADD MORE UNITS EITHER THROUGH
EXISTING EXPANSION OR DEMOLITIONS OF THEIR PROPERTY
AND WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE THAT TENANTS IN OTHER UNAUTHORIZED
WELLING UNITS ARE AFFORDED THE SAME TENANT PROTECTIONS AS
OTHER TENANTS. SO YOU KNOW THE EVICTION
PROTECTIONS IN SB 330 APPLY ONLY TO ILLEGAL UNITS.
THE TENANTS THAT LIVE IN UNITS THAT ARE UNITS NOT TO
UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNITS. AND THIS IS AN ATTEMPT TO TRY
TO BRING EVERYONE UNDER THE SAME PROTECTION.
SO I DID SIT THROUGH SEVERAL HEARINGS BOTH IN BUILDING
AND IN PLANNING OF TENANTS THAT WERE DISPLACED BECAUSE YOU
KNOW, A LANDLORD WAS GOING TO JUST RENOVATE THE PROPERTY, GET
THEM OUT FOR A LITTLE BIT WHILE RENOVATIONS WERE BEING MADE
AND THEN LO AND BEHOLD THEY JUST LOST THEIR UNITS.
SO THAT'S SOMETHING THAT NONE OF US WANT TO SUPPORT AND I
HOPE FOR I THINK MY COLLEAGUES ON THE LADIES
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE FOR SITTING THROUGH IT
AND RECOMMENDING IT AND I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
BRIAN MELGAR. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES PASSED
ON FIRST READING. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 63
. >> ITEM 63 WAS REFERRED WITHOUT
RECOMMENDATION AS AMENDED WITH A NEW TITLE WHICH NOW READS AN
ORDINANCE AMENDING THE PLANNING CODE TO ELIMINATE LIMITS ON
NONRESIDENTIAL USE SIZES IN THE PACIFIC AVENUE NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL DISTRICT AND CD POLK STREET AND CD WEST PORTAL
AVENUE IN CD NORTH BEACH AND CD AND NORTH BEACH SPECIAL USE
DISTRICT REGIONAL COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS AND RESIDENTIAL
COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS TO ALLOW SPECIFIED NONRESIDENTIAL USES
THAT EXCEED THE USE SIZE LIMITS TO DIVIDE INTO SMALLER SPACES
THAT MAY CONTINUE TO EXCEED THE USE SIZE LIMITS WITHOUT
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION TO ADJUST THE USE SIZE LIMIT
IN ALL NCDS TO AROUND NUMBER TWO AFFIRMED THE SPEAKER
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> CHAIRMAN LUGAR. THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
SO COLLEAGUES, WE HAD A ROBUST DISCUSSION ABOUT THIS AT
LEGISLATION THAT I SPONSORED AT THE LADIES AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE AND IT IS NOW IN FRONT OF YOU HAVING RECEIVED
AT NO RECOMMENDATION OR PASS OUT OF A COMMITTEE WITHOUT A
RECOMMENDATION TO YOU TODAY. AND I WANTED TO EXPLAIN A
LITTLE BIT ABOUT WHERE THIS CAME FROM.
>> SO THIS WAS A RESPONSE TO THE VASTLY AND RAPIDLY CHANGING
LANDSCAPE OF RETAIL IN OUR CITY.
>> IT'S REALLY A PHENOMENON THAT'S GOING ON ALL AROUND OUR
COUNTRY IN OUR WORLD HOW PEOPLE BUY GOODS NOW AS OPPOSED TO
THROUGH THE WAY THEY DID 30 YEARS AGO.
SO WE HAVE SEEN AROUND THE CITY THE SHUTTERING OF WALGREENS
AND CVS SAYS THERE ARE SOME FOLKS WHO WILL TALK ABOUT CRIME
AND WHILE THAT IS REAL, THE REALITY IS THAT WHEN CAREMARK
BRINGS YOU YOUR PRESCRIPTIONS TO YOUR HOUSE, THE INCENTIVE TO
GO TO WALGREENS AND ALSO BUY TOILET PAPER WHILE YOU'RE
PICKING UP A PRESCRIPTION HAS JUST BECOME LESS FREQUENT
AND THAT IS HAPPENING NOT JUST WITH PHARMACIES.
IT'S HAPPENING BECAUSE PEOPLE DON'T GO TO BANKS ANYMORE.
THEY DO THEIR BANKING ELECTRONICALLY.
SO WE HAVE HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF SQUARE FEET OF
BANKING INSTITUTIONS THAT IS EMPTY.
WE HAVE SEEN HOW BIG GROCERY STORES LIKE SAFEWAY HAVE
REORGANIZED THEIR AISLES TO MAKE IT EASIER FOR, YOU KNOW,
INSTACART DELIVERERS AND OTHERS TO COME AND PICK UP GROCERIES
AND BRING THEM TO PEOPLE HOMES. WE HAVE SEEN A SEA CHANGE
IN RETAIL BUT OUR LAND USE CONTROLS HAVE NOT REALLY
ADAPTED. >> WE ARE LAGGING BEHIND THE
INDUSTRY TRENDS SO THIS WAS A DIRECT RESPONSE TO THAT IN TRY
TO MAKE THINGS A LITTLE MORE FLEXIBLE SO THAT WE CAN KEEP
OUR COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS VIBRANT.
>> SO IN THE LEGISLATION DOES TWO MAIN THINGS ONE IT GETS RID
OF HARD CAPS AND PROHIBITIONS BEYOND A CERTAIN SIZE.
THERE ARE ONLY THREE NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL
CORRIDORS. I HAD THESE THAT WAS NORTH
BEACH CASTRO AND WEST PORTAL WEST PORTAL HAD THE MOST
STRINGENT AND IT IS A VERY SHORT DISTRICT ONLY THREE
BLOCKS LONG BUT IT HAD A SQUARE CAP FOR THOUSAND SQUARE FEET
THAT WAS AN IMPEDIMENT TWICE IN THE PAST COUPLE OF YEARS.
ONE WHEN WE OPENED ALAN NATH ONE OF THE MOST SUCCESSFUL
BUSINESSES ON WEST PORTAL BECAUSE THERE'S A 4000 SQUARE
FOOT CAP THEY HAD TO DESIGN THE SPACE AFTER THEY MERGED IT FOR
3998FT2. AND IF YOU'VE GONE TO L.A. AS
YOU KNOW THAT THERE'S A LINE OUT THE DOOR ALWAYS SO THEY
COULD USE THOSE EXTRA TWO SQUARE FEET FOR ANOTHER TABLE
AND THEN THE SAME BLOCK AT THE CORNER THERE WAS AN OPTOMETRIST
THAT ALSO MERGED TWO SPACES TO MAKE A NEW CLINIC AND I HAD TO
DO SPOT ZONING, MAKE A SPECIAL LEGISLATION JUST FOR THAT
IN THE PLANNING COMMISSION TOLD ME DON'T DO THIS HERE NOW
THAT'S NOT GOOD PLANNING. >> YOU SHOULD HAVE RULES FOR
EVERYONE. AND SO THAT'S WHERE THIS PART
OF THE LEGISLATION CAME FROM. >> IT ALSO DOES THE OPPOSITE
BIG SQUARE SPACE AND BIG BIG SQUARE FOOT SPACES LIKE WE HAVE
ON OCEAN AVENUE IN MANY OF YOU DO HAVE THESE IN YOUR DISTRICTS
THAT ARE EMPTY BECAUSE A CVS HAS LEFT THE WALGREENS HAVE
LEFT AND IT'S REALLY HARD TO RE RENT THOSE TO HAVE SOMEBODY WHO
CAN AFFORD TO PAY FOR ALL OF THAT SQUARE FOOTAGE AND TO
SUBDIVIDE IT, IT'S REALLY, REALLY DIFFICULT AT THE PROCESS
IS REALLY CUMBERSOME AND TIME CONSUMING.
SO IT'S YOU KNOW THAT THOSE SPACES TEND TO SIT EMPTY FOR A
LONG TIME. >> SO THIS LEGISLATION ALSO
DOES THE OPPOSITE IN THAT IT ALLOWS FOR SUBDIVISION OF THOSE
BIG SPACES SO THAT THE PROPERTY OWNERS CAN RENT THEM 2 TO 3 FOR
BUSINESSES. HOWEVER THE THE MARKET WILL
BEAR IN IT ALSO WILL ADVANTAGE SMALLER BUSINESSES TO BE ABLE
TO AFFORD THAT THOSE SPACES ON COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS.
>> SO THERE WAS A LOT OF QUESTIONS WE DID RECEIVE
PUSHBACK FROM FOLKS IN NORTH BEACH.
I DID CONSULT WITH DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR SAUDER WHO
AGREED WITH THE LEGISLATION IS ACTUALLY ONE OF THE CO-SPONSORS
AND PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AGREED TO PART OF THE LEGISLATION BUT
NOT ALL OF IT FOR THE CASTRO WHICH IS WHERE WE GOT TO TODAY.
BUT I DO THINK COLLEAGUES THAT IN LOOKING FORWARD TO WHAT'S
HAPPENING AROUND OUR CITY AND THE CHANGES IN RETAIL WE
SHOULD LOOK AT OUR CONTROLS AND WE SHOULD LOOK AT WHAT OUR
CHALLENGES ARE TODAY AND THE CHALLENGES THAT ARE COMING
TOMORROW BECAUSE WE SEE THEY'RE COMING AND NOT RESPOND TO THE
CHALLENGES OF 30 YEARS AGO BECAUSE IT IS NO LONGER
APPROPRIATE AND IT DOESN'T HELP US.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
CHAIR MELGAR SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT MADAM AND I
WANT TO THANK FIRST SUPERVISOR MALAGA FOR HER LEADERSHIP
AND IN EVALUATING THIS AND I CAN CONCUR AND UNDERSTAND YOU
THIS IS A PROBLEM SOLVING FOR HER DISTRICT IN TERMS OF
WESTPORT ALL WHAT I HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT THIS PIECE OF
LEGISLATION COLLEAGUES IS THAT IN THE CONTEXT OF UPCOMING
ZONING PLAN BUT ALSO THE LEGISLATION THAT WERE
PREVIOUSLY APPROVED LAYERING SUCH AS FLEXIBLE USE FOR FOR
OUR NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICT AS WELL AS THE MOST
RECENT OF PRIORITIZATION OF FORMULARY TILE WITH 20
STOREFRONTS AND LESS AND IT IS NOT SO MUCH OF THAT I AM
IN OPPOSITION OF THIS PARTICULAR LEGISLATION BUT IS
MUCH MORE SO IN THE CONTEXT OF NOT JUST THE UP ZONING BUT
OVERALL LAYERING OF DIFFERENT LEGISLATION AND HOW THAT
ACTUALLY NOT JUST IMPACTING NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL
CORRIDOR OR NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS IN IN
IN THE RICHMOND BUT CLEARLY ALSO IN OTHER REALLY CITY Y
AND I KNOW THAT WE'RE UNIQUE WE HAVE 47 DIFFERENT NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL DISTRICT AND SOME OF THEM HAVE DIFFERENT KINDS OF
RESTRICTION AND PARTICULARLY IN THE RICHMOND WE HAVE FOUR
JUST GARY ALONE WE HAVE RESTRICTION ON FORMULA RETAIL
AND FOOD AND FORMULA RETAIL ON PET STORE SPECIFICALLY BECAUSE
OF THAT I MUST SAY THAT I HAVE QUESTIONS AND CONCERNS AND JUST
WANTED TO SEEK A MORE BETTER UNDERSTANDING AND IN DEPTH
ANALYSIS THAT WHEN WE DO THIS IN THE EVENT THAT FOR A LARGER
LOTS CAN DO DO A DIVISION WITHOUT A CONDITIONAL USE
LAYERING WITH THE FLEXIBLE USE WITHOUT ADDITIONAL CONDITIONAL
USE HOW WOULD THAT ACTUALLY WORK FOR US AND WHAT DOES THAT
MEAN? I GOT A CLARIFICATION YESTERDAY
ON LAND USE AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR JOINING ME YESTERDAY
AND FOR ALLOWING ME TO JOIN YESTERDAY AT LAND USE COMMITTEE
THAT I CAN ASK QUESTIONS ABOUT PARCEL DELIVERY FACILITY
PARTICULARLY A CLARIFICATION THAT YOU KNOW FOR THE RICHMOND
IS NOT APPLICABLE FOR PARCEL DELIVERY SERVICE BUT ACTUALLY
IS NOT CLEAR WHETHER THE REMAINING OF OTHER NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL DISTRICT PARCEL DELIVERY SERVICE IS TECHNICALLY
BANNED IN THIS CASE WHICH WE KNOW IS HAS ACTUALLY HAS A
WAIVER FOR 5000 SQUARE FOOTAGE AND LESS ALL WHICH IS TO SAY
COLLEAGUES I I'M PUTTING OUT THERE AND AND AGAIN I CAN
UNDERSTAND THAT THERE IS A FEELING THAT YOU KNOW, WE
SHOULD MOVE FORWARD WITH THIS PIECE OF LEGISLATION TODAY
SINCE THERE'S A DUPLICATE UP FILE SEEMS LIKE IT'S A WAITING
FOR FURTHER AMENDMENT. I'M GOING TO PUT IT OUT THERE
THAT I WANT TO ASK COLLEAGUES TO THINK ABOUT WHETHER THERE'S
A POSSIBILITY TO EITHER FOR CONTINUANCE OF THIS PIECE OF
LEGISLATION TODAY OR SEND IT BACK TO COMMITTEE FOR FURTHER
COMMUNICATIONS AND YOU KNOW, CONVERSATIONS THAT WE CAN HAVE
WITH OUR CONSTITUENTS AND PARTICULARLY FOR ME, YOU
KNOW, NOT JUST I WANT TO SAY NOT JUST THAT BUSINESS LOCATED
IN THE RICHMOND NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICT BUT ALSO
FRANKLY CHINESE SPEAKING AND MONOLINGUAL MERCHANTS FOR
THEM TO ACTUALLY UNDERSTAND THIS PIECE OF LEGISLATION.
I HAVE QUESTIONS I WOULD IMAGINE SO WHAT MY CONSTITUENTS
NOT JUST IN D ONE BUT THROUGHOUT THE CITY THAT ARE
PARTICULARLY CHINESE SPEAKING. >> SO I AM GOING TO THROW IT
OUT THERE THAT I WILL HAVE THEM I AM PUTTING A MOTION OUT THERE
FOR A CONTINUANCE AS I KNOW I WILL REQUIRE A SECOND SECOND
BITE AND SO I'M GOING TO LAY IT OUT THERE AND AND FOR YOUR
CONSIDERATION AND BUT AGAIN, I WANT TO I DO WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR MAL GA FOR ALWAYS TRYING TO PROBLEM SOLVE FOR HER
DISTRICT AND BUT I UNDERSTAND YOU KNOW IF THERE'S A
CONSIDERATION AND COURTESY FOR PRESENT MADAM IN CARVING OUT
CONTRADICTORY AND REST OF THIS ACTUALLY IMPACT MANY YOU KNOW
ALL ACTUALLY NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICT CITYWIDE
I'M I YOU KNOW AND THIS WHAT CAME OUT AS COMMITTEE REPORT
I'M ASKING JUST FOR MORE MORE TIME I'M NOT SAYING THAT I'M
VOTING OPPOSITION I DON'T WANT TO BE IN VOTING OPPOSITION
TODAY BUT IF I MUST I PROBABLY WILL FOR TODAY.
SUPERVISOR CHAN JUST TO CLARIFY THE MOTION YOUR YOU HAVE MOVED
TO CONTINUE THIS TO THE NEXT MEETING THE NEXT MEETING
SEPTEMBER 2ND SEPTEMBER 2ND AND THAT HAS BEEN SECONDED BY
SUPERVISOR CHAN SUPERVISOR SLAUGHTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR YOUR WORK
ON THIS. >> I'VE HEARD CONCERNS ABOUT
THIS FROM SOME COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND I WANT TO KIND OF
ADDRESS THOSE BECAUSE I, I THINK THEY'RE COMING FROM A
GOOD PLACE AND AND THEY'RE VALID CONCERNS AT FIRST.
YOU KNOW, THE CONCERNS ARE SPEAK SOMEWHAT TO WHAT YOU WERE
SHARING SUPERVISOR CHAN ON ON THE LAYERING OF THE DIFFERENT
PIECES I THINK ALSO JUST THE KIND OF THE WORST CASE SCENARIO
IN SOME FOLKS MINDS OF OF STOREFRONTS BEING MERGED AT
WILL AND LARGE SPACES OPENING AND I TAKE ANY OF THOSE
CONCERNS SERIOUSLY FOR ME I THINK ACTUALLY THIS LEGISLATION
PUTS IN MORE GUARDRAILS THAN BEFORE AND IT DOES IT IN A MORE
TRANSPARENT MANNER. SPECIFICALLY THIS RETAINS THE
CONDITIONAL USE ABOVE 4000FT2. >> SO THAT IS A PROCESS THAT IS
RETAINED IN ON THE STOREFRONT MERGER SIDE, STOREFRONT MERGERS
ARE CURRENTLY NOT ALLOWED AND A LOT OF THE NCDS THAT I
REPRESENT AND WE HAVE PENDING LEGISLATION TO ALLOW MORE
FLEXIBILITY TO CHANGE THAT TO A CONDITIONAL USE AND IF WE ARE
SUCCESSFUL THERE STILL WILL BE A CONDITIONAL USE PROCESS.
SO TO ME IT IS TAKING THIS ACTION AND PUTTING IT TO A MORE
IN FRONT OF A MORE OBJECTIVE SET OF STANDARDS IN A MORE
TRANSPARENT MANNER. OTHERWISE WE'RE HAVING TO DO AS
SUPERVISOR MELGAR EXPLAINED. WE'RE HAVING TO DO SPOT
LEGISLATION AND THE QUESTION IS CAN THE GENERAL PUBLIC FOLLOW
THAT LEGISLATIVE PROCESS WHICH IS DONE AT THE WILL AND THE
SUBJECTIVE WILL OF AN INDIVIDUAL SUPERVISOR OR DO
THEY FOLLOW A PLANNING PROCESS BETTER?
NEITHER ARE EASY TO FOLLOW BUT THE PLANNING PROCESS DOES COME
WITH A NOTICE REQUIREMENT AND SO IF YOU'RE INTERESTED
IN COMMUNITY INPUT AND DOING THINGS TRANSPARENTLY I THINK
THERE'S ACTUALLY A CASE TO BE SAID THAT THIS DOES IT IN A
MORE TRANSPARENT MANNER. I ALSO REALLY APPRECIATE THE
THE PIECE OF THIS LEGISLATION AND I THINK THE PROBABLY THE
PIECE THAT WILL BE MOST IMPACTFUL OVER TIME IS THE
SUBDIVIDING OF SMALLER SPACES. I THINK THAT IS A SIGNIFICANT
ISSUE THAT THERE'S NOT ENOUGH ATTENTION ON CITYWIDE OF THESE
MASSIVE LARGE SPACES WHICH ARE JUST NOT IN DEMAND FOR RETAIL
ANYMORE AND SOMETHING LIKE THIS MAKING IT EASIER TO SUBDIVIDE I
THINK ACTUALLY GOES ADVANCES THE GOAL THAT MANY OF US SHARE
OF THIS SMALL NEIGHBORHOOD SERVING RETAIL IT ALSO ADVANCES
THE GOAL THAT MANY OF US SHARE OF OF MORE AFFORDABLE RENTS
WHICH ARE MORE ATTAINABLE WITH SMALLER SPACES.
SO ON THE BALANCE I THINK IT IS A GOOD PIECE OF LEGISLATION.
I ALSO YOU KNOW RECOGNIZING THOSE CONCERNS I NOTICE IT HAS
BEEN DUPLICATED AND I THINK THERE'S YOU KNOW THAT WOULD BE
AN AVENUE TO DO FURTHER WORK. I WILL NOT SUPPORT A WELL LET
ME PUT IT THIS WAY I'LL I'LL I'LL LOOK TO HEAR FROM
SUPERVISOR MELGAR ON THE ISSUE OF CONTINUANCE.
>> THANKS. SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU
PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN I JUST WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR
REALLY, REALLY LEANING INTO THIS HARD BEING INCREDIBLY
THOUGHTFUL AT THE END OF THE DAY THIS IS ABOUT MAKING IT
EASIER FOR SMALL BUSINESSES TO FILL SPACES THAT LARGE CHAIN
STORES CAN NO LONGER FILL BECAUSE OF RETAIL TRENDS THAT
ARE TOTALLY OUTSIDE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
HE SPOKE ABOUT IT VERY, VERY WELL AND I THINK SUPERVISOR
SAUTER TOUCHED ON IT AS WELL GIVING LANDLORDS THE ABILITY TO
SUBDIVIDE SPACES INTO SIGNIFICANTLY SMALLER SPACES
OFFERS NEW OPPORTUNITIES FOR SAN FRANCISCO CREATIVE
ENTREPRENEURS FOR FOR PEOPLE WITHOUT CORPORATE BACKING, FOR
IMMIGRANTS, FOR FOR YOUNG PEOPLE TO START BUSINESSES HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND FILL PERSISTENTLY VACANT SPACES.
THIS IS ABOUT CREATING OPPORTUNITY BY MAKING
UNFILMABLE LARGE SPACES INTO FILLABLE SMALL SPACES
SUPERVISOR MCGRATH THANK YOU FOR WEIGHING IN ON THIS SO
HEAVILY AND SO SPECIFICALLY. CHAIR MILLER ANY OBJECTION TO
LETTING SUPERVISOR WALTON GO FIRST?
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU PRESIDENT MADAM AND I
GUESS MY QUESTION IS TO THE CHAIR AS WHY DOES THIS HAVE TO
HAPPEN RIGHT NOW? LIKE IF IF THERE ARE CONCERNS
IN COMMUNITIES, WHY CAN'T THERE BE AT LEAST MORE CONVERSATION
BEFORE HAVING TO VOTE ON THIS TODAY?
>> CHAIR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDEL MAN I THINK
THIS IS ACTUALLY REALLY SMALL. WE DO HAVE YOU KNOW THESE
ISSUES WITH A LARGE SPACES THAT YOU KNOW NOW WILL HAVE AN
EASIER WAY TO SUBDIVIDE CHEAPER, CHEAPER AND EASIER
AND THAT IS SOMETHING THAT AFFECTS ALL OF US.
I HAVE NOT GOTTEN ANY OPPOSITION FROM ANYONE ABOUT
THAT A PART OF THE LEGISLATION IN FACT, YOU KNOW THE MERCHANTS
ON YOU KNOW, THE COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS ARE AFFECTED BY THE
OTHER PART OF THE LEGISLATURE ACTUALLY QUITE THIS LIKE THIS
QUITE A BIT AND I THINK THAT IT'S RELIEF FOR A LOT OF FOLKS
. I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, I WANT
TO ADDRESS SOME OF THE ISSUES THAT HAVE COME UP BECAUSE I
DON'T THINK THERE ARE ISSUES AND LIKE I SAID, I THINK THIS
IS REALLY SMALL IN WE SHOULD BE ABLE TO MOVE IT FORWARD TODAY I
DID DUPLICATE THE FILE IN CASE THERE ARE, YOU KNOW, ISSUES
THAT PEOPLE STILL WANT TO TINKER AROUND OR SOMEONE ELSE
WANTS YOU KNOW, TO GO FURTHER AT THE LEGISLATIONS ALREADY
WRITTEN AND WE CAN AMEND IT BUT I, I DON'T SEE A NEED TO DELAY
IT. LET ME JUST SAY THERE ARE NO
NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS WHERE DELIVERY PARCEL
DELIVERY IS PERMITTED. THERE ARE THREE WAYS YOU KNOW
THAT WE DEAL WITH IT. IT'S EITHER, YOU KNOW, PROHIBIT
IT OR IT IS PERMITTED OR YOU KNOW, PERMITTED WITH A
CONDITIONAL USE AND IN NO NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL
CORRIDOR IS PARCEL DELIVERY AT THE 5000FT2 OR LESS PERMITTED.
SO YOU KNOW, I DON'T THINK THAT'S AN ISSUE FOR ANY OF YOU
WHO HAVE NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS IN YOUR
DISTRICT BECAUSE IT IS LITERALLY PROHIBITED IN THIS
LEGISLATION DOES NOT CHANGE THAT.
I THINK THAT FOR THAT CONTROVERSIAL PART OF THIS
LEGISLATION WHICH IS THE USE SIZE CAP, THERE ARE ONLY THREE
COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS THAT ARE AFFECTED AND I HAVE SPOKEN TO
ALL THE SUPERVISORS THERE AND WE HAVE WORKED IT OUT IN A
WAY THAT IS SATISFACTORY TO THOSE SUPERVISORS.
SO I JUST DON'T SEE THE NEED FOR THE DELAY.
LIKE I SAID, I THINK THIS IS QUITE SMALL AND IT WILL BRING
RELIEF TO NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS THAT HAVE
THESE LARGE PIECES THAT HAVE BEEN VACANT.
>> THANK YOU. >> SUPER SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK
YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN COLLEAGUES I THINK WHEN THIS
ITEM CAME BEFORE THE LAND USE COMMITTEE I EXPRESSED THEIR
GRAVE CONCERN REGARDING THIS LEGISLATION.
ONE IS THE PORTION OF THE LEGISLATION THAT REMOVES THE
USE SIZE CAPS IN SOME NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL
DISTRICT MAY SEEM LIKE A MODEST CHANGE BUT THIS CONTROLS WERE
PUT IN PLACE IN ORDER TO PROTECT SMALL BUSINESS FROM
BEING SQUEEZED OUT BY LARGEST BUSINESS WITH MORE RESOURCES
MUCH IN GROUPS. >> MULTIPLE MERCHANT GROUPS
CAME TO ME AND EXPRESSED THEIR STRONG OPPOSITION TO
ELIMINATION OF THE EXISTING LIMITS BECAUSE THEY UNDERSTAND
THAT REMOVING THE CAPS COULD UNDERMINE THE VITALITY OF
NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICT.
THIS WILL ALSO OPEN DOOR FOR BIGGER AND WHILE RESOURCES TO
RETAIL TENANTS TO EXPAND THEIR FOOTPRINT AND PLACE UPWARD
PRESSURE ON RENTS I ALSO BELIEVE THAT THERE IS ANOTHER
MORE UNKNOWN FACTOR WHICH IS WILL COME TO US VERY SOON.
>> IT'S WITH THE MAYOR'S REZONING OF THE CITY COMMERCIAL
CORRIDOR COMING FORWARD THERE WILL BE UNDOUBTEDLY BE
DEMOLITION OF BUILDINGS WITH MULTIPLE SMALL BUILDINGS
AND THIS LEGISLATION CAN ALSO OPEN DOOR TO NEW DEVELOPMENT
THAT COULD INCLUDE LARGER STOREFRONT FOOTPRINT THAT WILL
BE AN AFFORDABLE TO SMALL BUSINESS.
>> SO WITH THE LEGISLATION AS OF TODAY I AM NOT READY TO
SUPPORT BUT IN COMMITTEE I DID DUPLICATE A FILE AND I DO HOPE
THAT WE CAN HAVE MORE TIME AND LOOK INTO IT SO WE CAN
ADDRESS SOME OF THOSE MERCHANTS CONCERN.
THANK YOU. UH, SUPERVISOR CHEN JUST WANTED
TO BRIEFLY MENTION THAT YOU KNOW IT'S WE JUST RECEIVED IT
THIS AFTERNOON AND I JUST WANT TO MAKE MENTION THAT, YOU KNOW,
AN ORGANIZATION, A CITY WIDE ORGANIZATION KNOWN AS SMALL
BUSINESS FOUR HAS ARTICULATED AGAIN NOT IN OPPOSITION TO THE
LEGISLATION BUT ALSO JUST SIMPLY ASKING FOR A
CONTINUANCE. SO THAT DIFFERENT MERCHANT
GROUPS CITYWIDE CAN HAVE A BETTER UNDERSTANDING ABOUT THE
IMPACT ON NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS.
I THINK THAT AGAIN THE PERSPECTIVE ABOUT WHETHER IT'S
A MINOR CHANGE OR NOT I THINK IT'S THE PROSPECT OF ABOUT
UNDERSTANDING THE IMPACT AND HOW IT ACTUALLY LAYERS
AND I CONCUR WITH SUPERVISOR CHEN'S SENTIMENT ABOUT THIS IS
REALLY ALSO IN THE CONTEXT OF THE UPCOMING UP ZONING PLAN
PROPOSED BY THE MAYOR AND HELP US ACTUALLY ALL UNDERSTAND HOW
THIS ACTUALLY WOULD WORK OUT FOR PARTICULARLY FOR THE
NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICT.
>> THANK YOU, CHAIRMAN. ALOHA.
I WILL JUST MAKE ONE LAST POINT AND LET THIS ONE GO.
SO YOU KNOW FOR NEW CONSTRUCTION THE EXISTING
CONTROLS STILL APPLY. SO IF IT'S A SPACE THAT'S
LARGER THAN 4000, 5000 SQUARE FOOT WHEREVER THAT IS, YOU
STILL NEED TO GO THROUGH A CONDITIONAL USE.
THERE ARE SOME AREAS WHERE THINGS ARE STREAMLINED.
THAT IS THE CASE AND IT IS A VERY SMALL SCENARIO NOT
NECESSARILY CONNECTED TO THE OBSERVING BUT I WILL ALSO SAY,
YOU KNOW IN THE EXPERIENCES THAT I HAD WITH A CAP ON WEST
PORTAL IT IN ALSO IT HAPPENED WITH THE FORMER SUPERVISOR
DISTRICT THREE WITH BOB'S DONUTS WHEN THE SPOT ZONING
HAPPENED IS BECAUSE YOU HAVE THAT ACCESS TO YOUR SUPERVISOR
WHO CAN WRITE LEGISLATION JUST FOR YOUR BUSINESS AND YOU CAN
PAY YOU KNOW BRANT GLADSTONE OR WHOEVER LAND USE LAWYER $700 AN
HOUR OR PAY AN EXPEDITER TO DO THIS FOR YOU.
IT IS NOT THE SMALL IMMIGRANT BUSINESSES THAT ARE BENEFITING
FROM OUR CURRENT REALLY RESTRICTIVE CONTROLS.
IT IS THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE ACCESS WHO HAVE MONEY TO PAY
THE LAND USE LAWYERS AND I THINK THAT WE ARE DOING A
DISSERVICE TO A SMALL IMMIGRANT NON-ENGLISH SPEAKING PEOPLE BY
HAVING THESE RESTRICTIONS THAT ONLY ALLOW ACCESS FOR SOME
AND NOT OTHERS. AND SO I JUST WANTED TO SAY
THAT THANK YOU. >> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, ON
THE MOTION TO CONTINUE THE ITEM MADE BY SUPERVISOR CHAN
AND SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHAN PLEASE CALL THE ROLL AN ITEM ON
THE MOTION TO CONTINUE ITEM 63 TO SEPTEMBER 2ND SUPERVISOR
RICARDO AND GAUDIO NO SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD NO. SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN NO MANDEL
MAN NO SUPERVISOR MILKER MELGAR NO SUPERVISOR SUTTER SUTTER NO
SUPERVISORS CHERYL CHERYL NO SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NO THERE ARE FOUR EYES AND SEVEN
NOS WITH SUPERVISORS AND GAUDIO MAHMOOD MANDEL MEN MELGAR
SORTER CHERYL AND DORSEY VOTING NO.
>> ALL RIGHT SO THE MOTION DOES NOT PASS.
IS THAT A GAVEL OF EVENT? WHY NOT SAYS THE CITY ATTORNEY.
>> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON ITEM 63 AND ITEM 63 SUPERVISOR RANK AUDIO AND VIDEO
I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
EYES SUPERVISOR MANDEL HIGH MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON HIGH WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE NO NOISE AND TO NOSE
WITH SUPERVISORS CHIN AND CHIN VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 64 ITEM
64 WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED WITH THE SAME TITLE.
IT'S AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUILDING CODE TO REQUIRE
BUILDINGS UNDERGOING MAJOR RENOVATIONS TO MEAN TO REMAIN
OR CONVERT TO ALL ELECTRIC BUILDINGS WITH EXEMPTIONS
EXCEPTIONS FOR PHYSICAL AND TECHNICAL AND FEASIBILITY
COMMERCIAL FOOD ESTABLISHMENTS NONRESIDENTIAL TO RESIDENTIAL
CONVERSIONS BUILDINGS WITH RECENT MAJOR SYSTEMS
REPLACEMENTS AND 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING TO AFFIRM
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEM 64 SUPERVISOR RANK AUDIO AND ENGARDIO EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMUD AHMAD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 65 ITEM
65 WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT.
>> IT'S A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE PLACEMENT OF
COMMEMORATIVE SIDEWALK PLAQUES AT VARIOUS LOCATIONS WITHIN
AND AROUND THE NORTH BEACH NEIGHBORHOOD AS PART OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO LITTLE ITALY HONOR WALK TO CELEBRATE PROMINENT
FIGURES IN THE ITALIAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
>> COLLEAGUES, I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 66.
YES AND I'LL FIRST STATE THAT ITEM 66 THROUGH 69 WERE
CONSIDERED BY THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING
ON MONDAY JULY 28TH. ITEM 66 WAS RECOMMENDED AS
AMENDED WITH THE SAME TITLE IT READS ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO REVISE THE GOALS AND REPORTING
REQUIREMENTS FOR FOOD PURCHASING BY THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH AND THE SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT FOR CITY HOSPITALS
AND JAILS AND TO ELIMINATE THE SUNSET DATE SUCH THAT THE
PROGRAM STANDARDS AND REPORTING REQUIREMENTS WILL REMAIN
IN EFFECT INDEFINITELY. >> CHAIR WALTON I WAS JUST
KIDDING. THANK YOU SO MUCH, PRESIDENT
MADAM IN. COLLEAGUES YESTERDAY ON RULES
COMMITTEE WE AMENDED AND DUPLICATED THE FAILED TO
REMOVE A PROVISION REQUIRING THE.
TO SOURCE 5% OF FOOD FROM MEDIUM AND SMALL FARMS BY
JANUARY 2027 AND INCREASE SOURCING TO 10 TO 15% BY
JANUARY 2028. >> THIS CHANGE WILL ALLOW DPS
TO EVALUATE AND ANALYZE THE UPDATED GOALS OVER THE AUGUST
RECESS. THESE SOURCING TARGETS WERE
ORIGINALLY ESTABLISHED BY H AND COORDINATION WITH THE
CENTER FOR GOOD FOOD PURCHASING IN 2000 1920 WHICH IS WHY THEY
WERE INCLUDED IN THIS LEGISLATION INITIALLY.
>> THIS POLICY WAS REINTRODUCED BECAUSE THE CURRENT POLICY IS
SET TO EXPIRE IN SEPTEMBER AND THIS IS AN OPPORTUNITY TO
STRENGTHEN OUR GOALS AROUND SUSTAINABILITY, HEALTH, LABOR
PRACTICES AND LOCAL FOOD SOURCING BY ENSURING THAT SAN
FRANCISCO'S PUBLIC DOLLARS SUPPORT ETHICAL FOOD SYSTEMS
THAT UPLIFT WORKERS AND COMMUNITIES.
AFTER FURTHER DISCUSSIONS WITH MY COLLEAGUES WHO SUPPORT THE
POLICY BUT REQUESTED A SUNSET DATE, WE'VE REACHED AN
AGREEMENT TO INCLUDE A TEN YEAR SUNSET FOR 2035.
WITH THAT I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO AMEND THE FOLLOWING
ON PAGE ONE LINE FIVE OF THE LONG TITLE REMOVE THE WORD
ELIMINATED AND REPLACE IT WITH REVISING ON LINE 6 TO 7.
REMOVE INDEFINITELY AND REPLACE IT WITH UNTIL DECEMBER 31ST
2035. AND ON PAGE 11 LINES TWO
THROUGH FOUR ADD A PROVISION TO SUNSET SECTIONS 21.3 21 D POINT
421 D POINT FIVE ON DECEMBER 31ST 2035 AND I HAVE ALSO
PASSED THESE AROUND TO EVERYONE AND I WILL SECOND THAT MOTION
AND OFFER MY THANKS TO THE CHAIR WALTON FOR HIS
WILLINGNESS TO MAKE THAT CHANGE AS FOLKS MAY BE AWARE.
MY OPEN FOR BUSINESS CONTRACT STREAMLINING ACT OF 2025
ENDEAVORS TO ESTABLISH TIME LIMITS FOR SOME OF OUR SOCIAL
POLICIES. I THINK IT'S GENERALLY GOOD
PRACTICE FOR US TO HAVE TIME LIMITS ON OUR PROCUREMENT
REQUIREMENTS. AND SO I WANT TO THANK THANK
THE CHAIR FOR BEING WILLING TO ACCOMMODATE THAT REQUEST
IN THIS PARTICULAR PIECE OF LEGISLATION.
>> I THINK I HOPE WE CAN TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION.
ALL RIGHT. >> SO THE MOTION PASSES.
AND THEN MADAM CLERK. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDED
ITEM. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE ORDINANCES PASSED ON FOR THE
AMENDED ORDINANCES PASSED ON FIRST READING.
>> AND THEN MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU LET'S SEE ITEM 67 WAS NOT
FORWARDED TO THE BOARD. SO CAN YOU CALL ITEM 68?
>> ITEM 68. THIS ITEM WAS AMENDED TO ADD
THE NAME OF THE APPOINTEE. SO IT NOW READS MOTION TO
APPOINT KELLY YUN TO THE CITIZEN'S COMMITTEE ON
COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TERM ENDING FEBRUARY 23RD, 2026.
>> LET'S TAKE THAT SAME HOUSE SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 69.
>> ITEM 69 THIS MOTION THE AMENDMENT WAS TO STRIKE THE
WORD REJECTING AND IT NOW READS MOTION TO APPROVE THE MAYOR'S
NOMINATION OF ELEANOR COX FOR APPOINTMENT TO THE HISTORIC
PRESERVATION COMMISSION. TERM ENDING DECEMBER 31ST,
2028. >> AND LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION
IS APPROVED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
A ROLL CALL FIRST MEMBER OF TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS IS
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO. THANK YOU COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
REQUESTING A HEARING TO EVALUATE THE EFFECTIVENESS OF
THE CITY'S PROGRAMS AND TAX INCENTIVES INTENDED TO
REVITALIZE OUR BEAUTIFUL COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS.
THIS HEARING WILL FOCUS ON THREE KEY INITIATIVES THE
DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING INSPECTIONS VACANT OR ABANDONED
COMMERCIAL STOREFRONT REGISTRY THE TREASURER AND TAX
COLLECTORS COMMERCIAL VACANCY TAX AND THE SAN FRANCISCO
PUBLIC WORKS GRAFFITI ABATEMENT OPTION PROGRAM.
AT FIRST GLANCE THESE PROGRAMS MAY SEEM DISTINCT BUT TOGETHER
THEY REFLECT THE CITY'S BROADER STRATEGY TO PREVENT COMMERCIAL
PROPERTY BLIGHT DISCOURAGE COMMERCIAL STOREFRONT VACANCIES
AND SUPPORT THE LONG TERM HEALTH OF OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS. VACANT AND POORLY MAINTAINED
STOREFRONTS DO MORE THAN AFFECT THE LOOK AND FEEL OF A
CORRIDOR. THEY UNDERMINE COMMUNITY
CONFIDENCE, DETER FOOT TRAFFIC AND DISCOURAGE SMALL BUSINESS
INVESTMENT. IN RECENT YEARS SAN FRANCISCO
HAS TAKEN MEANINGFUL STEPS TO ADDRESS THESE CHALLENGES
THROUGH TARGETED POLICIES. EACH WAS DESIGNED TO REDUCE
LONG TERM VACANCIES, IMPROVE THE CONDITION AND APPEARANCE OF
COMMERCIAL PROPERTIES AND MAINTAIN THE VIBRANCY OF
OUR SHARED PUBLIC SPACES. HOWEVER, IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE
THAT TWO OF THESE PROGRAMS THE VACANT OR ABANDONED COMMERCIAL
STOREFRONT REGISTRY AND THE COMMERCIAL VACANCY TAX WERE
ADOPTED BEFORE THE ONSET OF THE COVID 19 PANDEMIC WHICH
PROFOUNDLY RESHAPED OUR CITY'S ECONOMIC LANDSCAPE.
A MARCH 3RD 2020 JUST TWO WEEKS BEFORE COVID 19 LOCKDOWNS WENT
INTO EFFECT, SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS PASSED THE COMMERCIAL
VACANCY TAX AND IN FALL 2023 THIS BOARD SUSPENDED
IMPLEMENTATION OF THE VACANT OR ABANDONED COMMERCIAL STOREFRONT
REGISTRY FOR AN ENTIRE YEAR. >> BUT TODAY SAN FRANCISCO HAS
TWO OVERLAPPING COMMERCIAL VACANCY PROGRAMS EACH
ADMINISTERED BY TWO SEPARATE DEPARTMENTS.
THIS RAISES IMPORTANT QUESTIONS.
ARE THESE PROGRAMS EFFECTIVELY REDUCING LONG TERM VACANCIES?
ARE THEY HELPING TO PREVENT COMMERCIAL BLIGHT IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS? AND JUST AS CRITICALLY, WHO ARE
THESE PROGRAMS REALLY SERVING? ARE WE UNINTENTIONALLY PLACING
AN UNDUE BURDEN ON SMALL MOM AND POP PROPERTY OWNERS
NAVIGATING SHORT TERM VACANCIES?
CONVERSELY, ARE WE ALLOWING LONG TERM ABSENTEE LANDLORDS TO
AVOID RESPONSIBILITY WHILE THE CITY ABSORBS THE COSTS OF
MAINTAINING THE EXTERNAL APPEARANCE OF THEIR BLIGHTED
PROPERTIES? THESE ARE THE QUESTIONS WE MUST
ANSWER IF WE'RE SERIOUS ABOUT RESTORING THE VITALITY OF OUR
COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS AND MAKING SURE CITY POLICY REFLECTS BOTH
FAIRNESS AND IMPACT. >> AND COLLEAGUES, I'M ALSO
MAKING A FORMAL LEGISLATIVE DRAFTING REQUEST OF THE CITY
ATTORNEY TO HELP STREAMLINE AND CONSOLIDATE PERMIT FEES
LISTED IN SAN FRANCISCO'S BUSINESS TAX AND REGULATIONS
CODE. >> I KNOW ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
CLEANUP IS NOT THE MOST EXCITING TOPIC BUT IT IS
EXACTLY THIS SORT OF STREAMLINING CODE
SIMPLIFICATION AND CLEANUP OF ANTIQUATED PERMIT REQUIREMENTS
THAT HELPS DEMYSTIFY LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND HELPS MAKE OUR
CITY CHARTER EASIER TO ADMINISTER AND UNDERSTAND.
AND IT ALLOWS MORE CITIZENS AND MERCHANTS TO UNDERSTAND THE
COSTS AND COMPLEXITY ASSOCIATED WITH DOING BUSINESS IN SAN
FRANCISCO. OUR BUSINESS TAX
AND REGULATIONS CODE COVERS ALL KINDS OF OBSCURE THINGS FROM
BALLOON ADVERTISING LICENSE REQUIREMENTS FOR VENDING
MACHINES TO BIRD EXHIBITIONS AND BOWLING ALLEYS.
IT GOES INTO GREAT DETAIL TO SPECIFY THE FEES AND PERMIT
REQUIREMENTS THE CITY IS SUPPOSED TO IMPOSE AND COLLECT
ON TARGETED INDUSTRIES. SOME SECTIONS IN OUR BUSINESS
TAX AND REGULATIONS CODE HAVE BEEN ON THE BOOKS FOR NEARLY A
CENTURY. BUT MANY OF THESE INDUSTRIES NO
LONGER OPERATE IN THE CITY AND TODAY SOME AREN'T EVEN
LEGAL TO OPERATE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
MY STAFF HAS IDENTIFIED NEARLY 100 OBSCURE FEES AND CHARGES
THAT CITY DEPARTMENTS ARE MEANT TO COLLECT FROM BUSINESSES.
BUT AN OVERWHELMING MAJORITY OF THESE FEE CATEGORIES ARE NOT
FOUND IN DEPARTMENT BUDGET SUBMISSIONS.
MORE THAN SEVERAL LINE ITEM FEE CATEGORIES ARE ISSUED TO FEWER
THAN FIVE BUSINESSES EACH YEAR. A FEW DOZEN LINE ITEM FEE
CATEGORIES ARE ISSUED TO LESS THAN 20 BUSINESSES ANNUALLY.
>> ON AVERAGE EACH FEE WE REVIEWED GENERATES LESS THAN
$15,000 FOR DEPARTMENTS EACH YEAR AND NO FEE THAT WE REVIEW
GENERATES MORE THAN 100,000 IN ANNUAL REVENUE.
THAT IS WHY I'M ASKING THE CITY'S ATTORNEYS CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE WITH SUPPORT FROM THE COMPTROLLER TO HELP
IDENTIFY ADDITIONAL OBSCURE PERMITS CODIFIED IN OUR
BUSINESS, TECH AND TAX AND REGULATIONS CODE THAT
GENERATE LESS THAN $100,000 IN REVENUE FOR CITY
DEPARTMENTS. I BELIEVE IT'S POSSIBLE TO
SIMPLIFY THE CITY'S CODE AND BRING IT INTO THE 21ST
CENTURY. THERE ARE AMPLE OPPORTUNITIES
TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO'S PERMITS AND FEES EASIER TO COLLECT
AND ADMINISTER. >> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES AND THE
REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR AND GUARDIAN SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, I HAVE TWO
RESOLUTIONS FOR INTRODUCTIONS TODAY.
FIRST OFF I WANT TO ADDRESS AN URGENT MATTER.
>> PRESIDENT TRUMP IS ONCE AGAIN ATTACKING OUR SAN
FRANCISCO VALUES AND OUR MOST VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES.
JUST LAST WEEK HE SIGNED AN EXECUTIVE ORDER PURPORTING TO
CRIMINALIZE MENTAL ILLNESS AND POVERTY WHILE DEFUNDING
EVIDENCE BASED SOLUTIONS THAT ACTUALLY WORK.
>> THE CITY HAS STOOD UP AGAINST THE TRUMP
ADMINISTRATION'S CRUELTY TOWARDS IMMIGRANTS AND THE
LGBTQ COMMUNITY. >> TODAY WE MUST STAND UP FOR
OUR UNHOUSED RESIDENTS WHO ARE DESPERATELY TRYING TO CHANGE
THEIR OWN SITUATION AND FIND REAL HOUSING STABILITY.
NOBODY WANTS TO BE HOMELESS. THEIR CIRCUMSTANCES NEVER
APPEAR DESIRE ACCORDING TO OUR PUBLIC DASHBOARDS.
>> SAN FRANCISCO AS HAS NEARLY 18,000 PEOPLE THROUGH PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING. THAT'S NOT JUST SYNTHETIC
POLICY AND NUMBERS PLACED ON A GRAPH.
>> THAT'S REAL ACTUAL HUMAN LIVES CHANGED.
>> 83% OF THOSE PLACED IN PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING
STAY FOR MANY YEARS. >> IMAGINE 18,000 PEOPLE BACK
ON THE STREETS. >> THAT'S CHASE CENTER TOTALLY
FILLED. THAT'S 327 FULLY PACKED MUNI
BUSSES AND WE CAN STILL DO WAY BETTER.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS A RESOURCES. THIS IS WHAT HOUSING FIRST
LOOKS LIKE IN ACTION. IT RAISES THE BAR FOR THE
ENTIRE CITY TO BE BETTER BECAUSE HOUSING FIRST AND HARM
REDUCTION DO SAVE LIVES. >> TRUMP'S ORDER THREATENS TO
WITHHOLD FEDERAL HOMELESSNESS AND MENTAL HEALTH FUNDS FROM
JURISDICTIONS THAT REFUSE TO CRIMINALIZE POVERTY
AND ADDICTION. IT TAKES RESOURCES AWAY FROM
POLICIES THAT ACTUALLY WORK. IT IS PUNISHMENT FOR COMPASSION
AND EVIDENCE BASED STRATEGIES AND THAT IS UNACCEPTABLE.
AND HE'S ALREADY STARTED HE'S STARTED WITH CUTTING $3.6
BILLION IN HUD HOMELESS GRANTS THAT ARE NOW FROZEN.
>> 60,000 HOUSEHOLDS ARE AT RISK OF LOSING THEIR EMERGENCY
HOUSING VOUCHERS NATIONALLY. HIS BUDGET PROPOSES OVER $1
BILLION NATIONALLY IN CUTS TO MENTAL HEALTH AND ADDICTION
TREATMENT. >> AND IN SAN FRANCISCO WE
RECEIVED 63 MILLION DOLLARS IN FEDERAL FUNDING FOR
HOMELESSNESS ALONE. NOW AT RISK OF BEING DEFUNDED
BECAUSE MAKE NO MISTAKE THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION'S CRUELTY
IS THE POINT HE WANTS US TO EVICT, INCARCERATE
AND ABANDONED PEOPLE. HE WANTS TO DEFUND WHAT WORKS
BECAUSE IT'S NOT PUNITIVE ENOUGH.
>> BUT DONALD TRUMP DOES NOT GET TO DICTATE HOW SAN
FRANCISCO OPERATES. >> HE WAS NOT ELECTED HERE.
HOUSING FIRST WORKS WHEN WE PROVIDE A HOME AND SUPPORT
INSTEAD OF CONDITIONS AND ULTIMATUMS AND RED TAPE.
PEOPLE SURVIVE WHEN PEOPLE HAVE A HOME AND ALLOWS THEM TO
RECEIVE SERVICES. >> IT IS UNREALISTIC TO EXPECT
OUR VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES TO DO MORE WHEN THEY DON'T EVEN
HAVE A ROOF OVER THEIR HEADS. SO LET'S BE CLEAR MOVING AWAY
FROM HOUSING FIRST MEANS THAT WE'VE CONCEDED THE FIGHT
AND HAVE GIVEN IN TO DONALD TRUMP AND THE MAGA AGENDA.
>> IT MEANS REJECTING POLICIES THAT AFFIRM THE DIGNITY
AND POTENTIAL OF EVERY PERSON STRUGGLING WITH HOMELESSNESS.
>> LET'S DOUBLE DOWN ON WHAT WORKS.
>> UNTIL WE TRULY INVEST IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING, SHELTER
AND COMPREHENSIVE SERVICES, WE HAVE NO BUSINESS TO DISMANTLE
LAYING THE FRAGILE REFUGE FOR SO MANY THAT WE FOUGHT HARD TO
SECURE. >> AND THEN SECONDLY, I'M
INTRODUCING RESOLUTION TO UPHOLD SAN FRANCISCO'S VALUES
AND SUPPORT OUR IMMIGRANT RESIDENTS ONCE AGAIN WITH
TEMPORARY PROTECTED STATUS TPS .
TBS IS A TEMPORARY LEGAL STATUS FOR IMMIGRANTS GRANTED TO
GROUPS OF ELIGIBLE INDIVIDUALS FROM COUNTRIES EXPERIENCING
INSTABILITY DUE TO NATURAL OR ENVIRONMENTAL DISASTERS,
POLITICAL UNREST, WARFARE ETC. .
>> THE TPS PROGRAM HAS BEEN IN PLACE SINCE 1990
AND CURRENTLY ENCOMPASSES 16 COUNTRIES EL SALVADOR, HAITI,
HONDURAS. NEPAL.
NICARAGUA. SOMALIA.
SOUTH SUDAN. SUDAN.
SYRIA. YEMEN.
VENEZUELA. UKRAINE.
AFGHANISTAN. ETHIOPE BIA CAMEROON AND BURMA.
IN THE US THERE ARE OVER 1 MILLION TPS HOLDERS MANY OF
WHOM HAVE BEEN HERE FOR 27 YEARS.
THEY HAVE BUILT FAMILIES HAVE U.S. CITIZEN SPOUSES, CHILDREN
AND GRANDCHILDREN. >> THEY ARE OUR NEIGHBORS ARE
FRIENDS, OUR COWORKERS AND OUR FAMILIES.
>> SINCE TAKING OFFICE, THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION HAS BURIED
OUR COMMUNITIES WITH DAILY DECLARATIONS AND EXECUTIVE
ORDERS ATTEMPTING TO SEPARATE FAMILIES AND REMOVE ALL AVENUES
FOR IMMIGRANTS TO REMAIN IN THIS COUNTRY.
>> CUTTING ESTABLISHED PROGRAMS DENYING DUE PROCESS AND USING
DRACONIAN AND OFTEN ILLEGAL ENFORCEMENT DETENTION
AND DEPORTATION TACTICS IN DEFIANCE OF THE US
CONSTITUTION. >> SINCE JANUARY THE DEPARTMENT
OF HOMELAND SECURITY HAS TERMINATED TPS FROM
AFGHANISTAN, CAMEROON, HAITI, HONDURAS, NICARAGUA AND NEPAL
IMPACTING HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF INDIVIDUALS FROM COUNTRIES
WITH VERIFIABLY AND PERSISTENTLY UNSAFE
CONDITIONS. >> AND MORE COUNTRIES ARE
EXPECTED. THE TERMINATION OF TPS AFFECTS
OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THAT IS
WHY OUR CITY HAS FILED AMICUS BRIEFS IN SUPPORT OF PLAINTIFFS
IN SEVERAL LAWSUITS TO PROTECT TPS HOLDERS.
THANKS TO THE EFFORTS OF OUR CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHU, THIS
RESOLUTION UPHOLDS SAN FRANCISCO'S SUPPORT FOR TPS
HOLDERS, RECOGNIZES THEIR INVALUABLE CONTRIBUTIONS TO SAN
FRANCISCO AND CALLS ON OUR CALIFORNIA DELEGATION TO
PROTECT TPS IN CONGRESS AND SEEK A PERMANENT PATHWAY
FOR TPS HOLDERS. I WANT TO THANK EARLY
CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISORS WALTON, MELGAR, CHAN AND CHEN AND TO
CARESS AND SAN FRANCISCO THE LATINO TASK FORCE AND THE
NATIONAL TPS ALLIANCE FOR YOUR WORK TO ADVOCATE FOR OUR
COMMUNITIES. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR MAHMUT THANK YOU COLLEAGUES.
>> TODAY I'M PROUD TO PUT FORWARD A NEW ORDINANCE RELATED
TO BUILDING PERMITS THAT IS PART OF A BROADER EFFORT TO
MODERNIZE OUR BUILDING CODES AND ACCELERATE HOUSING
AND SMALL BUSINESS PROJECTS ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO.
>> OVER THE LAST SEVERAL MONTHS WE'VE HEARD FROM HOMEOWNERS,
SMALL BUSINESSES AND DEVELOPERS ALIKE AND IT'S CLEAR OUR
CURRENT PERMIT RULES SLOW DOWN PROGRESS, RAISE COSTS
AND DISCOURAGE PEOPLE FROM MOVING FORWARD ON CRITICAL
PROJECTS. THIS ORDINANCE IS A SIMPLE BUT
POWERFUL STEP TOWARDS BRINGING GREATER CLARITY, ACCOUNTABILITY
AND MOMENTUM TO OUR PERMITTING SYSTEM.
>> MORE SPECIFICALLY, THIS ORDINANCE.
THIS ORDINANCE MODERNIZES SAN FRANCISCO'S BUILDING PERMIT
TIMELINES TO REDUCE ADMINISTRATIVE BURDEN, ALIGN
WITH STATE CODE AND MAKE OUR PROCESSES MORE CONSISTENT WITH
OTHER MAJOR JURISDICTIONS. >> UNDER CURRENT LAW, ISSUED
PERMITS EXPIRE AFTER JUST 12 MONTHS FOR SMALLER PROJECTS
AND 48 MONTHS FOR LARGER PROJECTS.
>> REGARDLESS OF HOW MUCH PROGRESS IS BEING MADE, THIS
MEANS THAT IF THERE ARE SUPPLY CHAIN ISSUES, UNEXPECTED
OBSTACLES OR OTHER LIMITATIONS ON THE PACE OF A PROJECT,
BUILDERS NEED TO APPLY FOR AN EXTENSION.
>> THIS ADDS UNNECESSARY COSTS TO PROJECTS AND UNNECESSARY
WORK FOR A DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING INSPECTION.
>> THE PERMIT TIMELINES ARE ALSO BASED ON THE ESTIMATED
VALUE OF CONSTRUCTION. A UNIQUELY SAN FRANCISCO
APPROACH THAT ADDS COMPLEXITY AND CONFUSION FOR APPLICANTS
ESPECIALLY THOSE WORKING ACROSS MULTIPLE CITIES.
>> THIS LEGISLATION REPLACES A RIGID VALUATION BASED TIMELINE
WITH A CLEAR CONSISTENT STANDARD ISSUED PERMITS EXPIRE
365 DAYS AFTER ISSUANCE. BUT AS LONG AS THERE ARE
INSPECTIONS OR LOGGED ACTIVITY WITH THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTION, THE TIMELINE AUTOMAT LIKELY RESETS.
>> CRUCIALLY, THIS APPROACH ALLOWS BUILDERS TO KEEP
PROJECTS ACTIVE AS LONG AS THEY ARE PROGRESSING EVEN IF
CONSTRUCTION IS SLOW OR INTERMITTENT.
AS IS OFTEN THE CASE FOR SMALLER PROJECTS LIKE KITCHEN
REMODELS OR FOR LARGER MULTI-PHASE HOUSING
DEVELOPMENTS, RENEWAL FEES AND EXTENSION PAPERWORK ARE NO
LONGER REQUIRED UNLESS A PROJECT HAS BEEN COMPLETELY
INACTIVE FOR A FULL YEAR HELPING REDUCE UNNECESSARY
COSTS AND DELAYS BY ALIGNING OUR PERMIT EXPIRATION RULES
WITH THOSE OF THE STATE AND OTHER LARGE CALIFORNIA
CITIES. THIS LEGISLATION SIMPLIFIES THE
PROCESS FOR DEVELOPERS, HOMEOWNERS AND CONTRACTORS
NAVIGATING MULTIPLE JURISDICTIONS.
>> IN SHORT, THIS ORDINANCE HELPS REDUCE ADMINISTRATIVE
BURDEN, LOWERS COSTS AND GIVES CERTAINTY TO THOSE TRYING TO
BUILD IN OUR CITY WHETHER IT'S A HOUSING DEVELOPMENT OR A
TENANT IMPROVEMENT TO A COMMERCIAL SPACE.
I WANT TO THANK HANNAH AT THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTION AND PETER LYNCH, OUR DRAFTING ATTORNEY FOR THEIR
TECHNICAL WORK IN HELPING SHAPE THIS ORDINANCE.
>> AND I WANT TO ESPECIALLY THANK SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND HIS
LEGISLATIVE AIDE AND LAND USE SUPERSTAR MADISON TIM AND HIS
OFFICE FOR THEIR EARLY WORK ON THIS LEGISLATION AND PARTNERING
AND CO-SPONSORING AS WELL. >> THIS ORDINANCE WILL HELP US
STREAMLINE PERMITTING, REDUCE BUREAUCRACY AND MAKE OUR CITY
WORK BETTER FOR ALL THOSE TRYING TO BUILD IN IT.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MOMENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. TODAY I HAVE AN ORDINANCE
AND 17 RESOLUTIONS ALTHOUGH NOT TO WORRY 16 OF THEM ARE REALLY
THE SAME THING ON THE ORDINANCE.
I AM INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO ESTABLISH AN ARTIST HOUSING
CERTIFICATION PROGRAM. AS YOU MAY BE AWARE A RECENT
$100 MILLION PRIVATE GIFT IS HELPING FUND THE DEVELOPMENT OF
A 1687 MARKET STREET PROJECT WHICH WILL PROVIDE MORE THAN 90
AFFORDABLE APARTMENTS AND CREATIVE SPACES FOR ARTISTS
INCLUDING REHEARSAL SPACES AND A BLACK BOX THEATER.
>> THE DEVELOPMENT OF THIS PROJECT IS HIGHLIGHTED THE NEED
FOR A FORMAL PROCESS BY WHICH TO IDENTIFY ARTISTS WHO MAY
QUALIFY FOR THIS OR WHAT WE HOPE WILL BE FUTURE AFFORDABLE
ARTIST HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS. THE ARTIST HOUSING
CERTIFICATION PROGRAM WILL MEET THAT NEED FOR 1687 MARKET
AND OTHER SIMILAR PROJECTS REQUIRING THE ARTS COMMISSION
TO ESTABLISH AND MAINTAIN A REGISTRY OF ARTISTS WHO WOULD
QUALIFY FOR SUCH HOUSING. I WANT TO THANK FORMER MERCY
HOUSING CALIFORNIA PRESIDENT DOUG SHOEMAKER AND RAY MEDIA
AND MERCY FOR PROPOSING LEGISLATION OR IDENTIFYING THE
NEED FOR IT. I WANT TO THANK DIRECTOR DAN
ADAMS AND SHEILA NICHOLAS ELLIS FROM MO FOR HELPING THINK IT
THROUGH. I WANT TO THANK DIRECTOR RALPH
REMINGTON ON THE LIST OF ENTRY FROM THE ARTS COMMISSION AS
WELL. AND THEN THE LAWYERS HAVE BEEN
VERY HELPFUL WITH THIS AND SO THANKS TO DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEYS
LAUREN CURRY AND KEITH NAGY. AND I WANT TO THANK CALVIN
IN MY OFFICE AS WELL. >> 16 OF THE 17 RESOLUTIONS
THAT I AM INTRODUCING ARE RELATE TO THE INITIATION OF
LANDMARK DESIGNATION FOR 16 BUILDINGS ACROSS DISTRICT
EIGHT. THE PACKAGE REPRESENTS A FIRST
STEP TOWARD A MORE COMPREHENSIVE LOOK AT THE BUILT
ENVIRONMENT IN DISTRICT EIGHT. WE KNOW THAT SAN FRANCISCO HAS
RELATIVELY FEW LOCAL LANDMARKS AS WE MOVE AS WE REMOVE
CONSTRAINTS ON HOUSING AND UP SO NEIGHBORHOODS TO ALLOW MORE
DENSITY. WE NEED TO ENSURE THAT WHAT'S
LEFT STANDING STILL TELLS THE STORY OF WHAT WE'VE BEEN.
I WANT TO THANK RICH SUE ALEX WESTHOFF AND P P LA LA LA
VALLEE FROM PLANNING I WANT TO THANK S.F. HERITAGE
AND COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS INCLUDING THE MISSION DELORES
NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION. AND I WANT TO THANK CALVIN
AND MATTHEW AND MELANIE MATTHEW MATTHEW AND IN MY OFFICE ALL OF
THEM FOR THEIR WORK ON THIS. AND I LOOK FORWARD TO
CONTINUING TO WORK TOGETHER. AND FINALLY THE 17TH RESOLUTION
IS ONE TO ADD THE COMMEMORATIVE STREET NAME JIM MARSHALL WAY TO
THE SIGNAGE FOR THE BLOCK OF 16TH STREET BETWEEN ZOE
AND CASTRO. JIM MARSHALL WAS BORN
IN CHICAGO IN 1936 AND HIS FAMILY MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO
WHEN HE WAS TWO YEARS OLD. HE BEGAN PHOTOGRAPHING
MUSICIANS AND ARTISTS WHILE ATTENDING LOWELL HIGH SCHOOL
BUT IT WASN'T UNTIL THE 1960S THAT HE BEGAN TO RISE IN FAME.
DURING THE 60S HE DOCUMENTED SAN FRANCISCO'S COUNTERCULTURE
MOVEMENT FROM ITS BEAT GENERATION ROOTS IN NORTH BEACH
TO THE CULMINATION OF THE SUMMER OF LOVE
AND HAIGHT-ASHBURY. HE BEFRIENDED SAN FRANCISCO
BANDS INCLUDING THE GRATEFUL DEAD JEFFERSON AIRPLANE,
QUICKSILVER MESSENGER SERVICE, THE CHART, THE CHARLATANS, BIG
BROTHER AND THE HOLDING COMPANY WITH JANIS JOPLIN AND HIS
PHOTOGRAPHS OF THESE BANDS HELPED PUSH THEM INTO THE
MAINSTREAM CONSCIOUSNESS AND MARKED SAN FRANCISCO AS THE
EPICENTER OF THE COUNTERCULTURE MOVEMENT.
JIM MARSHALL'S PHOTOGRAPHY HAS BEEN ON MORE THAN 500 ALBUM
COVERS AND IN ROLLING STONE MAGAZINE IN 2017 HE WAS THE
FIRST PHOTOGRAPHER TO BE AWARDED A GRAMMY FOR HIS
CONTRIBUTION TO CHRONICLING MUSIC HISTORY.
HE WAS THE ONLY PHOTOGRAPHER ALLOWED BACKSTAGE AT THE
BEATLES LAST CONCERT AT CANDLESTICK PARK IN 1966
CAPTURED JIMI HENDRIX BURNING HIS GUITAR AT THE MONTEREY POP
FESTIVAL, SHOT JOHNNY CASH PERFORMING AT SAN QUENTIN STATE
PRISON IN DOC STATE PRISON AND DOCUMENTED MILES DAVIS
BOXING AT NEWMAN'S GYM IN THE TENDERLOIN.
TODAY HIS WORK IS CELEBRATED WORLDWIDE AND TOURING EXHIBITS
OF HIS PHOTOGRAPHS BRING IN NEW FANS AND COLLECTORS IN THE U.S.
AND EUROPE. IT SEEMS ESPECIALLY FITTING TO
BE RECOGNIZING JIM MARSHALL AS WE ENTER A DEAD SUMMER AS HE
CAPTURED THOUSANDS OF GRATEFUL DEAD PHOTOS AND HIS CHRONICLING
OF THE BAND BETWEEN 1966 AND 1977 WAS RECENTLY PUBLISHED
IN GRATEFUL DEAD BY JIM MARSHALL.
I WANT TO THANK MARSHALL'S LONGTIME FRIEND AND ASSISTANT
EMIL DAVIS AND HIS NEIGHBOR JUSTIN NICHOLSON WHO'VE BEEN
CAMPAIGNING FOR THIS COMMEMORATIVE STREET RENAMING
FOR THE LAST YEAR. THEY'VE GATHERED SUPPORT FROM
DOZENS OF NEIGHBORS ON THE BLOCK AS WELL AS THE DUBOSE
TRIANGLE NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE ON HOTH FOR
HIS WORK ON THIS PROJECT AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. YOUR USE OF THE WORD EPICENTER
AT THIS TIME SINCE THOSE 2.0 EARTHQUAKES.
>> OH DEAR. OOPS.
>> NOT LOST ON ME. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING THE SAN FRANCISCO STREET SAFETY ACT A
COMPREHENSIVE INTER-AGENCY LEGISLATION TO ADDRESS ONE OF
THE MOST URGENT AND PREVENTABLE PUBLIC HEALTH CRISES IN OUR
CITY WHICH IS TRAFFIC VIOLENCE. >> EVERY YEAR TRAFFIC CRASHES
KILL OR SERIOUSLY INJURED DOZENS OF SAN FRANCISCANS
PARTICULARLY CHILDREN. ELDERS, PEDESTRIANS AND LOW
INCOME PEOPLE. DESPITE OUR LONG STANDING
COMMITMENT TO VISION ZERO, THE RATE OF TRAFFIC FATALITIES
IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS REMAINED LARGELY UNCHANGED.
WE CANNOT AFFORD TO KEEP DOING THE SAME THING AND EXPECTING
DIFFERENT RESULTS. ACCORDING TO A 2025 REPORT THAT
I COMMISSIONED FROM OUR BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST TRAFFIC
RELATED DEATHS AND INJURIES COST THE FRANCISCANS NEARLY
$500 MILLION EVERY YEAR. NOT TO MENTION THE IMMEASURABLE
PAIN AND LOSS EXPERIENCED BY FAMILIES IN VICTIMS.
WE NOW HAVE A DECADE OF DATA SHOWING WHAT WE'RE THAT WHEN WE
REDESIGN STREETS CRASHES DROP. BUT TOO OFTEN IMPLEMENTATION IS
TOO SLOW TO REACT OR SILOED ACROSS AGENCIES.
>> THIS RESOLUTION IS A CALL TO ACTION AND A ACCOUNT AND A CALL
FOR ACCOUNTABILITY. IT DIRECTS DEPARTMENTS THE SFO
TO THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT, DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH, PUBLIC WORKS, THE FIRE DEPARTMENT AND THE
SCHOOL DISTRICT TO TAKE CLEAR MEASURABLE STEPS TO MAKE OUR
STREETS SAFER. BASED ON DATA BASED ON WHAT WE
KNOW, BASED ON WHAT WE HAVE SEEN.
THAT INCLUDES EXPANDING DAYLIGHTING.
DEPLOYING RED LIGHTS AND SPEED CAMERAS WITHIN STATE LIMITS.
INTEGRATING STREET SAFETY INTO REPAVING PROJECTS AS WE SHOULD
BE DOING ALREADY. AND PUBLISHING A CITYWIDE
DASHBOARD SO THAT THE PUBLIC CAN TRACK PROGRESS.
WE KNOW THAT SPEEDING IS THE LEADING CAUSE OF FATAL CRASHES
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND WE KNOW THAT RESIDENTS IN LOW INCOME
NEIGHBORHOODS AND PARTICULARLY IN COMMUNITIES OF COLOR ARE
DISPROPORTIONATELY AFFECTED BY UNSAFE CONDITIONS.
THIS RESOLUTION CENTERS VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES AND USES
DATA DRIVEN APPROACH TO TARGET THE MOST DANGEROUS STREETS WITH
A FOCUS ON CHILDREN. SENIORS AND PEOPLE WITH
DISABILITIES. THE SAN FRANCISCO STREET SAFETY
ACT IS NOT JUST A POLICY SOLUTION IT'S ALSO A
RECOMMITMENT TO MAKING SAFETY THE DEFAULT NOT THE EXCEPTION.
AND CALLS FOR ACCOUNTABILITY REGULAR REPORTING IN FRONT OF
US. AND IT WILL MAKE SURE THAT
PEOPLE DO WHAT THEY'RE SUPPOSED TO BE DOING.
I URGE MY COLLEAGUES TO JOIN ME IN SUPPORTING THIS EFFORT
BECAUSE NO ONE SHOULD FEAR FOR THEIR LIFE SIMPLY CROSSING THE
STREET IN OUR CITY. >> AND THE REST, MADAM CLERK.
I SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE TWO ITEMS TO INTRODUCE.
FIRST, I AM SUBMITTING A LETTER OF INQUIRY TO THE SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE DEPARTMENT TO EXAMINE THEIR APPROACH TO RECRUITING
AND TRAINING NEW OFFICERS. IT IS MY HOPE THAT WE CAN
IDENTIFY WAYS TO SUCCESSFULLY ACCELERATE THE PACE OF HIRING,
TRAINING AND PLACING OFFICERS SO THAT THEY CAN BE READY TO
SERVE OUR COMMUNITIES. I WANT TO START BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THAT I BELIEVE REAL PROGRESS IS BEING MADE
THROUGH MAYOR LURIE REBUILDING THE RANKS AN INITIATIVE WHICH I
WAS AN EARLY SUPPORTER OF. IN ONE SAMPLE OF THAT EARLY
SUCCESS FROM JANUARY TO JUNE 2025, S.F. PD HAS RECEIVED 2155
APPLICATIONS WHICH IS A 64% INCREASE FROM 1311 1311 DURING
THE SAME PERIOD IN 2024. BUT WITH A STAFFING SHORTAGE OF
WELL OVER 500 OFFICERS, WE NEED TO KEEP PUSHING FOR MORE
IMPROVEMENTS AT EVERY STEP OF THE PROCESS.
SO SPECIFICALLY I AM ASKING FOR MORE INFORMATION ON OUR
APPROACH TO LATERAL RECRUITMENT WHICH IS A PATHWAY THAT SEEMS
PROMISING BUT MAY BE HELD BACK BY LOW PAY BONUSES COMPARED TO
OTHER BAY AREA CITIES. I'M ALSO INTERESTED IN LEARNING
ABOUT A POSSIBLE PARTNERSHIP WITH OUR LOCAL UNIVERSITIES
SIMILAR TO THE LAW ENFORCEMENT CANDIDATE SCHOLARS PROGRAM AT
SACRAMENTO STATE UNIVERSITY WHICH IS A PROGRAM THAT
PREPARES UNDERGRADUATE STUDENTS FOR A CAREER IN LAW ENFORCEMENT
. MY LETTER OF INQUIRY ALSO ASKS
A SERIES OF QUESTIONS RELATED TO HOW WE CAN BETTER RECRUIT
AND RETAIN FRONTLINE PERSONNEL WHO ARE BILINGUAL AND CAN SERVE
OUR DIVERSE COMMUNITIES. I BELIEVE WE MUST COMMIT TO
IMPROVING THIS SKILL SET ACROSS EVERY DEPARTMENT ESPECIALLY OUR
FRONTLINE PUBLIC SAFETY AGENCIES.
I ALSO HAVE A HEARING REQUEST TO INTRODUCE TODAY JUST A FEW
WEEKS AGO I SAT IN THESE SAME CHAMBERS WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON
FIELDER AND CHERYL FOR A HEARING ON THE IMPLOSION OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO PARKS ALLIANCE. >> WHAT WE LEARNED SHOULD BE OF
GREAT CONCERN. A COMPLETE MISMANAGEMENT OF
MONEY, A TOTAL LACK OF RESPONSIBILITY AND AT LEAST
$5.8 MILLION MISSING THAT BELONGS TO COMMUNITY GROUPS.
TO BE VERY CLEAR, I BELIEVE THESE ISSUES LAY SQUARELY AT
THE FAULT OF THE PARKS ALLIANCE AND LIKELY A FEW INDIVIDUALS
IN LEADERSHIP. BUT IT DOES BRING TO MIND THE
BROADER QUESTION OF HOW OUR CITY ENGAGES WITH PARTNERS
IN NONPROFITS. AND IF THERE IS ANY MECHANISM
THAT WE COULD HAVE USED TO SPOT WARNING SIGNS EARLIER FOR THIS
EXACT PURPOSE, OUR CITY'S COMPTROLLER OFFICE OVERSEES A
NONPROFIT MONITORING AND CAPACITY BUILDING PROGRAM.
THIS PROGRAM IS LONG STANDING HAVING BEGUN IN 2005.
SINCE THEN A 2024 ORDINANCE CHAMPIONED BY NOW
ASSEMBLYMEMBER STEFANI ADDED A NEW ADDED NEW LEGISLATIVE
REQUIREMENTS AND REPORTING STANDARDS TO THIS PROGRAM.
OVER 700 NONPROFIT ORGANIZATIONS ARE CONTRACTED TO
WORK WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT AND THESE
ORGANIZATIONS DELIVER MORE THAN $1.5 BILLION IN SERVICES EACH
YEAR. WHILE 69% OF THE CITY'S
CONTRACTORS ENDED THE MOST RECENT OVERSIGHT CYCLE WITH
FULL COMPLIANCE, THE OTHER 31% FACE CHALLENGES WITH PRODUCING
AUDITED FINANCIAL STATEMENTS AND AGENCY WIDE BUDGETS.
SO IN OUR HEARING WE INTEND TO ASK FOR UPDATES ON THE MOST
RECENT OVERSIGHT AND REPORTING REQUIREMENT CHANGES FROM THE
2024 UPDATE AND DIG INTO WAYS THAT WE CAN BETTER WORK WITH
NONPROFIT PARTNERS TO DELIVER EFFECTIVE SERVICES WHILE
MINIMIZING WASTE AND FISCAL MISMANAGEMENT AND THE REST OF
IT. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER
SUPERVISOR SHERYL. SUBMIT THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH, MADAM
CHAIR. COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE
DEPARTMENT TO CONSTRUCT A NEW TRAINING FACILITY FOR THE
DEPARTMENT EMPLOYEES AT 1236 CARROLL.
THIS FACILITY WILL CONSOLIDATE AND REPLACE THE CURRENT
TRAINING FACILITIES ON TREASURE ISLAND AND IN THE MISSION
DISTRICT IN ORDER TO BUILD THE FACILITY.
SEVERAL UNACCEPTABLE STREETS NEED TO BE VACATED.
PUBLIC WORKS HAS PERFORMED THE NECESSARY STEPS FOR A STREET
VACATION. THERE ARE PUBLIC UTILITIES
COMMISSION AND PGE ANY UTILITIES IN THE VACATION AREA
AND THEIR RESPECTIVE ACCESS TO THOSE FACILITIES IS
INCORPORATED INTO THE LEGISLATION OF ATTACHED TO THE
PROJECT SITE LAYOUT. >> FOR REFERENCE TODAY'S
LEGISLATION INCLUDES A RESOLUTION OF INTENT ALONG WITH
THE ORDINANCE FOR STREET VACATION AND THE ORDINANCE FOR
THE PLANNING CODE UPDATE. THIS PROJECT IS FUNDED BY THE
VOTER APPROVED EARTHQUAKE SAFETY AND EMERGENCY RESPONSE
ALSO KNOWN AS THE EASTER BOND MEASURE FROM 2020.
PUBLIC WORKS HAS MET WITH SEVERAL NEIGHBORHOOD GROUPS TO
PROVIDE AN OVERVIEW OF THE PROJECT AND TO SOLICIT INPUT
INCLUDING THE BABY HUNTERS POINT CITIZENS ADVISORY
COMMITTEE. BELLEVUE HILL NEIGHBORHOOD
ASSOCIATION TRUE HOPE CHURCH AND ALICE GRIFFITH TENANTS
ASSOCIATION COUNCIL. I WANT TO THANK IAN SNYDER FROM
PUBLIC WORKS AND DCA CHRIS TOM FOR PUTTING THIS TOGETHER
AND THANK YOU TO THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT FOR
BRINGING THIS FACILITY AND THE IMPROVEMENTS THAT COME WITH IT
TO DISTRICT TEN. >> I'M ALSO INTRODUCING AN
AMENDMENT TO THE LEASE WITH THE YMCA FOR BUILDING 49 AT CRANE
COVE PARK WITH THE PORT TO HELP COVER UNEXPECTED COSTS FROM
CRITICAL STRUCTURAL REPAIRS. THIS AMENDMENT PROVIDES
$150,000 IN ADDITIONAL RENT CREDITS AND PROTECTS $6,000
IN CREDITS FOR MAINTAINING PUBLIC RESTROOMS.
THE NEW DOGPATCH YMCA OFFICIALLY OPENED THEIR DOORS
THIS YEAR AND IS ALREADY DELIVERING ON ITS PROMISE TO
SERVE THE COMMUNITY. THIS SMALL BUT IMPORTANT
ADJUSTMENT HELPS ENSURE THE PROJECT STAYS FINALLY
FINANCIALLY SUSTAINABLE WHILE CONTINUING TO PROVIDE PUBLIC
BENEFITS. >> AND LAST I HAVE A RESOLUTION
TO RECOGNIZE AUGUST 20TH, 25 AS BLACK BUSINESS MONTH HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> HONORING THE 22ND ANNUAL
NATIONAL BLACK BUSINESS MONTH FOUNDED BY SAN FRANCISCAN
FREDERICK E JORDAN SENIOR AND HISTORIAN JOHN WILLIAMS
TEMPLETON THIS MONTH UPLIFTS THE LEGACY AND IMPACT OF BLACK
ENTREPRENEURS BOTH PAST AND PRESENT.
IT HONORS PIONEERS LIKE CAPTAIN WILLIAM ALEXANDER LASTER OFF A
BLACK MARINA AND ONE OF SAN FRANCISCO'S FIRST MAJOR
ENTREPRENEURS WHO HELPED SHAPE THE CITY'S EARLY ECONOMY
AND SERVED AS ITS FIRST TREASURER IN THE 1840S.
FROM TRAILBLAZERS LIKE HIM TO TODAY'S THRIVING BLACK
BUSINESSES ALONG THE THIRD STREET CORRIDOR AND DISTRICT
TEN SUCH AS GUMBO SOCIAL YVONNE SWEETS PUMPKINS ONE STOP BEAUTY
SHOP SMOKE SOUL KITCHEN AND MORE.
BLACK OWNED BUSINESSES ARE ESSENTIAL TO SAN FRANCISCO'S
CULTURE AND ECONOMIC LIFE. THIS RESOLUTION CALLS ON THE
CITY TO DEEPEN ITS INVESTMENT IN EQUITABLE ECONOMIC
DEVELOPMENT AND UPLIFT BLACK BUSINESSES YEAR ROUND.
I'D LIKE TO GIVE A SPECIAL THANK TO SPECIAL THANK YOU TO
OUR SUMMER INTERN EZRA MERCER, A RECENT HOWARD GRADUATE FOR
WORKING ALONGSIDE MY CHIEF OF STAFF NOW LED ON THIS
RESOLUTION. I ALSO WANT TO SHOUT OUT OUR
TWO INCREDIBLE YEAR ROUND INTERNS DAMIAN ROCHELLE, A
SENIOR AT SAN FRANCISCO STATE WHO'S BEEN WITH US SINCE
JANUARY AND CARL LEVI, A RECENT UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO
GRADUATE WHO ALSO JOINED US IN JANUARY.
WE'RE SO GRATEFUL FOR THEIR DEDICATION AND CONTRIBUTIONS TO
THE DISTRICT TEN DREAM TEAM THIS YEAR.
THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR CHIN CHAN SUBMITS.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, LET'S SAY SORRY
ABOUT THIS, OKAY? >> I HAVE A BLUE REQUEST AND IN
MEMORIAM FIRST TIME TODAY SUBMITTING A REQUEST TO OUR
BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST'S OFFICE TO ESTIMATE
THE COST TO SAN FRANCISCO TAXPAYERS FOR PROVISIONS OF OUR
EQUAL BENEFITS ORDINANCE WHICH MANDATES DOMESTIC PARTNER
BENEFITS THAT WERE ONCE BUT NO LONGER THE ONLY CHANCE GAY
AND LESBIAN COUPLES HAD FOR EQUAL EMPLOYMENT BENEFITS.
TODAY SAME SEX MARRIAGE IS THE LAW OF THE LAND, OF COURSE,
AND IT HAS BEEN FOR THE LAST DECADE.
YET SAN FRANCISCO STILL PROHIBITS WHAT IS NOW A GROWING
MAJORITY OF BUSINESSES FROM EVEN COMPETING FOR ANY OF OUR
$5.8 BILLION IN TAXPAYER FUNDED CONTRACTS FOR GOODS
AND SERVICES ANNUALLY. THE REASON IS THAT THEY DON'T
PROVIDE ADEQUATE DOMESTIC PARTNER BENEFITS.
MY REQUEST TODAY POSES THREE QUESTIONS FOR THE BLR TO
RESEARCH. FIRST, WHAT IS THE MOST
RELIABLE ESTIMATE OF THE PERCENTAGE OF ALL U.S.
BUSINESSES THAT STILL OFFER THEIR EMPLOYEES DOMESTIC
PARTNERSHIP BENEFITS EQUAL TO THOSE THEY PROVIDE TO MARRIED
COUPLES? SINCE SAME SEX MARRIAGE RIGHTS
WERE FIRST SECURED NATIONWIDE BY THE U.S. SUPREME COURT'S
DECISION IN OBERGEFELL VERSUS HODGES IN 2015.
TWO. ASSUMING THE ACCURACY OF DATA'S
DATA, MY OFFICE IDENTIFIED SHOWING THAT NO MORE THAN 45%
OF LARGE BUSINESSES NATIONWIDE TODAY EVEN OFFER DOMESTIC
PARTNER BENEFITS WITH NO ESTIMATES FOR SMALL OR MEDIUM
SIZED BENEFITS FOR BUSINESSES. WHAT COST SAVINGS MIGHT SAN
FRANCISCO REASONABLY EXPECT WERE WE TO OPEN COMPETITIVE
BIDDING FOR CITY CONTRACTS TO 100% OF BUSINESSES RATHER THAN
JUST 45%? AND THREE WHAT ARE THE ACTUAL
DIRECT COSTS TO SAN FRANCISCO TAXPAYERS FOR ENFORCEMENT
AND COMPLIANCE OF EQUAL BENEFITS PROVISIONS BY THE
OFFICE OF CONTRACT ADMINISTRATION CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE AND OTHER DEPARTMENTS? I'M ASKING THAT THIS INCLUDE AN
ACCOUNTING FOR COSTS TO PROCESS WAIVERS AND FROM THESE
REQUIREMENTS AS WELL. NOW THERE ADMITTEDLY WAS A TIME
BEFORE SAME SEX MARRIAGE RIGHTS WERE SECURED NATIONWIDE WHEN
SUCH A BIDDING PROHIBITION MADE SENSE.
FOR YEARS DOMESTIC PARTNERSHIPS REFLECTED THE HOLY WORTHWHILE
PRINCIPLE OF LGBTQ PLUS EQUALITY AND THAT PRINCIPLE WAS
WORTH THE ADDED EXPENSE BORNE BY TAXPAYERS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
TODAY'S EQUAL BENEFITS ORDINANCE, HOWEVER, IS NO
LONGER AN LGBTQ PLUS ISSUE THAT IS INARGUABLE.
AND IT HASN'T BEEN AN LGBTQ PLUS ISSUE SINCE 2015.
BY MAKING COMPETITIVE BIDDING MORE COMPETITIVE SAN FRANCISCO
CAN DERIVE GREATER VALUE FOR THE GOODS AND SERVICES WE
PURCHASE WITH OUR TAXPAYERS DOLLARS.
>> IT CERTAINLY SEEMS PLAUSIBLE THAT EXPANDING OUR BIDDING
ELIGIBILITY FROM FEWER THAN 45% OF BUSINESSES TO FULLY 100% OF
BUSINESSES WOULD ACHIEVE SOME MEASURE OF SAVINGS FOR THE MORE
ROBUST COMPETITION. GIVEN PUBLISHED RESEARCH
SHOWING THAT SAN FRANCISCO'S ANNUAL EXPENDITURE FOR GOODS
AND SERVICES CONTRACTS TOTALS $5.8 BILLION, EVEN A MARGINAL
SAVINGS OF JUST 5% WOULD NET US $290 MILLION.
AND FOR CONTEXT THAT IS MORE THAN THE ENTIRE BUDGET OF THE
RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT. BEFORE WE PUT PEN TO PAPER ON
LEGISLATION OBVIOUSLY LET'S DO LET IT BE THOUGHTFUL ABOUT THIS
LET'S ALLOW THE BLR TO DO ITS WORK.
LET'S SEE WHAT KIND OF COST SAVINGS THEY ESTIMATE AND THEN
LET'S LEGISLATE RESPONSIBLY AND PRUDENTLY.
WE OWE SAN FRANCISCO TAXPAYERS NOTHING LESS.
>> AND NEXT. COLLEAGUES I ASK THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN REMEMBRANCE OF SCOTT GARVEY
,A DEEPLY COMPASSIONATE, CREATIVE AND LOVING SOUL WHOSE
TRAGIC RECENT DEATH HAS LEFT HIS FAMILY AND MANY OTHERS
REELING INCLUDING FRIENDS AND LOVED ONES HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. I GREW UP AS A CLOSE FRIEND OF
THE GARVEY'S AND I KNOW I'VE KNOWN THEM WELL MOST OF MY LIFE
. SCOTT ATTENDED ST MARY'S
CATHOLIC SCHOOL IN WESTFIELD, MASSACHUSETTS WITH HIS OLDER
BROTHER AND ME AND IT WAS PERHAPS THERE THAT SCOTT
DEVELOPED HIS COMMITMENT TO SOCIAL JUSTICE WHICH IN HIS
LIFE WOULD BECOME HIS MOST ADMIRED TRAIT.
SCOTT WAS A POET, A MUSICIAN AND ABOVE ALL A GIVER SOMEONE
WHO CARRIED THE BURDEN OF AN OUTSIZED HEART IN A WORLD THAT
TOO OFTEN SHUNS THOSE WHO STRUGGLE.
ALTHOUGH HE FACED MENTAL HEALTH CHALLENGES MOST OF HIS ADULT
LIFE HAVING BEEN DIAGNOSED WITH SCHIZOPHRENIA AND BIPOLAR
DISORDER, SCOTT'S GENEROUS SPIRIT AND HIS GOOD HEART WERE
UNDIMINISHED. HE FOUND PURPOSE IN OFFERING
COMFORT AND CARE TO OTHERS IN NEED AND HE WOULD OFTEN USE
WHATEVER DISCRETIONARY FUNDS HE HAD FROM HIS LIMITED DISABILITY
INCOME TO HELP OTHERS TO BUY CLEAN SOCKS OR WARM GLOVES OR
MEALS TO SHARE WITH UNHOUSED NEIGHBORS.
FOR SCOTT IT WASN'T PERFORMATIVE.
IT WAS WHO HE WAS. HIS IMPULSE TO HELP AND TO GIVE
BACK JUST CAME NATURALLY TO HIM.
THE FAMILY MEMBERS AND FRIENDS. SCOTT'S EMPATHY WAS RADIANT.
FRIENDS DESCRIBED HIM AS SOFT SPOKEN AND POETIC SOMEONE WHO
LISTENED MORE THAN HE SPOKE AND WHO HAD THE RARE GIFT OF
MAKING OTHERS FEEL TRULY SEEN. HIS ART ESPECIALLY HIS POETRY
AND HIS DRUMMING WAS AN EXTENSION OF HIS EMOTIONAL
GENEROSITY. LIKE MANY ARTISTS, HE COULD
FIND MEANING IN PAIN AND CREATE BEAUTY OUT OF STRUGGLE.
SAN FRANCISCO HELD A VERY SPECIAL PLACE IN SCOTT'S HEART
FOR A TIME. MANY YEARS AGO HE LIVED IN OUR
CITY'S STORIED HAIGHT-ASHBURY NEIGHBORHOOD WHICH WAS
ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL TO HIM AS A TALENTED MUSICIAN HIMSELF.
WHEN HE MOVED TO VERMONT EARLIER THIS YEAR ALONG WITH
HIS MOTHER JUDY OR MAMA J AS SHE'S AFFECTIONATELY
AFFECTIONATELY KNOWN, HE WANTED TO BE CLOSER TO HIS SISTER
KARA. IT WAS WITH THE HOPE OF
ACCESSING BETTER CARE IN THE REGION HE GREW UP THAT HE COULD
CONTINUE TO CONTINUE ON HIS PATH OF HEALING.
SADLY HE SCARCELY HAD THE CHANCE.
EARLIER THIS MONTH IN THE MIDST OF A MENTAL HEALTH CRISIS,
SCOTT LOST HIS LIFE WHEN HE WAS SHOT IN AN ENCOUNTER WITH A
VERMONT STATE POLICE TROOPER. UNARMED AT THE TIME.
HIS FAMILY IS NOW LEFT TO GRAPPLE WITH UNIMAGINABLE GRIEF
. THEY ARE BOTH HAUNTED BY
KNOWLEDGE OF COMPASSION AND GRACE.
SCOTT WASN'T EXTENDED IN HIS LAST MOMENTS WHEN HE NEEDED IT
MOST. THERE ALSO HUMBLED BY THE LOVE
AND KINDNESS OF FRIENDS AND FAMILY MEMBERS EVEN
NEIGHBORS AND STRANGERS IN THE COMMUNITY IN PUTNEY, VERMONT
WHO HAVE BEEN MOVED TO HELP THE GARVEY FAMILY AND TO HEAL.
IN REMEMBERING SCOTT TODAY, HIS FAMILY ASKS THAT WE DO NOT
SOLELY MOURN BUT ALSO TAKE IT AS A CALL TO CONSCIENCE
AND THAT WE CARRY SCOTT'S SPIRIT OF SOCIAL JUSTICE
AND HOW WE LEAD IN THE POLICIES WE PASSED AND HOW WE CARE FOR
OUR OWN MOST VULNERABLE AND HOW WE ENCOUNTER THOSE
IN BEHAVIORAL CRISES AND IN THE HOPES WE HOLD FOR A BETTER
WORLD. REST IN PEACE SCOTT.
MAY MEMORY BE A BLESSING AND A REMINDER OF WHAT WE NEED TO
CHANGE AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY
. MEMBERS WE RECEIVED
APPROXIMATELY 55 ITEMS FOR THE ALLY THIS WEEK.
ALL OF THE ITEMS YOU'VE INTRODUCED TODAY WILL BE
APPROPRIATELY REFERRED. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT.
YOU CAN LINE UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER ALONG
THE CURTAINS. ITEMS YOU CAN SPEAK TO THE
MINUTES HAS PRESENTED THE ITEMS 72 THROUGH 77 ON THE ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE CALENDAR.
OTHER GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON TODAY'S AGENDA BUT MUST BE
WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
>> WOULD YOU LIKE US TO COLLECT THAT FROM YOU MR. FIELD?
>> OKAY. THAT'S OKAY.
WE'LL SEND THE SERGEANT TO COME PICK THAT UP.
>> OKAY. >> ALL RIGHT.
I'LL SET YOUR TIME FOR YOU. >> YES.
THE QUEUE IS TO KEEP YOUR EMOTION TOWARDS BEAUTY.
BUT I THINK IN YOUR CASE IT'S NOT IT'S NOT ENOUGH.
THE DISEASE IS TOO. IT'S A DISEASE.
WE ARE DEALING WITH A DISEASE. >> THE KEY IS TO UNDERSTAND HOW
TO STOP ACCEPTING IT. >> THE POLITICAL SYSTEM WHICH
IS NOW WHICH HAS BEEN THERE FOR A LONG TIME ALREADY TOTALLY
INFECTED TO CREATE GOVERNMENTS RUN BY PEDOPHILES.
>> THAT'S WHAT YOU NEED TO UNDERSTAND OR TO STOP WORKING
IN THAT CASE FOR GOVERNMENTS RUN BY PEDOPHILES.
>> HOW DO YOU DO THAT? SO RAISE YOUR HAND IF YOU DON'T
KNOW HOW TO DO IT. OKAY.
SO NOW WHEN WE COME BACK, I'M STILL THE SAME WAY OF THINKING
I HOPE FOR YOU. >> YOU WILL HAVE NO MORE EXCUSE
IF I CALL YOU PEDOPHILES BECAUSE I SAID THAT.
>> YOU SEE, IT'S IMPORTANT TO UNDERSTAND.
>> YOU DON'T CALL OUT THE PEDOPHILES.
FIND A WAY TO DO IT. STEP BY STEP.
YOU BECOME A PEDOPHILE DESPITE WHAT YOU WANT.
>> SO IT MEANS NO MATTER WHAT YOU NO FUTURE BECAUSE NO
COMPETENCE, RIGHT? MEANING NO SAFETY ALL TOGETHER
WITH A GOVERNMENT OF PEDOPHILES.
>> IT'S AS SIMPLE AS THIS. >> SO NO SAFETY FOR ANYONE
UNDER WE HAVE NO RIGHTS, GUYS. >> WE ONLY HAVE DUTIES IN LIFE.
ONLY DUTIES TO DO WHAT'S HE'S AIMED AT.
>> BEAUTY. THAT'S IT.
>> OKAY. CAN WE HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER, PLEASE? YES.
I LIKE TO USE THE OVERHIT YES AS HAVE GO TV.
THANK YOU. YES I'M HERE CONCERNING MY SON
RB I HAVE A CUSTOMER WHO WAS MURDERED AUGUST 14TH 2006 ON
THE 14TH OF AUGUST WILL BE THE 19TH YEAR OF HIS DEATH AND I AM
ASKING FOR YOU SUPERVISORS TO PLEASE COME AND SUPPORT US
AND I BRING THESE OTHER PICTURES WITH ME CONCERNING
UNSOLVED HOMICIDES. AND COMMISSIONER MARY SCOTT
THAT WORKED FOR A POLICE COMMISSIONER NOW THAT'S HER SON
AND SHE IS GOING TO BE THERE AND I WOULD LOVE TO HAVE HER
SPEAK SO JUST SAYING THAT NO MATTER WHAT WE DO AND WHAT JOB
WE DO, OUR LOVED ONES ARE LEAVING THIS WORLD.
>> HERE'S OTHER UNSOLVED HOMICIDES THAT ARE NOT SOLVED.
>> I BRING HERE'S OTHER OTHERS UNSOLVED HOMICIDES THAT ARE NOT
SOLVED. >> I BRING THIS EVENT TO SEE
JUST TO INVITE AND I JUST HAD HER PASS SOME OUT TO EVERYONE.
>> I DON'T KNOW IF YOU'VE GOTTEN IT BUT YEAH SO I'M
ASKING FOR YOUR SUPPORT AND FOR MOTHERS AND FATHERS LIKE MYSELF
ON THAT DAY TO COME OUT JUST FOR A LITTLE WHILE IF YOU IF
YOU DON'T IF YOU CAN'T SEND A REPRESENTATIVE I'M ASKING MY
DISTRICT MY SUPERVISOR THE BYLAW TO PLEASE COME I NEED YOU
THERE. I KNOW YOU'RE GETTING MARRIED
AND CONGRATULATIONS BUT PLEASE BRING HER WITH YOU SO AND HALF
OF YOU HAVE LOST LOVED ONES AND IF YOU HAVE CHILDREN, IF
YOU HAVE CHILDREN, YOU HAVE NIECES AND NEPHEWS TOO.
WE DON'T WANT THIS TO HIT NOBODY ELSE'S HOME.
BELIEVE ME. THIS IS I DON'T LIKE DOING
THIS. I DON'T LIKE COMING HERE
TALKING ABOUT THIS ALL THE TIME.
BUT I WANT JUSTICE FOR MY CHILD .
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MISS BROWN.
OKAY. WELCOME.
HELLO. WE ARE BARELY SIX MONTHS INTO
THIS FEDERAL ADMINISTRATION AND LOCAL ONE TWO AND THINGS
WILL ONLY GET WORSE. WE ARE BEING PUT TO THE TEST
STARTING IN 2022 FOR REDISTRICTING IS WHEN I STARTED
GETTING INVOLVED IN LOCAL GOVERNMENT MAKING MY VOICE
KNOWN AS A CONSTITUENT. >> LATER I SPEARHEADED AND GOT
UNANIMOUS UNANIMOUSLY PASSED A PROTECT TRANS AND LGBTQ YOUTH
AND ADULTS RESOLUTION IN 2023 AND THEN THINGS GOT OUT OF MY
CONTROL. BUT I CONTINUE TO BE JUST ME
BECAUSE THAT'S ALL I KNOW REALLY HOW TO DO.
I TRY TO UPLIFT THE VOICES OF THE IGNORED POINT OUT THE
HYPOCRISY OF OUR GOVERNMENT, INFORM PEOPLE AND ENCOURAGE
PEOPLE TO CARE FOR OTHERS. I NEVER THOUGHT MYSELF AS A
LEADER BUT IN THESE FASCIST TIMES I CAN'T DOWNPLAY MY WORDS
AND ACTIONS ANYMORE BECAUSE PEOPLE ARE SCARED THERE'S LESS
PEOPLE BEING LOUD AND CRITICAL AND DEFIANT DURING THESE
DANGEROUS DAYS AND SO TO EVERY SCARED PERSON IN THIS BUILDING
AND EVERY SCARED PERSON WATCHING KNOW THAT I AM SCARED
TOO VERY SCARED. I DON'T KNOW HOW MUCH WORSE
THINGS WILL GET NOR WHAT WILL HAPPEN TO ME AS A DEFIANT TRANS
MEXICAN-AMERICAN. >> BUT I ALSO KNOW THAT I AM
PROUD OF MYSELF, PROUD OF MY FRIENDS AND PROUD OF OUR
COMMUNITY FOR NOT BOWING DOWN TO KISS ANY BILLIONAIRE'S RING
FOR ACTING UP IN DEFENSE OF OUR IMMIGRANT FAMILIES IN DEFENSE
OF PALESTINIAN SUFFERING, GENOCIDE AND DEFENSE OF
HOMELESS PEOPLE IN DEFENSE OF PEOPLE WITH SUBSTANCE USE
DISORDER FOR PERSISTING IN PRACTICING OUR MORALS OF
TREATING OTHERS THE WAY YOU WANT TO BE TREATED FOR
ACKNOWLEDGING THE HORRIBLE REVERBERATIONS OF THE GENOCIDE
OF INDIGENOUS PEOPLE HERE AND THE KIDNAPING
AND ENSLAVEMENT OF MILLIONS OF INDIGENOUS AFRICANS FOR NOT
ABANDONING THE T AND LGBTQ PLUS AND FOR PROTECTING TRANS
AND INTERSEX KIDS AND ADULTS WHO WANT NOTHING MORE BUT TO
LIVE THEIR LIVES AS THEMSELVES FOR LISTENING AND HEEDING TO
THE NEEDS OF DISABLED PEOPLE FOR NOT VILLAINIZING SEX
WORKERS BUT WANTING TO GIVE THEIR WORK DIGNITY
AND PROTECTION AND SO MUCH MORE SO MUCH MORE I CAN'T FIT HERE.
AND IF ANY OF THIS SOUNDS LIKE YOU I AM PROUD OF YOU.
>> YOU ARE ON THE RIGHT SIDE OF HISTORY.
FUTURE GENERATIONS WILL ADMIRE YOU.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WE HEAR FROM THE NEXT SPEAKER. PLEASE.
GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS. I'M JULIANNE MALONEY, CO-CEO OF
SUTRO POWER, THE SAN FRANCISCO BASED GREEN ENERGY COMPANY
AND I'M HERE REPRESENTING THE S.F. SOLAR AND STORAGE
COALITION. THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION JUST
ELIMINATED THE 30% SOLAR TAX CREDIT EFFECTIVE JANUARY 2026.
THIS CREATES IMMEDIATE URGENCY AS THOUSANDS OF SAN FRANCISCANS
ARE ATTEMPTING TO GET THEIR SYSTEMS DESIGNED, INSTALLED
AND ACTIVATED BEFORE THE DEADLINE AS SAN FRANCISCANS
RUSH TO GO SOLAR. OUR CITY'S PERMITTING PROCESSES
ARE BLOCKING THEM PLAN REVIEWS TAKE WEEKS IF NOT MONTHS LONGER
THAN NECESSARY. INSPECTIONS ARE ALSO MORE
DIFFICULT WHERE IT ONCE TOOK A SINGLE WEEK FOR INSPECTION
TURNAROUND IT IS NOW 3 TO 6 WEEKS TO GET FINALIZED.
OUR INSTALLATIONS FACE ADDITIONAL RED TAPE ON
MULTIFAMILY BUILDINGS, APARTMENTS AND COMMERCIAL
SPACES AS THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION ATTACKS GREEN
ENERGY, SAN FRANCISCO SHOULD MAKE IT EASIER FOR RESIDENTS TO
CHOOSE CLEAN ENERGY, NOT HARDER .
YOU'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM FRUSTRATED RESIDENTS WHOSE
SOLAR INSTALLATIONS ARE DELAYED BY CURRENT PROCESSES.
THIS ISN'T JUST ABOUT BEATING A FEDERAL DEADLINE.
THE PERMITTING REFORMS WE NEED NOW WILL SERVE RESIDENTS FOR
DECADES AS OUR CITY REQUIRES TENS OF THOUSANDS MORE SOLAR
AND STORAGE INSTALLATIONS. SUPERVISORS INCLUDE OUR
COALITION IN THESE POLICY DISCUSSIONS.
WE ARE IN THE TRENCHES HERE. WE UNDERSTAND EXACTLY WHERE THE
BOTTLENECKS ARE AND HOW TO FIX THEM.
WHILE OTHER BAY AREA CITIES ARE STREAMLINING, SAN FRANCISCO
SHOULDN'T FALL BEHIND USE THIS URGENT MOMENT TO PREPARE THE
GREEN ENERGY INFRASTRUCTURE OUR CITY NEEDS.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
I'M JOHN POWER UP AND REPRESENTING BOTH MY SOLAR
INSTALLATION FIRM SUTRO POWER AND THE SAN FRANCISCO SOLAR
AND STORAGE COALITION. I'VE REACHED OUT TO EACH OF
YOUR OFFICES VIA PHONE AND EMAIL BOTH A MONTH AGO
AND LAST WEEK REGARDING MY COALITION'S PLATFORM.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISORS FIELDER MELGAR
SHORTER AND GARCIA MAHMOOD AND PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR
FOLLOWING UP AND ENGAGING WITH US.
>> I CAME TODAY TO REQUEST THAT YOU CONVENE A SPECIAL SESSION
OR COMMITTEE HEARING DEDICATED TO HEARING DIRECTLY FROM OUR
COALITION ON URGENT MATTERS RELATED TO ROOFTOP SOLAR ENERGY
EQUITY AND THE CITY'S DECARBONIZATION GOALS BEFORE
FURTHER POLICY IS MADE BY DEVI YES A FIRE DEPARTMENT OR CLEAN
POWER S.F.. WE BELIEVE THERE'S AN IMMEDIATE
NEED FOR STRUCTURED DIALOG BETWEEN POLICYMAKERS AND FRONT
LINE STAKEHOLDERS WORKING ON DISTRIBUTED ENERGY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. WE'RE REQUESTING THAT A
SUPERVISOR SPONSOR THE SESSION SO THAT WE MAY FORMALLY PRESENT
DATA, TESTIMONY AND POLICY PROPOSALS THAT IMPACT THOUSANDS
OF RESIDENTS AND SMALL BUSINESSES.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. WE LOOK FORWARD TO
COLLABORATING ON A SESSION THAT ADVANCES LOCAL CLIMATE
LEADERSHIP AND ENERGY INDEPENDENCE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
THANK YOU. MY NAME IS MARIANNE RODRIGUEZ
GAVEL. I AM A RESIDENT AND EMPLOYEE
IN DISTRICT FIVE CLEAN POWER S.F. WAS CREATED BY SAN
FRANCISCANS TO GENERATE LOCAL ENERGY AND INCREASE OUR
INDEPENDENCE. IT WAS CREATED TO MAKE POSSIBLE
A PATH TO CLEAN LOCAL ENERGY WITHOUT THE WALL STREET GREED
AND PROFIT FOCUSED INVESTOR OWNED UTILITIES LIKE P, G AND E
NOW CLEAN POWER S.F. INTENDS TO ADOPT THE AVOIDED COST
CALCULATOR AND KILL ROOFTOP SOLAR IN SAN FRANCISCO.
LOOK NO FURTHER THAN OUR NEIGHBORS OUTSIDE OF THE CITY
WHERE IT'S ALREADY BEEN IMPLEMENTED F STOP SOLAR
ADOPTION HAS EXPERIENCED A NEAR MARKET COLLAPSE IN CALIFORNIA
OUTSIDE OF SAN FRANCISCO WE HAVE A CHOICE TO REJECT THIS
MODEL AND REAFFIRM OUR VALUES. WE VALUE CLEAN LOCAL ENERGY.
PLEASE REVIEW THE ESTABLISHED RECORD OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS RESOLUTION 406 14 THE CLEAN POWER S.F.
IMPLEMENTATION PLAN FROM 2015 AND S.F. ENVIRONMENTAL CODE
SECTION 18.1 REJECT ANY COMPENSATION MODEL THAT USES
THE AVOIDED COST CALCULATOR AND COMPENSATE SAN FRANCISCANS
FOR THE FULL BENEFITS OF SOLAR POWER.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER CHARLES ADDAMS ALBION POWER
COMPANY IS A LOCAL BUSINESS. OVER THE PAST 20 YEARS WE'VE
INSTALLED FEDERAL STATE RESIDENTIAL AND UTILITY SOLAR
PROJECTS AND I WAS IN THE ROOM WHEN SOME OF YOUR PREDECESSORS
WHEN CCAS WERE LEGISLATED. WE HAVE IMMENSE DISAPPOINTMENT
IN CLEAN POWER S EFFORTS TO DESTROY LOCAL SOLAR BY
DEVALUING RESIDENT PRODUCED SOLAR ENERGY WHILE SUBSCRIBING
TO AN ENVIRONMENTALLY DESTRUCTIVE SHELL GAME CLEAN
ENERGY MODEL FUNDED BY WALL STREET TAX EQUITY.
THE CITY IS CURRENTLY DESTROYING ITS MAIN STREET
GREEN ECONOMY AS INTENDED ROOFTOP SOLAR PRODUCES 100%
LOCAL CLEAN ENERGY, LOCAL JOB CREATION, LOCAL TAX REVENUE
FUNDED BY SAN FRANCISCANS USING THEIR OWN ROOFTOPS AND MONEY.
ALL OF THE ENERGY CREATED IN SAN FRANCISCO STAYS IN SAN
FRANCISCO IT IS LESS EXPENSIVE BUT CLEAN POWER S.F. MUST
HONESTLY COMPENSATE THE RESIDENTS WHO PROVIDE THIS
BENEFIT SFP P INSTEAD WANTS TO USE THE AC C CALCULATOR.
THE P, G AND E DEVICE ASSUMING ALL CLEAN ENERGY IS PROVIDED
CENTRALLY BY DECLARING LOCAL ENERGY LOCAL SMALL BUSINESS
ENERGY EFFICIENCY AND ENVIRONMENTAL CONSERVATION
AS A COST SHIFT TO THE POOR. THE PSEUDO ECONOMICS FAVORING
CENTRALIZED POWER GENERATION THE COST PLUS 10% UTILITY
INFRASTRUCTURE LOBBY HAS FUNDED A LOT OF STATE LEGISLATION OVER
THE PAST TWO YEARS DISGUISING A LOT OF ENVIRONMENTAL DAMAGE
AND INFRASTRUCTURE PROJECTS AS CLEAN ENERGY.
SAN FRANCISCO COPYING THIS REGULATORY CAPTURE AGAINST
LOCAL GENERATION IS A BETRAYAL OF EVERYTHING CCAS WERE CREATED
TO CHAMPION. WE ARE NOT ASKING FOR SUBSIDIES
WE'RE INSISTING CLEAN POWER S.F. PROVIDE AN HONEST
ACCOUNTING OF THE BENEFITS OF LOCAL GENERATION ON ROOFTOPS BY
RESIDENTS AND THE DBE BUILDING CODES CAN REALISTICALLY BE
IMPLEMENTED IN AN URBAN ENVIRONMENT THOSE THINGS ARE
NOT CURRENTLY HAPPENING. YOUR URGENT ATTENTION TO SFP
C'S MISUNDERSTANDING IS GREATLY APPRECIATED.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. THANK YOU AND AS A GOV TV THANK
YOU. REALLY HARD TO SEE THE EFFORTS
THAT CAN YOU USE THE MICROPHONE PLEASE?
THANK YOU. THIS IS PROBABLY HARD TO SEE.
IT'S THE SAN FRANCISCO BUILDING CODE ORDINANCES THAT WERE
PASSED BY THIS BOARD ON SOLAR PERMITTING AND INSPECTIONS
AND THOSE ARE NOT BEING FOLLOWED RIGHT NOW.
>> I'M JANINE COTTER. I'M CO-FOUNDER OF LUMINOL
AND WE'VE BEEN INSTALLING SOLAR AND BATTERIES IN SAN FRANCISCO
FOR 24 OVER 20 YEARS. I'M A RESIDENT OF DISTRICT FOUR
AND LUMINOSITIES IN DISTRICT TEN.
LUMINOL WAS SAN FRANCISCO'S FIRST WORKFORCE CERTIFIED GO
SOLAR MYSELF INSTALLER SO WE HIRED FOLKS THROUGH THAT
WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM AND I'M THE CHAIR OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S WORKFORCE INVESTMENT BOARD AND ON JULY
4TH TRUMP'S ONE BIG BEAUTIFUL BILL ELIMINATED THE 30% TAX
CREDIT FOR SOLAR BATTERY INSTALLS AFTER THIS YEAR WE
HAVE FIVE MONTHS. WE HAVE FIVE MONTHS.
I CAME TODAY WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO SOLAR BATTERY
COALITION WHICH IS COMPRISED OF LOCALLY OWNED SMALL BUSINESSES
LIKE LUMINOL. AND WE HAVE THREE ISSUES OF
REALLY EXCRUCIATING CONCERN TO US.
ONE IS PERMITTING. THE OTHER IS INSPECTIONS
AND THEN THERE'S CLEAN POWER AS JEFF'S PROPOSAL TO ADOPT
GENIE'S NESE NET BILLING TARIFF AND UNDERVALUE SOLAR ENERGY
GENERATED BY SAN FRANCISCANS, PERMITS USED TO BE PULLED
ONLINE FOR MODEST SOLAR SYSTEMS AS PERMITS FOR LARGER SYSTEMS
TOOK 3 TO 5 DAYS. >> THEY NOW TAKE 4 TO 8 WEEKS
WITH OUTLIERS TAKING SIX OR MORE MONTHS.
SOLAR APP AUTOMATIC AUTOMATED PERMITTING IS MORE RESTRICTIVE
IN SAN FRANCISCO THAN ANY OTHER JURISDICTIONS.
MOST OF OUR PROJECTS DON'T QUALIFY FOR SOLAR APP.
I'M IN THE BUILDING CODE SECTION 106 8.1.15.6
INSPECTIONS SAYS THAT ONLY ONE INSPECTION IS REQUIRED FOR
MODESTLY SIZED SOLAR SYSTEMS BEGINNING IN OCTOBER OF 2020.
>> THANK YOU MA'AM, FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND JUST FOR THOSE OF
YOU WHO MIGHT NOT HAVE SPOKEN HERE BEFORE, I JUST WANT TO
DRAW YOUR ATTENTION TO THE CLOCK ON THAT PODIUM.
IT'LL LET YOU KNOW WHERE YOU'RE AT IN YOUR TWO MINUTES.
>> THANK WELCOME. THANK YOU.
GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISOR ZACH LIPTON.
I'M ON THE STEERING COMMITTEE OF STREETS FOR ALL SAN
FRANCISCO. >> MEMBER OF WALK S.F. AND I'M
GLAD TO BE HERE TO SUPPORT SUPERVISOR MAL GARS STREET
SAFETY ACT TRAFFIC SAFETY IS PUBLIC SAFETY.
>> MORE PEOPLE ARE KILLED IN TRAFFIC VIOLENCE THAN
HOMICIDES IN SAN FRANCISCO EVERY SINGLE YEAR.
WE FOCUS A LOT ON THESE FATALITIES RIGHTFULLY BUT I
ALSO WANT TO HIGHLIGHT THE SERIOUS INJURIES EVERY EIGHT
HOURS. SOMEONE IS INJURED BADLY ENOUGH
ON OUR STREETS TO NEED TO BE RUSHED TO THE TRAUMA CENTER AT
S.F. GENERAL. THESE ARE OFTEN DEVASTATING
AND LIFE CHANGING INJURIES AND YET THEY USUALLY GO WITHOUT
A SINGLE MENTION IN THE PRESS AND NO RESPONSE FROM THE CITY.
SO I'M GLAD THAT THIS MEASURE REAFFIRMS THE CITY'S COMMITMENT
TO VISION ZERO. >> WHERE I'M CONCERNED IS THAT
A LOT OF THIS IS NOT NEW. IT'S BEEN THE LAW IN THE CITY
FOR MORE THAN 15 YEARS THAT ANY PUBLIC OR PRIVATE PROJECT ON
THE RIGHT OF WAY HAS TO BE PART OF AN INTERAGENCY PROCESS TO
MAKE SIGNIFICANT STREETSCAPE AND PEDESTRIAN SAFETY
IMPROVEMENTS. THAT'S THE BETTER STREETS
POLICY THIS BOARD ALREADY ENACTED.
>> BUT IN PRACTICE THAT'S WORKED FOR MANY PRIVATE
PROJECTS BUT RARELY EVER HAPPENS FOR PUBLIC PROJECTS.
>> FOR EXAMPLE, THE CITY REPAVED 10TH STREET JUST A
COUPLE OF BLOCKS FROM HERE LAST FALL.
>> UTILITIES GOT UPGRADED, WE GOT NEW PAVEMENT AND THEN THE
CREWS PUT THE STREET RIGHT BACK THE WAY IT WAS AND THE WAY IT
WAS IS IS A SIX LANE WIDE SPEEDWAY TO A RESIDENTIAL
NEIGHBORHOOD WITH AN ELEMENTARY SCHOOL AND THE HUMAN AGENCY
HUMAN SERVICES SERVICE CENTER AND OTHER IMPORTANT CITY
INSTITUTIONS. >> THIS WAS A MISSED
OPPORTUNITY TO MAKE SAFETY IMPROVEMENTS AT VERY LITTLE
COST WHILE THE STREET WAS BEING REPAVED ANYWAY.
AND THAT HAPPENS ROUTINELY AROUND THE CITY.
>> IT SHOULD BE AUTOMATIC TO MAKE THESE PROVEN LIFE SAVING
IMPROVEMENTS WHENEVER A STREET IS BEING REPAVED.
WHY DO WE EVEN HAVE A VISION ZERO TOOL KIT IF WE DON'T USE
IT WHENEVER WE REPAVE OUR STREETS?
>> WHY DID WE SPEND THE TIME AND MONEY TO CREATE A BIKING
AND ROLLING PLAN IF WE DON'T IMPLEMENT IT WHEN STREETS ARE
RENOVATED? I'M THANKFUL FOR SUPERVISOR
MOGHERINI'S LONG TERM LEADERSHIP ON VISION ZERO
AND LOOK FORWARD TO THE INTERAGENCY COORDINATION
IN VITAL SAFETY IMPROVEMENTS THIS MEASURE WILL BRING.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS JEAN LAMB. I LIVE ON 18TH STREET NEAR
GUERRERO AND I'M HERE TO SUPPORT SUPERVISOR MAL GARS
PROPOSAL FOR SAFER STREETS. I'VE BEEN LIVING IN SAN
FRANCISCO FOR 20 YEARS CAR FREE BIKING AND WALKING EVERYWHERE
WHICH IS A WONDERFUL PRIVILEGE. I WAS LOOKING FORWARD TO
GROWING OLD HERE AND BEING ABLE TO BE MOBILE AND I'VE JUST
FOUND IT TO BE INCREASINGLY CHAOTIC, UNORGANIZED
AND DANGEROUS TO WALK AND BIKE HERE TO THE POINT WHERE I
HONESTLY FEEL LIKE I'M GOING TO BE KILLED ON MY BIKE IN THE
BIKE LANE OR ON CROSSING A STREET.
I CAN TELL YOU THAT I ROUTINELY AT INTERSECTIONS SEE CARS STOP
AT A RED LIGHT AND THEN LOOK AROUND AND JUST DRIVE THROUGH
IT OR THEY JUST ROLL THROUGH IT .
>> I SEE CARS ROUTINELY MAKING RIGHT TURNS WHERE THEY COME
RIGHT UP TO THE CROSSWALK AND HOVER AND DOG YOU UNTIL YOU
GET OUT OF THEIR WAY SO THEY CAN MAKE THEIR TURN IN THE BIKE
LANES. >> OF COURSE THERE'S CARS
PARKED IN ALMOST EVERY BLOCK AT SOME TIMES A DAY WITH NO ONE
IN THEM. THERE'S ALL THESE NEW USES NOW
THAT HAVE COME OUT IN RECENT YEARS OF MOTORIZED SCOOTERS
THAT ARE DELIVERING THINGS. THEY'RE SPEEDING IN THE BIKE
LANE, PASSING ON THE RIDE, DOING UNEXPECTED ERRATIC THINGS
. THERE'S STAND UP PEOPLE
STANDING ON SCOOTERS, THERE'S SCOOTERS AND ELECTRIC BIKES ON
THE SIDEWALKS WEAVING AMONG PEOPLE AND SOMETHING NEEDS TO
BE DONE TO ORGANIZE THIS AND MAKE IT SAFER.
AND AS THE GENTLEMAN BEFORE ME SAID, BESIDES THE SHOCKING
STATISTICS OF FATALITIES, IT'S ROUTINELY PEOPLE ARE HIT
AND MAKE ARMED AND INJURED AND PLEASE SUPPORT SUPERVISOR
MEL GARS PROPOSAL. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. WELCOME.
>> HI EVERYONE. MY NAME IS AUDREY.
I'M A RESIDENT OF DISTRICT ONE. I APPRECIATE AND IN IN STRONG
SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR MEL GUY'S RESOLUTION FOR A CITYWIDE
TRAFFIC SAFETY COMMITMENT. NOW MORE THAN EVER OUR CITY
MUST DOUBLE DOWN ON VISION AND OUR VISION ZERO GOALS 2024
HAD THE HIGHEST NUMBER OF TRAFFIC DEATHS IN RECENT MEMORY
WHERE 40 PEOPLE WERE KILLED IN TRAFFIC CRASHES INCLUDING A
72 YEAR OLD NEIGHBOR IN MY NEIGHBORHOOD THE RICHMOND ON
FULTON ON FEBRUARY. AND THIS IS TO SAY NOTHING
ABOUT THE HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE WHO ARE MAIMED EACH YEAR ON OUR
STREETS. >> OF COURSE NOBODY WANTS TO
SEE OUR FELLOW NEIGHBORS KILLED OR HURT.
BUT I HOPE THAT THIS RESOLUTION NOT ONLY GIVES US
ACCOUNTABILITY BUT OUR LEADERS THE POLITICAL COURAGE NEEDED TO
IMPLEMENT THESE CHANGES. WE MUST IMPLEMENT PROVEN
SYSTEMIC SOLUTIONS LIKE COMPLETE STREETS, LOWER SPEED
LIMITS EVEN IN THE FACE OF OPPOSITION.
WHILE POLICE ENFORCEMENT IS IMPORTANT, IT'S NOT A
REPLACEMENT FOR THESE CHANGES. ULTIMATELY WE MUST CHANGE THE
PHYSICAL LAYOUT OF OUR CITY OUR TRAFFIC RULES AND HOW WE GET
AROUND. WE CANNOT ACHIEVE VISION ZERO
WITHOUT THEM. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS CYRUS HALL. I APOLOGIZE IF MY VOICE IS
HOARSE. I NEED WATER TONIGHT I AM
SPEAKING AS A MEMBER OF STREETS FOR ALL SAN FRANCISCO AND THE
STREETS FOR ALL STEERING COMMITTEE STREETS FOR ALL
SUPPORTS THE INTENT AND DIRECTION OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO STREETS SAFETY ACT AND DEEPLY APPRECIATE
SUPERVISOR MEL GA'S LEADERSHIP IN INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION
. AND AS SAN FRANCISCO DISCUSSES
HOW TO MOVE FORWARD ON VISION ZERO, WE WELCOME THE
RESOLUTION'S FOCUS ON A PREVENTATIVE INTER-AGENCY DATA
DRIVEN APPROACH TO ENDING TRAFFIC VIOLENCE.
STREETS FOR ALL RESPECTFULLY URGES THAT THE RESOLUTION OFFER
A CLEAR DIRECTIVE TO IMPLEMENT VISION ZERO SAFETY MEASURES
SUCH AS PROTECTED BIKE LANES DURING REPAVING AND STREET
RECONSTRUCTION PROJECTS ON ALL STREETS.
>> THIS IS CONSISTENT WITH BOTH THE BETTER STREETS PLAN AND THE
CITY'S BIKING AND ROLLING PLAN. WHEN REPAVING, RECONSTRUCTING
OR CONDUCTING OTHER STREET LEVEL WORK ALL RECOMMENDED
SAFETY INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROVEMENTS SHOULD BE DESIGNED
AND CONSTRUCTED. THESE INCLUDE SEPARATED
AND PROTECTED BIKE LANES AS OUTLINED IN THE BIKING
AND ROLLING PLAN AS WELL AS CURB EXTENSIONS AS TRAFFIC
CALMING AND HARDENED DAYLIGHTING.
>> A STRONG RESOLUTION REAFFIRMING THE BOARD'S 2010
DETERMINATIONS AND THE BETTER STREETS PLAN WILL INDICATE
INDICATE CLEAR SUPPORT FOR MULTIPLE USES OF STREETS
INCLUDING SAFE ACTIVE AND AMPLE SPACE FOR PEDESTRIANS, BICYCLES
AND PUBLIC TRANSIT. SAFE STREETS WITH DIVERSE
TRANSPORTATION MODES ARE MORE CONDUCIVE TO DIVERSE PUBLIC
LIFE AND THE EFFICIENT MOVEMENT OF PEOPLE AND GOODS THAN
STREETS DESIGNED PRIMARILY TO MOVE AUTOMOBILES.
LET'S WORK TOGETHER TO DESIGN AND PASS THE STRONGEST
RESOLUTION POSSIBLE. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE. >> HELLO.
>> MY NAME IS EVE CARTER AND I LIVE IN THE RICHMOND DISTRICT.
AND I'M GOING INTO SIXTH GRADE AND OLD ENOUGH TO WALK TO
SCHOOL BY MYSELF. >> I LIVE ALONG CALIFORNIA
STREET AND HAVE TO CROSS IT TO GET TO SCHOOL.
IT'S VERY BUSY. I WOULD LIKE TO THANK MYRNA
MELGAR FOR WHAT SHE IS DOING. IT'LL HELP NOT JUST ME BUT LOTS
AND LOTS OF OTHER PEOPLE IN THE CITY WHO NEED TO GET PLACES
AND FIND IT UNSAFE TO TRY AND CROSS BUSY ROADS OR AREAS
WHERE LIKE THEIR ARE CARS PARKED NEAR THE CROSSING SO
THEY CAN'T SEE AND LIKE YEAH IT'S REALLY ANNOYING WHEN
AND AND THERE'S A ROAD THAT YOU CAN'T CROSS AND HAVE TO AVOID
AND HAVE TO GO THE LONG WAY AROUND.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NICELY DONE. ALL RIGHT.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
THANK YOU. MY NAME IS CHARLOTTE MOONEY.
I'M A RESIDENT OF DISTRICT ONE AND I CANNOT SAY THINGS ANY
BETTER THAN MY DAUGHTER ALREADY SAID.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR INTRODUCING THIS AND I REALLY
ENCOURAGE ALL OF YOU TO ACT ON THIS STREET SAFETY ACT THAT
AFFECTS ALL OF US. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS RICHARD BAUMAN.
I LIVE IN THE RICHMOND DISTRICT.
I'VE LIVED THERE FOR THE PAST 30 YEARS EVER SINCE COVID
STARTED. I'VE NOTICED THREE THINGS.
FIRST OF ALL, THERE ARE MORE PEOPLE WALKING DOGS.
SECONDLY, THERE ARE MORE PEOPLE PUSHING BABY CARRIAGES.
AND THIRD THERE ARE MORE CARS IGNORING STOP SIGNS SPEED ING
AND ENTERING IN CROSSWALKS WHEN PEDESTRIANS ARE IN THE
CROSSWALKS. I DON'T KNOW WHAT HAPPENED
DURING COVID BUT DRIVING GOT CRAZIER AND NOW I'VE NOTICED
IT'S MUCH MUCH MORE DANGEROUS TO WALK AROUND IN THE RICHMOND
DISTRICT. THEREFORE I STRONGLY URGE YOU
TO VOTE TO PASS SUPERCAR SUPERVISOR MEL GUY'S
RESOLUTION. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISOR PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN, I COME TO
YOU AS A SURVIVOR OF TWO COLLISIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> BOTH OF THEM OCCURRED IN CROSSWALKS AS I WAS WALKING
ONE OF THEM 24.5 YEARS AGO AND ONE OF THEM EIGHT WEEKS AGO
WITHIN THE DISTRICT I LIVE ON ON THIS STREET I LIVE ON WHICH
HAS HASTE REACHED. AND WHAT WILL HAPPEN WITH THE
STREET SAFETY ACT IS IT WILL COORDINATE CITY DEPARTMENTS TO
WORK TOGETHER. WHAT WASN'T WORKING THAT DAY
VERY WELL? >> NOT AT ALL IS THE STREET
LIGHT ON WOODEN POLE OVER THE CORNER OF HAYES AND LAGUNA AT
POLE 2667 ONE ONE WAS NOT WORKING AND THE DRIVER SAID WHO
HIT ME AND FILLING OUT THE OFFICERS INQUIRY ON THE TRAFFIC
COLLISION REPORT WHICH IT HAS A SERIAL NUMBER OF 2503157 EIGHT
ZERO. >> HE SAID HE COULDN'T SEE ME.
WELL A CITY MAINTAINED CONSTRUCTED LIGHT POLE THE
LIGHT WASN'T WORKING FOR WEEKS AFTER I WAS OPERATED ON IT.
SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL BY SOME GREAT ORTHOPEDIC DOCTORS I
CALLED 311 AND TWO WEEKS LATER THE LIGHT WAS TURNED ON SO THAT
LIGHT SHOULD HAVE BEEN ALWAYS ON.
>> IF IT'S CITY PROPERTY AND PLEASE THROUGH THE STREET
SAFETY ACT ENSURE THAT WE HAVE COORDINATION FROM ALL THE CITY
DEPARTMENTS TO ENSURE A COLLISION LIKE MINE DOESN'T
HAPPEN AGAIN AND ANYONE ELSE OF THE OTHER ONES THAT HAVE
HAPPENED IN THE MOUNTAIN OF DEATH COLLISION LAST YEAR.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME. NEXT SPEAKER THANK YOU BOARD
PRESIDENT PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ALI GELLER. I WORK FOR THE FAMILIES FOR
SAFE STREETS NATIONAL ORGANIZATION AND I LIVED IN D
ONE A FEW WEEKS AGO MY HUSBAND AND I WERE WALKING ABOUT EIGHT
BLOCKS TO DINNER IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD AND WE WERE ALMOST
HIT THREE SEPARATE TIMES. A DRIVER SPED THROUGH AN
INTERSECTION. A DRIVER BLEW THROUGH A RED
LIGHT. >> A DRIVER BLEW THROUGH A STOP
SIGN. THIS HAS BECOME OUR EVERY
SINGLE DAY AND I AM SO TIRED OF FEELING HEARTSICK AND WORRIED
FOR MYSELF AND MY FAMILY IN THE CITY I LOVE SUPERVISOR MELGAR
THANK YOU FOR INTRODUCING THE STREET SAFETY ACT.
>> SUCH MEASURES MEASURES AS STREAMLINING SAFETY PROJECTS,
EXPANDING AUTOMATED ENFORCEMENT ,ADDING HARDENED DAYLIGHTING
TO ALL HIGH INJURY STREETS AND FULLY HARNESSING THE QUICK
BUILD PROGRAM. ABSOLUTELY WILL SAVE LIVES IF
IT IS APPLIED AT SCALE AND PROACTIVELY RATHER THAN
REACTIVELY AFTER PREVENTABLE TRAGEDIES.
EVERYONE IN THIS ROOM HAS PEOPLE WE LOVE AND WORRY ABOUT
THIS RESOLUTION ABSOLUTELY CAN PROTECT OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
STREETS AND LARGER CORRIDORS AS WELL FROM THE RAMPANT SPEED
AND RECKLESSNESS THAT CURRENTLY AND TRAGICALLY ARE INVITED ON
OUR ROADWAYS. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THE HARD
WORK YOU DO AND I REALLY URGE YOU TO HELP US GET THIS PASSED.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER, WELCOME. GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
I SEE THAT YOU'VE HAD A LONG DAY.
>> I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR MORE THAN JUST A CLIMATE
CHAMPION AND REALLY DOING IMPORTANT STUFF.
I'M NOT GOING TO GO INTO THE NUMBER OF MISSED RED LIGHTS
AND NEAR-MISSES WITH DRIVERS. LUCKILY I'VE AVOIDED CLIPPING
ACTUAL PHYSICAL IMPACT BUT IT'S BEEN EXCEEDINGLY CLOSE ON
OCCASION. SO I'M REALLY GLAD TO SEE THE
CALLING OUT THE RESPONSIBILITIES FOR THE
VARIOUS AGENCIES. AND HOPEFULLY THAT WILL HAVE A
SIGNIFICANT IMPACT THAT COORDINATION AMONG AGENCIES IS
CRITICAL TO MAKE THIS HAPPEN. SO JUST THANK YOU AND I'M
LOOKING FORWARD TO SEEING IT MOVE FORWARD AND GETTING ACTION
FROM THE RELEVANT DEPARTMENTS TONIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME.
NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD EVENING.
>> I'M HARRY ROWE AND I'M HOPING TO GIVE YOU A LITTLE
COMIC RELIEF AT LEAST TO EVEN LOOK AT YOU IN PERSON AND SAY
HELLO. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR
TACKLING THIS ONE. HIS SUPER THE VISION ZERO THAT
RAN OUT LAST YEAR NEEDED TO BE REDO REDONE BECAUSE THE TRAFFIC
THING HAS GOTTEN OUT OF HAND. I'VE SEEN LEFT TURNS WHERE
THERE'S MANY LEFT TURN SIGNS. TODAY I WAS ON FULTON STREET AT
25 MILE AN HOUR LIST WHICH STREET I WAS GOING 30 DON'T
TELL THE POLICE AND CARS WERE PASSING ME AND I HAD AN SUV ON
MY BEHIND BECAUSE I WAS GOING TO SLOW AT FIVE MILES OVER THE
SPEED LIMIT. I WAS IN A CROSSWALK THE OTHER
DAY AND AS I WAS CROSSING A CAR THAT WANTED TO MAKE A RIGHT
TURN ON THE RED LIGHT ALL LEGAL BUT PULLS INTO THE CROSSWALK
IN FRONT OF ME TWO FEET AWAY FROM ME.
I HAD TO STOP BACK UP, GO AROUND THE CAR.
>> IT WAS A WAYMO SELF-DRIVING CAR.
I MEAN THEY'RE NOT EVEN PROGRAMED TO PAY ATTENTION.
SO THE CITY HAS GOTTEN REALLY CRAZY.
I'M 80. I'VE BEEN HERE SINCE 70.
THAT'S 50 YEARS. IT'S GOTTEN WORSE AND WORSE
AND WORSE. PLEASE DO EVERYTHING YOU CAN TO
GET IT BACK. LIVING THE REST OF MY LIFE OR
ANYONE HAVING TO BE ON CRUTCHES OR IN A WHEELCHAIR OR IN A
COFFIN IS NOT THE WAY SAN FRANCISCO SHOULD RESPOND TO
WHAT'S GOING ON IN THE TRAFFIC HERE.
>> WE HAD A PERIOD WHERE WE DOUBLED DOWN ON DOUBLE PARKING
A FEW YEARS AGO MAYBE BEFORE SOME OF YOU WERE AROUND
AND THAT WORKED. WE GOT THE DOUBLE PARKING TO
STOP. WHY CAN'T A TRUCK THAT'S
DELIVERING SOMETHING PULL INTO AN EMPTY SPOT SOMEWHERE BECAUSE
THEY DON'T WANT TO WALK EXTRA STEPS SO THEY PARK RIGHT IN THE
STREET AND STOP. SOMETHING'S GOT TO BE DONE.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK ALL OF YOU FOR YOUR JOBS
AND FOR WHAT YOU'RE DOING. >> I KNOW YOU'RE HEARING THIS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD EVENING.
BOARD PRESIDENT MANDEL MEN AND SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS MARTA LINDSEY. I'M THE COMMUNICATIONS DIRECTOR
AT WALK SAN FRANCISCO WHICH ADVOCATES EVERY DAY FOR
PEDESTRIANS IN OUR CITY. I'M HERE TO REALLY, REALLY
THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR INTRODUCING THE STREET SAFETY
ACT TONIGHT. >> I AM LOOKING AT A BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WHO REALLY GETS WHY THIS RESOLUTION IS SO NEEDED.
YOU'VE SUPPORTED SPEED CAMERAS. YOU'VE LEGISLATED FOR
DAYLIGHTING TO BE PAINTED ACROSS YOUR DISTRICT AND YOU'VE
PUSHED FOR THE SPEED TO GET BACK IN THE GAME OF TRAFFIC
ENFORCEMENT. >> I KNOW YOU'RE HEARING FROM
CONSTITUENTS WHO FEEL LIKE IT'S THE WILD WEST OUT THERE AND NO
MATTER WHAT PART OF THE CITY YOU REPRESENT, YOU KNOW THAT
SENIORS AND CHILDREN ARE WAY TOO VULNERABLE GETTING AROUND
AND YOU DO NOT WANT TO GET THAT TEXT OR PHONE CALL SAYING THAT
SOMEONE HAS BEEN KILLED IN YOUR DISTRICT.
>> SUPERVISOR MEL GARS RESOLUTION REAFFIRMS SAN
FRANCISCO'S PRIOR VISION ZERO COMMITMENT TO END SEVERE
AND FATAL CRASHES AND THIS IS CRUCIAL.
WITHOUT THIS FUNDAMENTAL COMMITMENT AS A CITY, TRAFFIC
SAFETY WILL NOT BE PRIORITIZED .
IT'S THAT SIMPLE AND ZERO IS STILL AND ALWAYS WILL BE THE
RIGHT GOAL. SO I REALLY WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR REAFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO AS A
VISION ZERO CITY. >> BUT SUPERVISOR MELGAR
RESOLUTION INCLUDES A LOT MORE AS A SUITE OF TARGETED ACTIONS
FOR KEY AGENCIES TO DO A LOT MORE TO DESIGN AND ENFORCE OUR
STREETS FOR SAFETY. THIS IS EVERYTHING FROM LEADING
INTO AUTOMATED ENFORCEMENT REFORMING THE RESIDENTIAL
TRAFFIC CALMING PROGRAM REQUIRING THAT STREETS ARE LEFT
BETTER THAN THEY WERE FOUND WHEN THEY ARE PAINTED OR PAVED
AND BY BETTER I MEAN A WHOLE LOT SAFER.
AND THERE'S A LOT OF RED TAPE CUTTING SO THAT STREET SAFETY
PROJECTS CAN HAPPEN FASTER BECAUSE WE NEED THEM TO HAPPEN
SO MUCH FASTER. SO WITH THE STREET SAFETY ACT
YOU ALL CAN DO WHAT I KNOW YOU WANT TO DO SAVE LIVES AND SHOW
THAT SAN FRANCISCO CAN LEAD ON AN ISSUE THAT AFFECTS EVERYONE
EVERY DAY IN OUR CITY. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> I LOST MY FOURTH JOB IN SIX MONTHS THIS PAST FRIDAY.
IT'S NEVER A PERFORMANCE ISSUE BUT A DISCRIMINATE TORY ONE I'M
GIVEN LOOKS OF INFERIORITY WHEN OTHERS LEARN I'M ON PROBATION
JUST AS I WILL TODAY OTHERS TO IGNORE THEIR OWN CRIMES BEING
ACTIVELY COMMITTED NO MATTER HOW MINIMAL OR EXTREME TO FACE
NO CONSEQUENCE AS THE ONES WITH MORE MONEY NEVER DO.
WHILE REGULARLY DENYING DUE WAGES AMONG OTHER CRIMES OF
INTENT RATHER THAN OVERREACTION, I WAS TOLD I WAS
ANNOYING THIS WEEKEND I'VE ANNOYED A LOT OF PEOPLE THAT
PERMIT ABUSE AND DISCRIMINATION BUT THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THEM
AND MYSELF IS I DO NOT PERMIT IT NOR DO I REGULARLY ATTEMPT
TO DENY OTHERS THEIR FREEDOMS WHILE CONTINUING TO FORCED
CONTINUING A FORCED EXPERIENCE. THEY NEVER LET YOU ESCAPE TO
ANYONE THAT MIGHT FIND THIS REALITY ANNOYING.
LET YOURSELF UNDERSTAND YOU ARE NO BETTER.
I FIND IT ANNOYING BEING STRANGLED FOR 35 MINUTES
AND HAVING A FEMALE TELLING ME I SHOULD HAVE LEARNED FROM IT.
I FIND IT ANNOYING HAVING TO SPEND FOUR MONTHS IN CUSTODY
FOR TAKING DOWN A CURTAIN STABLE TO THE WALL WITH FECES
ON IT. MY SLUMLORDS CALLED ME A
FREELOADING DRUG ADDICT AS I WAS DENIED DUE WAGES BY TWO
MORE THAT I WON'T TELL YOU THEIR RACE BECAUSE IT'S NOT A
RACE ISSUE THAT MANY OF YOU ATTEMPT TO MAKE EVERY ISSUE
IT'S A DENIAL OF RIGHTS ISSUE MOST OFTEN FORCED BY MANY THAT
DON'T LIVE HERE. BUT PLEASE DON'T DISREGARD I'VE
LONG UNDERSTOOD THERE BEING IN EVERY RACE.
I FIND IT ANNOYING HAVING OTHERS SEEK THE ARREST OF
CITIZENS FOR LEGALLY PROTECTED RIGHTS WHILE THEY SHUT DOWN
BRIDGES FOR FOREIGN LANDS AND WANT TO SAY YOU BUT
ATTEMPT TO HOLD YOU CRIMINALS SHOULD YOU SAY YOU BACK THAT
HAPPENED THIS WEEKEND AND MORE THAN ONE MEMBER OF THE BOARD
HAS USED FOUL LANGUAGE UNABLE TO CONTROL THEIR QUOTE UNQUOTE
UNHINGED BEHAVIOR AS I'M TOLD TO HAVE.
SHOULD I USE THE SAME WORDS WHILE NOT EARNING $160,000 A
YEAR BUT EXPERIENCING CONTINUED DISCRIMINATORY PROSECUTION
AND EXPECTATION? YES, I AM REPEATING MUCH OF THE
SAME BUT THE SAME HAS YET TO CHANGE AS OUR SUICIDE RATE
CONTINUES TO INCREASE. I'M NOT CLAIMING PERFECT ACTION
IN EVERY INSTANCE BUT THAT'S THANK YOU AND OTHER CASES.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND EVEN ATTEMPTED SIR.
THANK YOU MR. SLEEPER TIME'S CONCLUDED IN WHICH THEY USE
THEMSELVES WHILE THEY WIN. >> THANK YOU.
SHAME TO MURDER THE SITTING PRESIDENT AT THE SAME SPACE.
>> THEY DON'T WANT YOU TO SAY THE WORD.
>> THANK YOU, SHANE. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 72
THROUGH 77 YES. >> ITEM 72 THROUGH 77 WERE
INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT REFERENCE TO COMMITTEE.
A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR AN ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION
ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY. ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY
REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER I WOULD LIKE TO SEVER AND AMEND ITEM 73
. >> ANYBODY ELSE?
>> ALL RIGHT. 73 IS SEVERED SO MADAM CLERK,
COULD YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THE REMAINING BALANCE OF THE ITEMS
? >> SUPERVISOR FIELD ARE YOU
SAID 73, RIGHT? YES, CORRECT.
73. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO THEN ON 72, 74, 75, 76 AND 77.
SUPERVISOR ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN RIGHT MANDOLIN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 73 ITEM 73 A RESOLUTION TO
SUPPORT THE GOLDEN STATE VALKYRIES WOMEN'S BASKETBALL
TEAM AND THEIR FIGHT FOR A FAIR COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AGREEMENT
AND EQUAL COMPENSATION IN THE WOMEN'S NATIONAL BASKETBALL
ASSOCIATION. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU
COLLEAGUES. >> I HAVE SOME NON SUBSTANTIVE
AMENDMENTS TO THIS ITEM TO SPECIFY OUR SUPPORT OF THE
VALKYRIES PLAYERS AS THEY ENGAGE IN THEIR NEGOTIATIONS.
>> I NOW MOVE TO AMEND THIS ITEM BY ADDING PLAYERS AFTER
GOLDEN STATE VALKYRIES. >> ON PAGE ONE LINE ONE
AND ONLINE THREE. BY ALSO CHANGING MEMBERS TO A
MEMBER ON PAGE TWO LINE 15 ADDING BETWEEN THE WNBA
AND WNBA PARENTHESES WOMEN'S NATIONAL BASKETBALL PLAYERS
ASSOCIATION AFTER NEGOTIATION ON PAGE TWO, LINE 24 AND ADDING
PLAYERS ON PAGE THREE LINE NINE .
>> IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY MAHMOOD?
COLLEAGUES CAN WE TAKE THAT AMENDMENT WITHOUT OBJECTION
THEN WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AMENDMENT PASSES AND I THINK
THAT WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDED RESOLUTION SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AMENDED RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED
AND THEN MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA
ITEMS? >> NONE TO REPORT, MR.
PRESIDENT. >> RIGHT.
COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
>> YES. TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL ON
BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR THE LATE MR. SCOTT GARVEY.
ALL RIGHT. I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE
END OF OUR AGENDA. MADAM CLERK.
IS THERE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY ALL THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED